<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="gallipoliSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
<title>GALLIPOLI DIARY BY GENERAL SIR IAN HAMILTON, G.C.B.</title>
  
<chapter n="0" heading="PREFACE">PREFACE</chapter>

<entry><p>
On the heels of the South African War came the sleuth-hounds pursuing
the criminals, I mean the customary Royal Commissions. Ten thousand
words of mine stand embedded in their Blue Books, cold and dead as so
many mammoths in glaciers. But my long spun-out intercourse with the
Royal Commissioners did have living issue--my Manchurian and Gallipoli
notes. Only constant observation of civilian Judges and soldier
witnesses could have shown me how fallible is the unaided military
memory or have led me by three steps to a War Diary:--</p>

<p>(1) There is nothing certain about war except that one side won't win.</p>

<p>(2) The winner is asked no questions--the loser has to answer for
everything.</p>

<p>(3) Soldiers think of nothing so little as failure and yet, to the
extent of fixing intentions, orders, facts, dates firmly in their own
minds, they ought to be prepared.</p>

<p>Conclusion:--In war, keep your own counsel, preferably in a note-book.</p>

<p>The first test of the new resolve was the Manchurian Campaign, 1904-5;
and it was a hard test. Once that Manchurian Campaign was over I never
put pen to paper--in the diary sense[1]--until I was under orders for
<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>. Then I bought a note-book as well as a Colt's automatic
(in fact, these were the only two items of special outfit I did buy),
and here are the contents--not of the auto but of the book. Also, from
the moment I took up the command, I kept cables, letters and copies
(actions quite foreign to my natural disposition), having been taught in
my youth by Lord Roberts that nothing written to a Commander-in-Chief,
or his Military Secretary, can be private if it has a bearing on
operations. A letter which may influence the Chief Command of an Army
and, therefore, the life of a nation, may be "Secret" for reasons of
State; it cannot possibly be "Private" for personal reasons.[2]</p>

<p>At the time, I am sure my diary was a help to me in my work. The
crossings to and from <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> gave me many chances of reckoning up
the day's business, sometimes in clear, sometimes in a queer cipher of
my own. Ink stands with me for an emblem of futurity, and the act of
writing seemed to set back the crisis of the moment into a calmer
perspective. Later on, the diary helped me again, for although the
Dardanelles Commission did not avail themselves of my formal offer to
submit what I had written to their scrutiny, there the records were.
Whenever an event, a date and a place were duly entered in their actual
coincidence, no argument to the contrary could prevent them from falling
into the picture: an advocate might just as well waste eloquence in
disputing the right of a piece to its own place in a jig-saw puzzle.
Where, on the other hand, incidents were not entered, anything might
happen and did happen; _vide_, for instance, the curious misapprehension
set forth in the footnotes to pages 59, 60, Vol. II.</p>

<p>So much for the past. Whether these entries have not served their turn
is now the question. They were written red-hot amidst tumult, but
faintly now, and as in some far echo, sounds the battle-cry that once
stopped the beating of thousands of human hearts as it was borne out
upon the night wind to the ships. Those dread shapes we saw through our
periscopes are dust: "the pestilence that walketh in darkness" and "the
destruction that wasteth at noonday" are already images of speech: only
the vastness of the stakes; the intensity of the effort and the grandeur
of the sacrifice still stand out clearly when we, in dreams, behold the
Dardanelles. Why not leave that shining impression as a martial cloak to
cover the errors and vicissitudes of all the poor mortals who, in the
words of Thucydides, "dared beyond their strength, hazarded against
their judgment, and in extremities were of an excellent hope?"</p>

<p>Why not? The tendency of every diary is towards self-justification and
complaint; yet, to-day, personally, I have "no complaints." Would it not
be wiser, then, as well as more dignified, to let the Dardanelles
R.I.P.? The public will not be starved. A Dardanelles library exists---
nothing less--from which three luminous works by Masefield, Nevinson and
<person name="Charles_Callwell">Callwell</person> stand out; works each written by a man who had the right to
write; each as distinct from its fellow as one primary colour from
another, each essentially true. On the top of these comes the Report of
the Dardanelles Commission and the Life of Lord Kitchener, where his
side of the story is so admirably set forth by his intimate friend, Sir
George Arthur. The tale has been told and retold. Every morsel of the
wreckage of our Armada seems to have been brought to the surface. There
are fifty reasons against publishing, reasons which I know by heart. On
the other side there are only three things to be said:--</p>

<p>(1) Though the bodies recovered from the tragedy have been stripped and
laid out in the Morgue, no hand has yet dared remove the masks from
their faces.</p>

<p>(2) I cannot destroy this diary. Before his death Cranmer thrust his own
hand into the flames: "his heart was found entire amidst the ashes."</p>

<p>(3) I will not leave my diary to be flung at posterity from behind the
cover of my coffin. In case anyone wishes to challenge anything I have
said, I must be above ground to give him satisfaction.</p>

<p>Therefore, I will publish and at once.</p>

<p>A man has only one life on earth. The rest is silence. Whether God will
approve of my actions at a moment when the destinies of hundreds of
millions of human beings hung upon them, God alone knows. But before I
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>, and until they know the truth, as it appeared to me at the
time, how can they give that verdict?
                                                         <person name="Ian_Hamilton">IAN HAMILTON</person>.</p>

<p><location town="Dormansland">LULLENDEN FARM,
   DORMANSLAND</location>.
  _April_ 25, 1920.</p>


<p>
LETTER FROM <person name="Albert_d'Amade">GENERAL D'AMADE</person> TO THE AUTHOR</p>

<p>
MON GENERAL,</p>

<p>Dans la guerre Sud Africaine, ensuite en Angleterre, j'avais en
spectateur vecu avec votre armee. Avec elle je souhaitais revivre en
frere d'armes, combattant pour la meme cause.</p>

<p>Les <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> ont realise mon reve. Mais le lecteur ne doit pas
s'attarder avec moi. Lire le recit de celui meme qui a commande: quel
avantage! L'Histoire, comme un fleuve, se charge d'impuretes en
s'eloignent de ses sources. En en remontant le cours, dans votre
Journal, j'ai decouvert les causes de certains effets demeure, pour moi
des enigmes.</p>

<p>Au debut je n'avais pas cru a la possibilite de forcer les <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>
sans l'intervention de l'armee. C'est pour cela que, si la decision
m'eut appartenus et avant d'avoir ete place sous vos ordres, j'avais
songe a debarquer a Adramit, dans les eaux calmes de Mithylene, a courir
ensuite a Brousse et Constantinople, pour y saisir les clefs du detroit.</p>

<p>En presence de l'opiniatre confiance de l'amiral de Robecq j'abaissai
mon pavillion de terrien et l'inclinai devant son autorite de marin
Anglais. Nous fumes conquis par cette confiance.</p>

<p>Notre theatre de guerre de Gallipoli etait tres borne sur le terrain. Ce
front restreint a permis a chacun de vos soldats de vous connaitre.
Autant qu'avec leurs armes, ils combattaient avec votre ardeur de grand
chef et votre inflexible volonte.</p>

<p>Dans le passe ce theatre qui etait la Troade, venait se souder aux
eternels recommencements de l'Histoire.</p>

<p>Dans l'avenir son domaine etait aussi vaste. "Si nos navires avaient pu
franchir les detroits, a dit le Premier Ministre Loyd Georges le 18
decembre 1919 aux Communes, la guerre aurait ete raccourcie de 2 ou 3
ans."</p>

<p>Il y a pire qu'une guerre, c'est une guerre qui se prolonge. Car les
devastations s'accumulent. Le vaincu qui a eu l'habilete de les eviter a
son pays, se donnera, sur les ruines, des manieres de vainqueur. Le
premier but de guerre n'est il pas d'infliger a l'adversaire plus de mal
qu'il ne vous en fait?</p>

<p>Si nous avions atteint Constantinople dans l'ete 1915 c'etait alors
terminer la guerre, eviter la tourmente russe et tous les obstacles
dresses par ce cataclysme devant le retablissement de la paix du monde.
C'etait epargner a nos Patries des milliards de depenses et des
centaines de milliers de deuils.</p>

<p>Que nous n'ayons pas atteint ce but ne saurait etablir qu'il n'ait ete
juste et sage de le poursuivre.</p>

<p>Voila pour quelle cause sont tombes les soldats des <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>.
"Honneur a vous, soldats de <location country="France">France</location> et soldats du Roi! ainsi que vous
les adjuriez en les lancant a l'attaque.</p>

<p>"Morts heroiques! il n'a rien manque a votre gloire, pas meme une
apparence d'oubli. Des triomphes des autres vous n'avez recueilli que
les rayons extremes: ceux qui ont franchi la cime des arcs de triomphe
pour aller au loin, coups egares de la grande gerbe, eclairer vos
tombes.</p>

<p>"Mais 'Ne jugez pas avant le temps.' Le crepuscule eteint, laissez
encore passer la nuit. Vous aurez pour vous le soleil Levant."</p>

<p>Vous, Mon General, vous aurez ete l'ouvrier de cette grande idee, et
l'annonciateur de cette aurore.
                                                      <person name="Albert_d'Amade">Gen. A. d'Amade</person>.</p>

  <p>  <location town="Fronsac">Fronsac,</location>
     Gironde, <location country="France">France</location>.
  22 decembre, 1919.</p>



<p></p>

</entry>


<chapter n="1" heading="THE START">CHAPTER I</chapter>


<entry><p>In the train between Paris and Marseilles, 14th March, 1915._</p>

<p>Neither the Asquith banquet, nor the talk at the Admiralty that midnight
had persuaded me I was going to do what I am actually doing at this
moment. <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> had made no sign nor waved his magic baton. So I just kept as
cool as I could and had a sound sleep.</p>

<p>Next morning, that is the 12th instant, I was working at the Horse
Guards when, about 10 a.m., <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> sent for me. I wondered! Opening the door
I bade him good morning and walked up to his desk where he went on
writing like a graven image. After a moment, he looked up and said in a
matter-of-fact tone, "We are sending a military force to support the
Fleet now at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>, and you are to have Command."</p>

<p>Something in voice or words touched a chord in my memory. We were once
more standing, <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> and I, in our workroom at <location city="Pretoria">Pretoria</location>, having just
finished reading the night's crop of sixty or seventy wires. <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> was
saying to me, "You had better go out to the <location region="Transvaal">Western Transvaal</location>." I asked
no question, packed up my kit, ordered my train, started that night. Not
another syllable was said on the subject. Uninstructed and unaccredited
I left that night for the front; my outfit one A.D.C., two horses, two
mules and a buggy. Whether I inspected the columns and came back and
reported to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> in my capacity as his Chief Staff Officer; or, whether,
making use of my rank to assume command in the field, I beat up de la
Rey in his den--all this rested entirely with me.</p>

<p>So I made my choice and fought my fight at <location town="Roodewal">Roodewal</location>, last strange battle
in the West. That is <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s way. The envoy goes forth; does his best with
whatever forces he can muster and, if he loses;--well, unless he had
liked the job he should not have taken it on.</p>

<p>At that moment <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> wished me to bow, leave the room and make a start as I
In those old <location city="Pretoria">Pretoria</location> days I had known the <location region="Transvaal">Transvaal</location> by heart; the
number, value and disposition of the British forces; the characters of
the Boer leaders; the nature of the country. But my knowledge of the
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> was nil; of the Turk nil; of the strength of our own forces
next to nil. Although I have met <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> almost every day during the past six
months, and although he has twice hinted I might be sent to <location city="Thessaloniki">Salonika</location>;
never once, to the best of my recollection, had he mentioned the word
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>.</p>

<p>I had plenty of time for these reflections as <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, after his one
tremendous remark had resumed his writing at the desk. At last, he
looked up and inquired, "Well?"</p>

  <p>"We have done this sort of thing before, <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person>" I said; "we have run
this sort of show before and you know without saying I am most deeply
grateful and you know without saying I will do my best and that you can
trust my loyalty--but I must say something--I must ask you some
questions." Then I began.</p>

<p><person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> frowned; shrugged his shoulders; I thought he was going to be
impatient, but although he gave curt answers at first he slowly
broadened out, until, at the end, no one else could get a word in
edgeways.[3]</p>

<p>My troops were to be Australians and New Zealanders under <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> (a
friend); strength, say, about 30,000. (A year ago I inspected them in
their own Antipodes and no finer material exists); the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit>,
strength, say 19,000 under <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person>--a slashing man of action; an
acute theorist; the <unit type="division">Royal Naval Division</unit>, 11,000 strong (an excellent
type of Officer and man, under a solid Commander--<person name="Archibald_Paris">Paris</person>); a French
contingent, strength at present uncertain, say, about a Division, under
my old war comrade the chivalrous <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person>, now at Tunis.</p>

<p>Say then grand total about 80,000--probably panning out at some 50,000
rifles in the firing line. Of these the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> are
extras--_division de luxe._</p>

<p><person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> went on; he was now fairly under weigh and got up and walked about
the room as he spoke. I knew, he said, his (<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s) feelings as to the
political and strategic value of the Near East where one clever tactical
thrust delivered on the spot and at the spot might rally the wavering
Balkans. Rifle for rifle, _at that moment_, we could nowhere make as
good use of the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> as by sending it to the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>, where
each of its 13,000 rifles might attract a hundred more to our side of
the war. Employed in <location country="France">France</location> or Flanders the <unit type="division">29th</unit> would at best help to
push back the German line a few miles; at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> the stakes
were enormous. He spoke, so it struck me, as if he was defending himself
in argument: he asked if I agreed. I said, "Yes." "Well," he rejoined,
"You may just as well realize at once that G.H.Q. in <location country="France">France</location> do not
agree. They think they have only to drive the Germans back fifty miles
nearer to their base to win the war. Those are the same fellows who used
to write me saying they wanted no New Army; that they would be amply
content if only the old Old Army and the Territorials could be kept up
to strength. Now they've been down to Aldershot and seen the New Army
they are changing their tune, but I am by no means sure, _now_, that
I'll give it to them. French and his Staff believe firmly that the
British Imperial Armies can pitch their camp down in one corner of
Europe and there fight a world war to a finish. The thing is absurd but
French, plus <location country="France">France</location>, are a strong combine and they are fighting tooth
and nail for the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit>. It must clearly be understood then:--"</p>

<p>(1) That the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> are only to be a loan and are to be returned
the moment they can be spared.</p>

<p>(2) That all things ear-marked for the East are looked on by powerful
interests both at home and in <location country="France">France</location> as having been stolen from the
West.</p>

<p>Did I take this in? I said, "I take it from you." Did I myself, speaking
as actual Commander of the Central Striking Force and executively
responsible for the land defence of <location country="England">England</location>, think the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit>
could be spared at all? "Yes," I said, "and four more Territorial
Divisions as well." <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> used two or three very bad words and added, with
his usual affability, that I would find myself walking about in civilian
costume instead of going to <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> if he found me making any
wild statements of that sort to the politicians. I laughed and reminded
him of my testimony before the Committee of Imperial Defence about my
Malta amphibious manoeuvres; about the <location city="Malta">Malta</location> Submarines and the way
they had destroyed the battleships conveying my landing forces. If there
was any politician, I said, who cared a hang about my opinions he knew
quite well already my views on an invasion of <location country="England">England</location>; namely, that it
would be like trying to hurt a monkey by throwing nuts at him. I didn't
want to steal what French wanted, but now that the rifles had come and
the troops had finished their musketry, there was no need to squabble
over a Division. Why not let French have two of my <unit type="division">Central Force
Territorial Division</unit> at once,--they were jolly good and were wasting
their time over here. That would sweeten French and he and Joffre would
make no more trouble about the <unit type="division">29th</unit>.</p>

<p><person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> glared at me. I don't know what he was going to say when <person name="Charles_Callwell">Callwell</person>
came into the room with some papers.</p>

<p>We moved to the map in the window and <person name="Charles_Callwell">Callwell</person> took us through a plan of
attack upon the Forts at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>, worked out by the Greek
General Staff. The Greeks had meant to employ (as far as I can remember)
150,000 men. Their landing was to have taken place on the North-west
coast of the Southern part of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>, opposite <location heights="Kilid_Bahr">Kilid Bahr</location>. "But,"
said <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, "half that number of men will do you handsomely; the Turks are
busy elsewhere; I hope you will not have to land at all; if you _do_
have to land, why then the powerful Fleet at your back will be the prime
factor in your choice of time and place."</p>

<p>I asked <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> if he would not move the Admiralty to work a submarine or two
up the Straits at once so as to prevent reinforcements and supplies
coming down by sea from <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>. By now the Turks must be on the
alert and it was commonsense to suppose they would be sending some sort
of help to their Forts. However things might pan out we could not be
going wrong if we made the <location sea="Marmora_Sea">Marmora</location> unhealthy for the Turkish ships.
<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> thereupon made the remark that if we could get one submarine into the
<location sea="Marmora_Sea">Marmora</location> the defences of the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> would collapse. "Supposing," he
said, "one submarine pops up opposite the <location town="Gallipoli">town of Gallipoli</location> and waves a
Union Jack three times, the whole Turkish garrison on <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> will
take to their heels and make a bee line for <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>."</p>

<p>In reply to a question about Staff, <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person>, in the gruff voice he puts
on when he wants no argument, told me I could not take my own Chief of
Staff, <person name="Gerald_Ellison">Ellison</person>, and that <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> would go with me in his place.
<person name="Gerald_Ellison">Ellison</person> and I have worked hand in glove for several years; our qualities
usefully complement one another; there was no earthly reason I could
think of why <person name="Gerald_Ellison">Ellison</person> should _not_ have come with me, but; I like
<person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>; he had been on my General Staff for a time in the Southern
Command; he is cheery, popular and competent.</p>

<p><person name="Wolfe_Murray">Wolfe Murray</person>, the Chief of the Imperial General Staff, was then called
in, also <person name="Archibald_Murray">Archie Murray</person>, Inspector of Home Forces, and <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>. This
was the first (apparently) either of the Murrays had heard of the
project!!! Both seemed to be quite taken aback, and I do not remember
that either of them made a remark.</p>

<p><person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> was very nice and took a chance to whisper his hopes he
would not give me too much cause to regret <person name="Gerald_Ellison">Ellison</person>. He only said one
thing to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> and that produced an explosion. He said it was vital that we
should have a better air service than the Turks in case it came to
fighting over a small area like <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location>: he begged,
therefore, that whatever else we got, or did not get, we might be fitted
out with a contingent of up-to-date aeroplanes, pilots and observers. <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>
turned on him with flashing spectacles and rent him with the words,
_"Not one_!"</p></entry>

<entry><p>_15th March, 1915. <location ship="H.M.S._Phaeton">H.M.S. "Phaeton."</location> <location city="Toulon">Toulon Harbour</location>._ Embarked at
Marseilles last night at 6 p.m. and slept on board. Owing to some
mistake no oil fuel had been taken aboard so we have had to come round
here this morning to get it. Have just breakfasted with the Captain,
Cameron by name, and have let the Staff go ashore to see the town. We do
not sail till 2 p.m.: after special trains and everything a clean
chuck-away of 20 hours.</p>

<p>I left off in the S. of S.'s room at the War Office. After the bursting
of the aeroplane bomb <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> did most of the talking. I find it hard to
remember all he said: here are the outstanding points:--</p>

<p>(1) We soldiers are to understand we are string Number 2. The sailors
are sure they can force the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> on their own and the whole
enterprise has been framed on that basis: we are to lie low and to bear
in mind the Cabinet does not want to hear anything of the Army till it
sails through the Straits. But if the Admiral fails, then we will have
to go in.</p>

<p>(2) If the Army has to be used, whether on the <location straits="Bosphorus">Bosphorus</location> or at the
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>, I am to bear in mind his order that no serious operation is
to take place until the whole of my force is complete; ready;
concentrated and on the spot. No piecemeal attack is to be made.</p>

<p>(3) If we do start fighting, once we _have_ started we are to burn our
boats. Once landed the Government are resolved to see the enterprise
through.</p>

<p>(4) Asia is out of bounds. <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> laid special stress on this. Our sea
command and the restricted area of Gallipoli would enable us to
undertake a landing on <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> with clearly limited liabilities.
Once we began marching about continents, situations calling for heavy
reinforcements would probably be created. Although I, Hamilton, seemed
ready to run risks in the defence of London, he, <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, was not, and as he
had already explained, big demands would make his position difficult
with <location country="France">France</location>; difficult everywhere; and might end by putting him (<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>) in
the cart. <location coast="Besika_Bay">Besika Bay</location> and <location city="Alexandreta">Alexandretta</location> were, therefore, taboo--not to be
touched! Even after we force the Narrows no troops are to be landed
along the Asian coastline. Nor are we to garrison any part of the
<location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">Gallipoli Peninsula</location> excepting only the <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location> Lines which had best be
permanently held, <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> thinks, by the <unit type="division">Naval Division</unit>.</p>

<p>When we get into the <location sea="Marmora_Sea">Marmora</location> I shall be faced by a series of big
problems. What would I do? From what quarter could I attack
<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>? How would I hold it when I had taken it? <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> asked me
the questions.</p>

<p>With the mud of prosaic Whitehall drying upon my boots these remarks of
<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s sounded to me odd. But, knowing <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>, and--what was more
to the point at the moment--knowing <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s hatred of hesitation, I managed
to pull myself together so far as to suggest that if the city was weakly
held and if, as he had said, (I forgot to enter that) the bulk of the
Thracian troops were dispersed throughout the Provinces, or else moving
to re-occupy Adrianople, why then, possibly, by a _coup de main_, we
might pounce upon the <location region="Chatalja">Chatalja</location> Lines from the South before the Turks
could climb back into them from the North.<person name="Herbert_Kitchener"> Lord K.</person> made a grimace; he
thought this too chancy. The best would be if we did not land a man
until the Turks had come to terms. Once the Fleet got through the
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>,<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> could not hold out. Modern<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>
could not last a week if blockaded by sea and land. That was a sure
thing; a thing whereon he could speak with full confidence. The Fleet
could lie off out of sight and range of the Turks and with their guns
would dominate the railways and, if necessary, burn the place to ashes.
The bulk of the people were not Osmanli or even Mahomedan and there
would be a revolution at the mere sight of the smoke from the funnels of
our warships. But if, for some cause at present non-apparent, we were
forced to put troops ashore against organized Turkish opposition, then
he advocated a landing on the Asiatic side of the <location straits="Bosphorus">Bosphorus</location> to hold out
a hand to the Russians, who would simultaneously land there from the
Black Sea. He only made the suggestion, for the man on the spot must be
the best judge. Several of the audience left us here, at <person name="Herbert_Kitchener"> Lord K.</person>'s
suggestion, to get on with their work. <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> went on:--</p>

<p>The moment the holding of <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> comes along the French and the
Russians will be very jealous and prickly. Luckily we British have an
easy part to play as the more we efface ourselves at that stage, the
better he, <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, will be pleased. The Army in <location country="France">France</location> have means of making
their views work in high places and pressure is sure to be put on by
them and by their friends for the return of the <unit type="division">29th</unit> and <unit type="division">Naval</unit> Divisions
the moment we bring <location country="Turkey">Turkey</location> to book. Therefore, it will be best in any
case to "let the French and Russians garrison <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> and sing
their hymns in S. Sophia," whilst my own troops hold the railway line
and perhaps <location city="Adrianople">Adrianople</location>. Thus they will be at a loose end and we shall be
free to bring them back to the West; to land them at <location city="Odesa">Odessa</location> or to push
them up the Danube, without weakening the Allied grip on the waterway
linking the Mediterranean with the Black Sea.</p>

<p>This was the essence of our talk: as it lasted about an hour and a half,
I can only have put down about one tenth of it.</p>

<p>At odd times I have been recipient of <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.'s</person> reveries but always,
_always_, he has rejected with a sort of horror the idea of being War
Minister or Commander-in-Chief. Now by an extreme exercise of its ironic
spirit, Providence has made him both.</p>

<p>In pre-war days, when we met in <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> and at <location island="Malta">Malta</location>, <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> made no bones
about what he wanted. He wanted to be Viceroy of India or Ambasssador at
<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>.</p>

<p>I remember very well one conversation we had when I asked him why he
wanted to hang on to great place, and whether he had not done enough
already. He said he could not bear to see <location country="India">India</location> being mismanaged by
nincompoops or our influence in <location country="Turkey">Turkey</location> being chucked out of the window
with both hands: I answered him, I remember, by saying there were only
two things worth doing as Viceroy and they would not take very long. One
was to put a huge import duty on aniline dyes and so bring back the
lovely vegetable dyes of old India, the saffrons, indigoes, madders,
etc.; the other was to build a black marble Taj at Agra opposite the
white and join the two by a silver bridge. I expected to get a rise, but
actually he took the ideas quite seriously and I am sure made a mental
note of them. Anyway, as Viceroy, <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> would have flung the whole vast
weight of India into the scale of this war; he would have poured Army
after Army from East to West. Under <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> India could have beaten <location country="Turkey">Turkey</location>
single-handed; aye, and with one arm tied behind her back. With <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> as
Ambassador at <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> he would have prevented <location country="Turkey">Turkey</location> coming into
the war. There is no doubt of it. Neither <person name="Enver_Pasha">Enver Pasha</person> nor <person name="Talaat_Pasha">Talaat</person> would
have dared to enrage <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, and as for the idea of their deporting him, it
is grotesque. They might have shot him in the back; they could never
have faced him with a war declaration in their hands. As an impresser
of Orientals he is a nonesuch. So we put him into the War Office in the
ways of which he is something of an amateur, with a big prestige and a
big power of drive. Yes, we remove the best experts from the War Office
and pop in <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> like a powerful engine from which we have removed all
controls, regulators and safety valves. Yet see what wonders he has
worked!</p>

<p>Still, he remains, in the War Office sense, an amateur. The Staff left
by French at the W.O. may not have been von Moltke's, but they were <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s
only Councillors. An old War Office hand would have used them. But in no
case, even had they been the best, could <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> have had truck or parley
with any system of decentralization of work--of semi-independent
specialists each running a show of his own. As late (so-called) Chief of
Staff to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> in <location country="South_Africa">South Africa</location>, I could have told them that whatever
work <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> fancies at the moment he must swipe at it, that very moment, off
 his own bat. The one-man show carried on royally in <location country="South_Africa">South Africa</location> and all
the narrow squeaks we had have been completely swallowed up in the final
success; but how will his no-system system work now? Perhaps he may pull
it through; anyway he is starting with a beautifully cleaned slate. He
has surpassed himself, in fact, for I confess even with past experience
to guide me, I did not imagine our machinery could have been so
thoroughly smashed in so short a time. Ten long years of General Staff;
Lyttelton, Nicholson, French, Douglas; where are your well-thought-out
schemes for an amphibious attack on <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>? Not a sign!
<person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> set to work in the Intelligence Branch at once. But beyond
the ordinary text books those pigeon holes were drawn blank. The
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> and <location straits="Bosphorus">Bosphorus</location> might be in the moon for all the military
information I have got to go upon. One text book and one book of
travellers' tales don't take long to master and I have not been so free
from work or preoccupation since the war started. There is no use trying
to make plans unless there is some sort of material, political, naval,
military or geographical to work upon.</p>

<p><person name="Winston_Churchill">Winston</person> had been in a fever to get us off and had ordered a special
train for that very afternoon. My new Staff were doubtful if they could
get fixed up so quickly and <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> settled the matter by saying there was no
need to hustle. For myself, I was very keen to get away. The best plan
to save slips between cup and lip is to swallow the liquor. But <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>
thought it wisest to wait, so I 'phoned over to Eddie to let <person name="Winston_Churchill">Winston</person>
know we should not want his train that day.</p>

<p>Next morning, the 13th, I handed over the Central Force Command to
<person name="Leslie_Rundle">Rundle</person> and then, at 10.30 went in with <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> to say good-bye. <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>
was standing by his desk splashing about with his pen at three different
drafts of instructions. One of them had been drafted by Fitz--I suppose
under somebody's guidance; the other was by young Buckley; the third <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>
was working on himself.<person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, Fitz and I were in the room; no one
else except <person name="Charles_Callwell">Callwell</person> who popped in and out. The instructions went over
most of the ground of yesterday's debate and were too vague. When<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>asked the crucial question:--the enemy's strength? <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> thought I had
better be prepared for 40,000. How many guns? No one knows. Who was in
command? <person name="Djavad_Pasha">Djavad Pasha</person>, it is believed. But, <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> says, I may take it that
the <location heights="Kilid_Bahr">Kilid Bahr Plateau</location> has been entrenched and is sufficiently held.
South of <location heights="Kilid_Bahr">Kilid Bahr Plateau</location> to the point at <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location>, I may take it that the
Peninsula is open to a landing on very easy terms. The cross fire from
the Fleet lying part in the <location sea="Aegean_Sea">Aegean</location> and part in the mouth of the Straits
must sweep that flat and open stretch of country so as to render it
untenable by the enemy.<person name="Herbert_Kitchener"> Lord K.</person> demonstrated this cross fire upon the
map. He toiled over the wording of his instructions. They were headed
"<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> Expeditionary Force." I begged him to alter this to
avert Fate's evil eye. He consented and both this corrected draft and
the copy as finally approved are now in <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> despatch box more
modestly headed "Mediterranean Expeditionary Force." None of the drafts
help us with facts about the enemy; the politics; the country and our
allies, the Russians. In sober fact these "instructions" leave me to my
own devices in the East, almost as much as <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.'s</person> laconic order "git" left
me to myself when I quitted <location city="Pretoria">Pretoria</location> for the West thirteen years ago.</p>

<p>So I said good-bye to old <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> as casually as if we were to meet together
at dinner. Actually my heart went out to my old Chief. He was giving me
the best thing in his gift and I hated to leave him amongst people who
were frightened of him. But there was no use saying a word. He did not
even wish me luck and I did not expect him to, but he did say, rather
unexpectedly, _after_ I had said good-bye and just as I was taking up my
cap from the table, "If the Fleet gets through, <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> will fall
of itself and you will have won, not a battle, but the war."</p>

<p>At 5 o'clock that afternoon we bade adieu to <location city="London">London</location>. <person name="Winston_Churchill">Winston</person> was
disappointed we didn't dash away yesterday but we have not really let
much grass grow under our feet. He and some friends came down to Charing
Cross to see us off. I told <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person> <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> would not think me loyal if
I wrote to another Secretary of State. He understood and said that if I
"You will agree perhaps that the <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">First Lord</person> should see." Then the S. of
S. for War would be bound to show him the letter:--which proves that
with all his cleverness <person name="Winston_Churchill">Winston</person> has yet some points to learn about his
K. of K.!</p>

<p>My Staff still bear the bewildered look of men who have hurriedly been
snatched from desks to do some extraordinary turn on some unheard of
theatre. One or two of them put on uniform for the first time in their
lives an hour ago. Leggings awry, spurs upside down, belts over shoulder
straps! I haven't a notion of who they all are: nine-tenths of my few
hours of warning has been taken up in winding up the affairs of the
Central Force.</p>

<p>At <location city="Dover">Dover</location> embarked on <location ship="H.M.S._Foresight">H.M.S. _Foresight_</location>,--a misnomer, for we ran into a
fog and had to lie-to for a devil of a time. Heard far-off guns on
French front,--which was cheering.</p>

<p>At 10.30 p.m. we left <location city="Calais">Calais</location> for <location city="Marseilles">Marseilles</location> and during the next day the
French authorities caused me to be met by Officers of their Railway
Mobilization Section. Had my first breathing space wherein to talk over
matters with <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, and <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">he</person> and I tried to piece together the
various scraps of views we had picked up at the War Office into a
pattern which should serve us for a doctrine. But we haven't got very
much to go upon. A diagram he had drawn up with half the spaces unfilled
showing the General Staff. Another diagram with its blank spaces only
showed that our Q. branch was not in being. Three queried names,
<person name="Gen.Woodward">Woodward</person> for A.G., Winter for Q.M.G. and <person name="Col.Williams">Williams</person> for Cipher Officer.
The first two had been left behind, the third was with us. The following
hurried jottings by <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>:--"Only 1600 rounds for the 4.5
Howitzers!!! High Explosive essential. Who is to be C.R.E.? Engineer
Stores? French are to remain at <location country="Tunis">Tunis</location> until the day comes that they are
required. Egyptian troops also remain in <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> till last moment.
Everything we want by 30th (it is hoped). Await arrival of <unit type="division">29th Division</unit>
before undertaking anything big. If <person name="Sackville_Carden">Carden</person> wants military help it is for
<person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian's</person> consideration whether to give or to withhold it." These rough
notes; the text book on the Turkish Army, and two small guide books: not
a very luminous outfit. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> tells me our force are not to take
with them the usual 10 per cent. extra margin of reserves to fill
casualties. Wish I had realised this earlier. He had not time to tell
me he says. The General Staff thought we ought certainly to have these
and <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">he</person> and <person name="Wolfe_Murray">Wolfe Murray</person> went in and made a personal appeal to the A.G.
But <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">he</person> was obdurate. This seems hard luck. Why should we not have our
losses quickly replaced--supposing we do lose men? I doubt though, if I
should have been able to do very much even if I had known. To press <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>
would have been difficult. Like insisting on an extra half-crown when
you've just been given Fortunatus' purse. Still, fair play's a jewel,
and surely if formations destined for the French front cross the Channel
with 10 per cent. extra, over and above their establishment, troops
bound for <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> ought to have a 25 per cent. margin over
establishment?</p></entry>

<entry><p>_17th March, 1915. <location ship="H.M.S._Phaeton">H.M.S. "Phaeton."</location> At sea._ Last night we raced past
<location island="Corfu">Corfu</location>--my birthplace--at thirty knots an hour. My first baby breath was
drawn from these thyme scented breezes. This crimson in the Eastern sky,
these waves of liquid opal are natal, vital.</p>

<p>Thirty miles an hour through Paradise! Since the 16th January, 1853, we
have learnt to go the pace and as a result the world shrinks; the
horizons close in upon us; the spacious days are gone!</p>

<p>Thoughts of my <person name="Corinna_Hamilton">Mother</person>, who died when I was but three. Thoughts of her
refusal as she lay dying--gasping in mortal pain--her refusal to touch
an opiate, because the Minister, Norman Macleod, had told her she so
might dim the clearness of her spiritual insight--of her thoughts
ascending heavenwards. What pluck--what grit--what faith--what an
example to a soldier.</p>

<p>Exquisite, exquisite air; sea like an undulating carpet of blue velvet
outspread for Aphrodite. Have been in the <location sea="Aegean_Sea">Aegean</location> since dawn. At noon
passed a cruiser taking back <person name="Sackville_Carden">Admiral Carden</person> invalided to <location island="Malta">Malta</location>. One week
ago the thunder of his guns shook the firm foundations of the world. Now
a sheer hulk lies poor old <person name="Sackville_Carden">Carden</person>. _Vanitas vanitatum_.</p>

<p>Have got into touch with my staff. They are all General Staff: no
Administrative Staff. The Adjutant-General-to-be (I don't know him) and
the Chief Medico (I don't know who he is to be) could not get ready in
time to come off with us, and the Q.M.G., too, was undecided when I
Quite characteristic of <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, though, that barring <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, not one of
the associates he has told off to work hand in glove with me in this
enterprise should ever have served with me before.</p>

<p>Only two sorts of Commanders-in-Chief could possibly find time to
scribble like this on their way to take up an enterprise in many ways
unprecedented--a German and a Britisher. The first, because every
possible contingency would have been worked out for him beforehand; the
second, because he has nothing--literally nothing--in his portfolio
except a blank cheque signed with those grand yet simple words--John
Bull. The German General is the product of an organising nation. The
British General is the product of an improvising nation. Each army would
be better commanded by the other army's General. Sounds fantastic but is
true.[4]</p></entry>

  


<chapter n="2" heading="THE STRAITS">CHAPTER II</chapter>


<entry><p>
Cast anchor at <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location> at 3 p.m., 17th March, 1915, having entered the
harbour at the very same instant as le <person name="Albert_d'Amade">general d'Amade</person>.</p>

<p>Hurried over at once to a meeting aboard that lovely sea monster, <location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">H.M.S.
_Queen Elizabeth_</location>.</p>

<p>Present:--</p>

<p>  <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral de Robeck</person>,
  <person name="Roger_Keyes">Commodore Roger Keyes</person>,
  <person name="Emile_Guepratte">Admiral Guepratte</person>, cmdg. French Fleet,
  <person name="Albert_d'Amade">General d'Amade</person>,
  <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">General Braithwaite</person>,
  <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral Wemyss</person>,
  <person name="Peter_Pollen">Captain Pollen</person>,
  <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Myself</person>.</p>

<p><person name="John_de_Robeck">De Robeck</person> greeted me in the friendliest fashion. He is a fine looking
man with great charm of manner. After a word or two to <person name="Albert_d'Amade"> d'Amade</person> and being
introduced to <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral Wemyss</person>, <person name="Emile_Guepratte">Guepratte</person> and <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>, we sat down round a table and
the <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral</person> began. His chief worry lies in the clever way the enemy are
now handling their mobile artillery. He can silence the big fortress
ordnance, but the howitzers and field guns fire from concealed
positions and make the clearing of the minefields something of a V.C.
sort of job for the smaller craft. Even when the Fleet gets through,
these moveable guns will make it very nasty for store ships or
transports which follow. The mine-sweepers are slow and bad with worn
out engines. Some of the civilian masters and crews of the trawlers have
to consider wives and kids as well as V.C.s. The problem of getting the
Fleet through or of getting submarines through is a problem of clearing
away the mines. With a more powerfully engined type of mine-sweeper and
regular naval commanders and crews to man them, the business would be
easy. But as things actually stand there is real cause for anxiety as to
mines.</p>

<p>The Peninsula itself is being fortified and many Turks work every night
on trenches, redoubts and entanglements. Not one single living soul has
been seen, since the engagement of our Marines at the end of February,
although each morning brings forth fresh evidences of nocturnal
activity, in patches of freshly turned up soil. All landing places are
now commanded by lines of trenches and are ranged by field guns and
howitzers, which, thus far, cannot be located as our naval seaplanes are
too heavy to rise out of rifle range. There has been a muddle about
these seaplanes. Nominally they possess very powerful Sunbeam engines;
actually the d----d things can barely rise off the water. The naval
guns do not seem able to knock the Turkish Infantry out of their deep
trenches although they can silence their fire for awhile. This was
proved at that last landing by Marines. The Turkish searchlights are
both fixed and mobile. They are of the latest pattern and are run by
skilled observers. He gave us, in fact, to understand that German
thoroughness and forethought have gripped the old go-as-you-please Turk
and are making him march to the _Parade-schritt_.</p>

<p>The <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral</person> would prefer to force a passage on his own, and is sure he
can do so. Setting <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> on one side for the moment, _if_ the
Fleet gets through and the Army _then_ attacks at <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>, we would have
the Turkish Army on <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> in a regular trap. Therefore, whether
from the local or the larger point of view, he has no wish to call us in
until he has had a real good try. He means straightway to put the whole
proposition to a practical test.</p>

<p>His views dovetail in to a hair's breadth with <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s views. The <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral's</person>
"real good try" leads up towards <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s "after every effort has been
exhausted."</p>

<p>That's a bit of luck for our kick-off, anyway. What we soldiers have to
do now is to hammer away at our band-o-bast[5] whilst the Navy pushes as
hard, as fast and as far as its horsepower, manpower and gunpower will
carry it.</p>

<p>The <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral</person> asked to see my instructions and <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> read them out.
When he stopped, <person name="Roger_Keyes">Roger Keyes, the Commodore</person>, inquired, "Is that all?"
And when <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> confessed that it was, everyone looked a little
blank.</p>

<p>Asked what I meant to do, I said I proposed to get ready for a landing,
as, whether the Fleet forces the passage and disembarked us on the
<location straits="Bosphorus">Bosphorus</location>; or, whether the Fleet did not force the passage and we had to
"go for" <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>, the _band-o-bast_ could be made to suit either
case.</p>

<p>The <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral</person> asked if I meant to land at <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>? I replied my mind was
open on that point: that I was a believer in seeing things for myself
and that I would not come to any decision on the map if it were possible
to come to it on the ground. He then said he would send me up to look at
the place through my own glasses in the <location ship="H.M.S._Phaeton">Phaeton</location> to-morrow; that it would
not be possible to land large forces on the neck of <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location> itself as
there were no beaches, but that I should reconnoitre the coast at the
head of the Gulf as landing would be easier with every few miles we drew
away towards the North. I told him it would be useless to land at any
distance from my objective, for the simple reason that I had no
transport, mechanical or horse, wheeled or pack, to enable me to support
myself further than five or six miles from the Fleet and it would take
many weeks and many ships to get it together; however, I ended, I would
to-morrow see for myself.</p>

<p>The air of the <location sea="Aegean_Sea">Aegean</location> hardly differs so much from the <location sea="North_Sea">North Sea</location> haze as
does the moral atmosphere of <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location> differ from that of the War Office.
This is always the way. Until the plunge is taken, the man in the arm
chair clamps rose coloured spectacles on to his nose and the man on the
spot is anxious; _but_, once the men on the spot jump off they become
as jolly as sandboys, whilst the man in the arm chair sits searching for
a set-back with a blue lens telescope.</p>

<p>Here, <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> looks a tougher nut to crack than it did on <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person>'s
small and featureless map. I do not speak for myself for I have so far
only examined the terrain through a field glass. I refer to the tone of
the sailors, which strikes me as being graver and less irresponsible
than the tone of the War Office.</p>

<p>The <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral</person> believes that, at the time of the first bombardment, 5000
men could have marched from <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location> right up to the <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location> lines.
(Before leaving the ship I learnt that some of the sailors do not
agree). Now that phase has passed. Many more troops have come down,
German Staff Officers have grappled with the situation, and have got
their troops scientifically disposed and heavily entrenched. This
skilful siting of the Turkish trenches has been admired by all competent
British observers; the number of field guns on <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> is now many
times greater than it was.</p>

<p>After this the discussion became informal. Referring again to my
instructions, I laid stress on the point that I was a waiting man and
that it was the <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral's</person> innings for so long as he could keep his
wicket up.<person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> asked a question or two about the trenches and
all of us deplored the lack of aeroplanes whereby we were blinded in our
attack upon an enemy who espied every boat's crew moving over the
water.</p>

<p>The more I revolve these matters in my mind, the more easy does it seem
to accept <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s order not to be in too great a hurry to bring the Army to
the front. I devoutly hope indeed (and I think the fiercest of our
fellows agree) that the Navy will pull us out the chestnuts from the
fire.</p>

<p>At the close of the sitting I made these notes of what had happened and
drafted a first cable to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person>, giving him an epitome of the <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral's</person>
opening statement about the enemy's clever use of field guns to hinder
the clearing of the minefields; his good entrenchments and the nightly
work thereon; our handicap in all these matters because the type of
seaplanes sent us "are too heavy to rise out of effective rifle
range"--(one has to put these things mildly). I add that the <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral</person>,
"while not making light of dangers was evidently determined to exhaust
every effort before calling upon the soldiers for their help on a large
scale"; and I wind up by telling him <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location> seems a bad base and that I
am off to-morrow on an inspection of the coasts of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>. Having
got these matters off my chest on to the chest of <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, was then taken
round the ship by the Flag Captain, G.P.W. Hope. By this time it was
nearly 7 so I stayed and dined with the <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral</person>--a charming host. After
dinner got back here.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_18th March, 1915._ <location ship="H.M.S._Phaeton">_H.M.S. "Phaeton."_</location> Cleared <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location> Harbour at 4
a.m. and reached <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location> at 6 a.m. I never saw so many ships collected
together in my life; no, not even at <location city="Hong-Kong">Hong Kong</location>, <location city="Bombay">Bombay</location> or <location city="New-York">New York</location>.
Filled up with oil fuel and at 7 a.m. <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person> and Major-General <person name="Archibald_Paris">Paris</person>,
commanding the <unit type="division">Royal Naval Division</unit>, came on board with one or two Staff
Officers. After consulting these Officers as well as <person name="Ewan_McLagan">McLagan, the
Australian Brigadier</person>, cabled <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> to say <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> _must_ be our
base as "the <unit type="division">Naval Division</unit> transports have been loaded up as in peace
time and they must be completely discharged and every ship reloaded," in
war fashion. At <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>, where there are neither wharfs, piers, labour
nor water, the thing could not be done. Therefore, "the closeness of
<location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location> to the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>, as implying the rapid transport of troops, is
illusory."</p>

<p>The moment I got this done, namely, at 8.30 a.m., we worked our way out
of the long narrow neck of <location coast="Mudros_Harbour">Mudros Harbour</location> and sailed for the <location coast="Saros_Gulf">Gulf of
Saros</location>. Spent the first half of the sixty mile run to the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> in
scribbling. Wrote my first epistle to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, using for the first time the
formal "Dear <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord Kitchener</person>." My letters to him will have to be formal,
and dull also, as he may hand them around. I begin, "I have just sent
you off a cable giving my first impressions of the situation, and am now
steaming in company with Generals <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person> and <person name="Archibald_Paris">Paris</person> to inspect the
North-western coast of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location>." I tell him that the
real place "looks a much tougher nut to crack than it did over the
map,"--I say that his "impression that the ground between <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location>
and <location town="Krithia">Krithia</location> was clear of the enemy," was mistaken. "Not a bit of it." I
say, "The <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral</person> tells me that there is a large number of men tucked
away in the folds of the ground there, not to speak of several field
Batteries." Therefore, I conclude, "If it eventually becomes necessary
to take <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location> by military force, we shall have to
proceed bit by bit." This will vex him no doubt. He likes plans to move
as fast as his own wishes and is apt to forget, or to pretend he has
forgotten, that swiftness in war comes from slow preparations. It is
fairer to tell <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> this now, when the question has not yet arisen, than
hereafter if it does then arise.</p>

<p>Passing the mouth of the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> we got a wonderful view of the
stage whereon the Great Showman has caused so many of his amusing
puppets to strut their tiny hour. For the purpose it stands matchless.
No other panorama can touch it. There, Hero trimmed her little lamp;
yonder the amorous breath of Leander changed to soft sea form. Far away
to the Eastwards, painted in dim and lovely hues, lies Mount Ida. Just
so, on the far horizon line she lay fair and still, when Hector fell and
smoke from burning Troy blackened the mid-day sun. Against this
enchanted background to deeds done by immortals and mortals as they
struggled for ten long years five thousand years ago,--stands forth
formidably <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>. Glowing with bright, springtime colours it
sweeps upwards from the sea like the glacis of a giant's fortress.</p>

<p>So we sailed on Northwards, giving a wide berth to the shore. When we
got within a mile of the head of the <location coast="Saros_Gulf">Gulf of Saros</location>, we turned, steering
a South-westerly course, parallel to, and one to two miles distant from,
the coastline. Then my first fears as to the outworks of the fortress
were strengthened. The head of the <location coast="Saros_Gulf">Gulf</location> is filled in with a horrible
marsh. No landing there. Did we land far away to the Westward we must
still march round the marsh, or else we must cross it on one single road
whose long and easily destructible bridges we could see spanning the bog
holes some three miles inland. Opposite the fortified lines we stood in
to within easy field gun range, trusting that the Turks would not wish
prematurely to disclose their artillery positions. So we managed a peep
at close quarters, and were startled to see the ramifications and extent
of the spider's web of deep, narrow trenches along the coast and on
either front of the lines of <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>. My Staff agree that they must have
taken ten thousand men a month's hard work from dark to dawn. In advance
of the trenches, Williams in the crow's nest reported that with his
strong glasses he could pick out the glitter of wire over a wide expanse
of ground. To the depth of a mile the whole Aegean slope of the neck of
<location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> was scarred with spade work and it is clear to a tiro that
to take these trenches would take from us a bigger toll of ammunition
and life than we can afford: especially so seeing that we can only see
one half of the theatre; the other half would have to be worked out of
sight and support of our own ships and in view of the Turkish Fleet.
Only one small dent in the rockbound coast offered a chance of landing
but that was also heavily dug in. In a word, if <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location> had been the only
way open to me and I had no alternative but to take it or wash my hands
of the whole business, I should have to go right about turn and cable
my master he had sent me on a fool's errand.</p>

<p>Between <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location> and <location coast="Suvla_Bay">Suvla Bay</location> the coastline was precipitous; high cliffs
and no sort of creeks or beaches--impracticable. <location coast="Suvla_Bay">Suvla Bay</location> itself seems
a fine harbour but too far North were the aim to combine a landing there
together with an attack on the Southern end of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>. Were we,
on the other hand, to try to work the whole force ashore from <location coast="Suvla_Bay">Suvla Bay</location>,
the country is too big; it is the broadest part of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>; also,
we should be too far from its waist and from the Narrows we wish to
dominate. Merely to hold our line of Communications we should need a
couple of Divisions. All the coast between <location coast="Suvla_Bay">Suvla Bay</location> and for a little
way South of <location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location> seems feasible for landing. I mean we could get
ashore on a calm day if there was no enemy. <location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location> itself would be
ideal, but, alas, the Turks are not blind; it is a mass of trenches and
wire. Further, it must be well under fire of guns from <location heights="Kilid Bahr">Kilid Bahr plateau</location>
, and is entirely commanded by the high ridge to the North of it.
To land there would be to enter a defile without first crowning the
heights.</p>

<p>Between <location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location> and <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location>, the point of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>, the
coastline consists of cliffs from 100 to 300 feet high. But there are,
in many places, sandy strips at their base. Opinions differ but I
in going for at least one spot that _seems_ impracticable.</p>

<p>Sailing Southwards we are becoming more and more conscious of the
tremendous bombardment going on in the Straits. Now and then, too, we
can see a huge shell hit the top of <location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi Baba</location> and turn it into the
semblance of a volcano. Everyone excited and trying to look calm.</p>

<p>At 4 p.m., precisely, we rounded <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location>. I had promised <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>
not to take his fastest cruiser, fragile as an egg, into the actual
Straits, but the Captain and the Commander (<person name="John_Cameron">Cameron</person> and <person name="Comr_Rosomore">Rosomore</person>), were
frightfully keen to see the fight, and I thought it fair to allow one
mile as being the _mouth_ of the Straits and not _the_ Straits. Before
we had covered that mile we found ourselves on the outskirts of--dream
of my life--a naval battle! Nor did the reality pan out short of my
hopes. Here it was; we had only to keep on at thirty knots; in one
minute we should be in the thick of it; and who would be brave enough to
cry halt!</p>

<p>The world had gone mad; common sense was only moonshine after all; the
elephant and the whale of Bismarckian parable were at it tooth and nail!
Shells of all sizes flew hissing through the skies. Before my very eyes,
the graves of those old Gods whom Christ had risen from the dead to
destroy were shaking to the shock of Messrs. Armstrong's patent thunder
bolts!</p>

<p>Ever since the far-away days of <location country="Afghanistan">Afghanistan</location> and Majuba Hill friends have
been fond of asking me what soldiers feel when death draws close up
beside them. Before he charged in at <location town="Edgehill">Edgehill</location>, <person name="Robert_Astley">Astley</person> (if my memory
serves me) exclaimed, "O, God, I've been too busy fixing up this battle
to think much about you, but, for Heaven's sake, don't you go and
forget about me," or words to that effect.</p>

<p>The Yankee's prayer for fair play just as he joined issue with the
grizzly bear gives another glimpse of these secrets between man and his
Maker. As for myself, there are two moments; one when I think I would
not miss the show for millions; another when I think "what an ass I am
to be here"; and between these two moments there _is_ a border land when
the mind runs all about Life's workshop and tries to do one last bit of
stock-taking.</p>

<p>But the process can no more be fixed in the memory than the sequence of
a dream when the dew is off the grass. All I remember is a sort of
wonder:--why these incredible pains to seek out an amphibious battle
ground whereon two sets of people who have no cause of quarrel can blow
one another to atoms? Why are these Straits the cockpit of the world?
What is it all about? What on earth has happened to sanity when the
whale and elephant are locked in mortal combat making between them a
picture which might be painted by one of H.M.'s Commissioners in Lunacy
to decorate an asylum for homicides.</p>

<p>Whizz--flop--bang--what an ass I am to be here. If we keep on another
thirty seconds we are in for a visit to Davy Jones's Locker.</p>

<p>Now above the <location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">_Queen Elizabeth_</location>, making slowly backwards and forwards up
in the neck of the Narrows, were other men-o'-war spitting tons of hot
metal at the Turks. The Forts made no reply--or none that we could make
out, either with our ears or with glasses. Perhaps there was an attempt;
if so, it must have been very half-hearted. The enemy's fixed defences
were silenced but the concealed mobile guns from <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> and from
Asia were far too busy and were having it all their own way.</p>

<p>Close to us were steam trawlers and mine-sweepers steaming along with
columns of spray spouting up close by them from falling field gun
shells, with here and there a biggish fellow amongst them, probably a
five or six inch field howitzer. One of them was in the act of catching
a great mine as we drew up level with her. Some 250 yards from us was
the <location ship="H.M.S._Inflexible">_Inflexible_</location> slowly coming out of the Straits, her wireless cut away
and a number of shrapnel holes through her tops and crow's nest.
Suddenly, so quickly did we turn that, going at speed, the decks were at
an angle of 45 deg. and several of us (<person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person> for one) narrowly escaped
slipping down the railless decks into the sea. The <location ship="H.M.S._Inflexible">_Inflexible_</location> had
signalled us she had struck a mine, and that we must stand by and see
her home to <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location>. We spun round like a top (escaping thereby a salvo
of four from a field battery) and followed as close as we dared.</p>

<p>My blood ran cold--for sheer deliberate awfulness this beat everything.
We gazed spellbound: no one knew what moment the great ship might not
dive into the depths. The pumps were going hard. We fixed our eyes on
marks about the water line to see if the sea was gaining upon them or
not. She was very much down by the bows, that was a sure thing. Crew and
stokers were in a mass standing strictly at attention on the main deck.
A whole bevy of destroyers crowded round the wounded warrior. In the
sight of all those men standing still, silent, orderly in their ranks,
facing the imminence of death, I got my answer to the hasty moralizings
about war, drawn from me (really) by a regret that I would very soon be
drowned. On the deck of <location ship="H.M.S._Inflexible">that battleship</location> staggering along at a stone's
throw was a vindication of war in itself; of war, the state of being,
quite apart from war motives or gains. Ten thousand years of peace would
fail to produce a spectacle of so great virtue. Where, in peace,
passengers have also shown high constancy, it is because war and martial
discipline have lent them its standards. Once in a generation a
mysterious wish for war passes through the people. Their instinct tells
them that _there is no other way_ of progress and of escape from habits
that no longer fit them. Whole generations of statesmen will fumble over
reforms for a lifetime which are put into full-blooded execution within
a week of a declaration of war. There is _no other way_. Only by intense
sufferings can the nations grow, just as the snake once a year must with
anguish slough off the once beautiful coat which has now become a strait
jacket.</p>

<p>How was it going to end? How touching the devotion of all these small
satellites so anxiously forming escort? Onwards, at snail's pace, moved
our cortege which might at any moment be transformed into a funeral
affair, but slow as we went we yet went fast enough to give the go-by
to the <location ship="F.S._Gaulois">French battleship _Gaulois_</location>, also creeping out towards <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location> in
a lamentable manner attended by another crowd of T.B.s and destroyers
eager to stand to and save.</p>

<p>The <location ship="H.M.S._Inflexible">_Inflexible_</location> managed to crawl into <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location> under her own steam but
we stood by until we saw the <location ship="F.S._Gaulois">_Gaulois_</location> ground on some rocks called
<location island="Rabbit_Island">Rabbit Island</location>, when I decided to clear right out so as not to be in the
way of the Navy at a time of so much stress. After we had gone ten miles
or so, the <location ship="H.M.S._Phaeton">_Phaeton_</location> intercepted a wireless from the <location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">_Queen Elizabeth_</location>,
ordering the <location ship="H.M.S._Ocean">_Ocean_</location> to take the <location ship="H.M.S._Irresistible">_Irresistible_</location> in tow, from which it
would appear that <location ship="H.M.S._Irresistible">she (the _Irresistible_)</location> has also met with some
misfortune.</p>

<p>Thank God we were in time! That is my dominant feeling. We have seen a
spectacle which would be purchased cheap by five years of life and, more
vital yet, I have caught a glimpse of the forces of the enemy and of
their Forts. What with my hurried scamper down the Aegean coast of the
Peninsula and the battle in the Straits, I begin to form some first-hand
notion of my problem. More by good luck than good guidance I have got
into personal touch with the outer fringes of the thing we are up
against and that is so much to the good. But oh, that we had been here
earlier! <person name="Winston_Churchill">Winston</person> in his hurry to push me out has shown a more soldierly
grip than those who said there was no hurry. It is up to me now to
revolve to-day's doings in my mind; to digest them and to turn myself
into the eyes and ears of the War Office whose own so far have
certainly not proved themselves very acute. How much better would I be
able to make them see and hear had I been out a week or two; did I know
the outside of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> by heart; had I made friends with the
Fleet! And why should I not have been?</p>

<p>Have added a P.S. to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s letter:--</p>

<p>"Between <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location> and <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>. 6 p.m.--This has been a very bad day for us
judging by what has come under my own personal observation. After going
right up to <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location> and down again to the South-west point looking at the
network of trenches the Turks have dug commanding all possible landing
places, we turned into the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> themselves and went up about a
mile. The scene was what I believe Naval writers describe as 'lively.'"
(Then follows an account based on my Diary jottings). I end:</p>

<p>"I have not had time to reflect over these matters, nor can I yet
realise on my present slight information the extent of these losses.
Certainly it looks at present as if the Fleet would not be able to carry
on at this rate, and, if so, the soldiers will have to do the trick.":</p>

<p>"Later.</p>

<p>"The <location ship="H.M.S._Irresistible">_Irresistible_</location>, the <location ship="H.M.S._Ocean">_Ocean_</location> and the <location ship="F.S._Bouvet">_Bouvet_</location> are gone! The
<location ship="F.S._Bouvet">_Bouvet_</location>, they say, just slithered down like a saucer slithers down in a
bath. The <location ship="H.M.S._Inflexible">_Inflexible_</location> and the <location ship="F.S._Gaulois">_Gaulois_</location> are badly mauled."</p></entry>

<entry><p>_19th March, 1915._ <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">_H.M.S. "Franconia</location>."_--Last night I left <location ship="H.M.S._Phaeton">H.M.S.
_Phaeton_</location> and went on board the <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">_Franconia_</location>. To-day, we have been busy
fixing things up. The chance sailors, seen by the Staff, have been using
highly coloured expletives about the mines. Sheer bad luck they swear;
bad luck that would not happen once in a hundred tries. They had knocked
out the Forts, they claim, and one, three-word order, "Full steam
ahead," would have cut the Gordian Knot the diplomats have been fumbling
at for over a hundred years by slicing their old <location country="Turkey">Turkey</location> in two. Then
came the big delay owing to ships changing stations during which mines
set loose from up above had time to float down the current, when, by the
Devil's own fluke, they impinge upon our battleships, and blow <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>
and his plans into the middle of next week--or later! These are
ward-room yarns. <person name="John_de_Robeck">De Robeck</person> was working by stages and never meant, so far
as we know, to run through to the <location sea="Marmora_Sea">Marmora</location> yesterday.</p>

<p>Cabled to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> telling him of yesterday's reconnaissance by me and
the battle by <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>. Have said I have no official report to go upon
but from what I saw with my own eyes "I am being most reluctantly driven
to the conclusion that the Straits are not likely to be forced by
battleships as at one time seemed probable and that, if my troops are to
take part, it will not take the subsidiary form anticipated. The Army's
part will be more than mere landings of parties to destroy Forts, it
must be a deliberate and progressive military operation carried out at
full strength so as to open a passage for the Navy."</p>

<p>To be able, if necessary, to act up to my own words I sent another
message to the <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral</person> and told him, if he could spare the troops from
the vicinity of the Straits, I would like to take them right off to
<location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> so as to shake them out there and reship them ready for
anything. He has wirelessed back asking me, on political grounds, to
delay removing the troops "until our attack is renewed in a few days'
time."</p>

<p>Bravo, the <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral</person>! Still; if there are to be even a few days' delay I
<location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> is the only port possible.</p>

<p><person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Wemyss</person> has just sent me over the following letter. It confirms
officially the loss of the three battleships:--</p>

<p>                                                              _Friday._</p>

<p>  "My Dear General,</p>

<p>"The enclosed is a copy of a Signal I have received from <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>. I
what results we have achieved I think. I gather from intercepted signals
that the _Ocean_ also is sunk, but of this I am not quite certain. I am
off in _Dublin_ immediately she comes in and expect I may be back
to-night. This of course depends a good deal upon what <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> wants.
Captain Boyle brings this and will be at your disposal. He is the Senior
Naval Officer here in my absence.</p>

<p>                "Believe me, Sir,
                   "Yours sincerely,
                       (_Sd._) "<person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">R. Wemyss</person>."</p>

<p>           Copy of Telegram enclosed:--</p>

<p>  "_From_ V.A.E.M.S.
  "_To_ S.N.O. Mudros.
  "_Date, 18th March, 1915._</p>

<p>"Negative demonstration at <location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location>, 19th. Will you come to <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location> and
see me to-morrow. We have had disastrous day owing either to floating
mines or torpedoes from shore tubes fired at long range. <location ship="H.M.S._Irresistible">H.M.S.
_Irresistible_</location> and <location ship="F.S._Bouvet">_Bouvet_</location> sunk. <location ship="H.M.S._Ocean">H.M.S. _Ocean_</location> still afloat, but
probably lost. <location ship="H.M.S._Inflexible">H.M.S. _Inflexible_</location> damaged by mine. <location ship="F.S._Gaulois">_Gaulois_</location> badly
damaged by gunfire. Other ships all right, and we had much the best of
the Ports."</p></entry>

<entry><p>_20th March, 1915._ <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">_H.M.S. "Franconia</location>." <location coast="Mudros_Harbour">Mudros Harbour</location>._ Stormy
weather, and even here, inside <location coast="Mudros_Harbour">Mudros harbour</location>, touch with the shore is
cut off.</p>

<p>After I was asleep last night, an answer came in from <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, straight,
strong and to the point. He says, "You know my view that the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>
passage must be forced, and that if large military operations on the
<location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">Gallipoli Peninsula</location> by your troops are necessary to clear the way, those
operations must be undertaken after careful consideration of the local
defences and must be carried through."</p>

<p>Very well: all hinges on <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">the Admiral</person>.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_21st March, 1915._ <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">_H.M.S. "Franconia.</location>"_ A talk with <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral Wemyss</person> and
<person name="Albert_d'Amade">General d'Amade</person>. <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Wemyss</person> is clear that the Navy must not admit a check
and must get to work again as quickly as they can. Wemyss is Senior
Naval Officer at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> and is much liked by everyone. He has
put his seniority in his pocket and is under his junior--fighting first,
rank afterwards!</p>

<p>A letter from <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>, dated "<location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">Q.E.</location> the 19th," has only just come to
hand:--</p>

<p>"Our men were splendid and thank heaven our loss of life was quite
small, though the French lost over 100 men when <location ship="F.S._Bouvet">_Bouvet_</location> struck a mine.</p>

<p>"How our ships struck mines in an area that was reported clear and swept
the previous night I do not know, unless they were floating mines
started from the Narrows!</p>

<p>"I was sad to lose ships and my heart aches when one thinks of it; one
must do what one is told and take risks or otherwise we cannot win. We
are all getting ready for another 'go' and not in the least beaten or
downhearted. The big forts were silenced for a long time and everything
was going well, until _<location ship="F.S._Bouvet">Bouvet</location>_ struck a mine. It is hard to say what
amount of damage we did, I don't know, there were big explosions in the
Forts!"</p>

<p><person name="William_Birdwood">Little Birdie</person>, now grown up into a grand General, turned up at 3 p.m.<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>was enchanted to see him. We had hundreds and thousands of things to
talk over. Although the confidence of the sailors seems quite unshaken
by the events of the 18th, <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdie</person> seems to have made up his mind that
the Navy have shot their bolt for the time being and that we have no
time to lose in getting ready for a landing. But then he did not see the
battle and cannot, therefore, gauge the extent to which the Turkish
Forts were beaten.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_22nd March, 1915._ <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">_H.M.S. "Franconia</location>."_ At 10 a.m. we had another
Conference on board the <location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">_Queen Elizabeth_</location>.</p>

<p>Present:--</p>

<p>  <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral de Robeck</person>,
  <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral Wemyss</person>,
  <person name="William_Birdwood">General Birdwood</person>,
  <person name="Walter_Braithwaite"> General Braithwaite</person>,
  <person name="Peter_Polen">Captain Pollen</person>,
  <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Myself</person>.</p>

<p>The moment we sat down <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> told us _he was now quite clear he
could not get through without the help of all my troops_.</p>

<p>Before ever we went aboard <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, Birdwood and I had agreed that,
whatever we landsmen might think, we must leave the seamen to settle
their own job, saying nothing for or against land operations or
amphibious operations until the sailors themselves turned to us and said
they had abandoned the idea of forcing the passage by naval operations
alone.</p>

<p>They have done so. The fat (that is us) is fairly in the fire.</p>

<p>No doubt we had our views. <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdie</person> and my own Staff disliked the idea of
chancing mines with million pound ships. The hesitants who always make
hay in foul weather had been extra active since the sinking of the three
men-of-war. Suppose the Fleet _could_ get through with the loss of
another battleship or two--how the devil would our troopships be able to
follow? And the store ships? And the colliers?</p>

<p>This had made me turn contrary. During the battle I had cabled that the
chances of the Navy pushing through on their own were hardly fair
fighting chances, but, since then, <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>, the man who should know,
had said twice that he _did_ think there was a fair fighting chance. Had
he stuck to that opinion at the conference, then I was ready, as a
soldier, to make light of military croaks about troopships.
<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> must surrender, revolt or scuttle within a very few hours
of our battleships entering the <location sea="Marmora_Sea">Marmora</location>. Memories of one or two obsolete
six inchers at Ladysmith helped me to feel as <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> would feel
when her rail and sea communications were cut and a rain of shell fell
upon the penned-in populace from <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>'s terrific batteries. Given a
good wind that nest of iniquity would go up like Sodom and Gomorrah in a
winding sheet of flame.</p>

<p>But once <person name="John_de_Robeck">the Admiral</person> said his battleships could not fight through
without help, there was no foothold left for the views of a landsman.</p>

<p>So there was no discussion. At once we turned our faces to the land
scheme. Very sketchy; how could it be otherwise? On the German system
plans for a landing on Gallipoli would have been in my pocket,
up-to-date and worked out to a ball cartridge and a pail of water. By
the British system (?) I have been obliged to concoct my own plans in a
brace of shakes almost under fire. Strategically and tactically our
method may have its merits, for though it piles everything on to one
man, the Commander, yet he is the chap who has got to see it through.
But, in matters of supply, transport, organisation and administration
our way is the way of Colney Hatch.</p>

<p>Here am I still minus my Adjutant-General; my Quartermaster-General and
my Medical Chief, charged with settling the basic question of whether
the Army should push off from <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location> or from <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>. Nothing in the
world to guide me beyond my own experience and that of my <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Chief of the
General Staff</person>, whose sphere of work and experience lies quite outside
these administrative matters. I can see that <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location> is practically
impossible; I fix on <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> in the light of <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite's</person> advice and
my own hasty study of the map. Almost incredible really, we should have
to decide so tremendous an administrative problem off the reel and
without any Administrative Staff. But time presses, the responsibility
cannot be shirked, and so I have cabled <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> that <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location> must be a
wash-out and that I am sending my troops to get ship-shape at <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>
although, thereby, I upset every previous arrangement. Then I have had
to cable for Engineers, trench mortars, bombs, hand grenades,
periscopes. Then again, seeing things are going less swimmingly than <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>
had thought they would, I have had to harden my heart against his horror
of being asked for more men and have decided to cable for leave to bring
over from <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> <unit type="brigade">a Brigade of Gurkhas</unit> to complete <unit type="division">Birdwood's New Zealand
Division</unit>. Last, and worst, I have had to risk the fury of the Q.M.G. to
the Forces by telling the War Office that their transports are so loaded
(water carts in one ship; water cart horses in another; guns in one
ship; limbers in another; entrenching tools anyhow) that they must be
emptied and reloaded before we can land under fire.</p>

<p>These points were touched upon at the Conference. I told them too that
my Intelligence folk fix the numbers of the enemy now at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>
as 40,000 on <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location> with a reserve of 30,000 behind
<location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>: on the Asiatic side of the Straits there are at least a
Division, but there _may_ be several Divisions. The <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral</person>'s
information tallies and, so <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdie</person> says, does that of the Army in <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location>.
The War Office notion that the guns of the Fleet can sweep the enemy off
the tongue of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> from <location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi Baba</location> Southwards is moonshine. My
trump card turns out to be the Joker; best of all cards only it don't
happen to be included in this particular pack!</p>

<p>As ideas for getting round this prickly problem were passing through my
mind, two suggestions for dealing with it were put forward. The sailors
say some lighters were being built, and probably by now are built, for
the purpose of a landing in the North: they would carry five hundred
men; had bullet-proof bulwarks and are to work under their own gas
engines. If I can possibly get a petition for these through to <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person>
we would very likely be lent some and with their aid the landing under
fire will be child's play to what it will be otherwise. But the cable
must get to <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person>: if it falls into the hands of <person name="John_Fisher">Fisher</person> it fails, as
the sailors tell me he is obsessed by the other old plan and grudges us
every rope's end or ha'porth of tar that finds its way out here.</p>

<p>Rotten luck to have cut myself off from wiring to <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person>: still I see
no way out of it: with <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> jealous as a tiger--what can I do? Also,
although the sailors want me to pull this particular chestnut out of the
fire, it is just as well they should know I am not going to speak to
<person name="John_Fisher">their Boss</person> even under the most tempting circs.: but they won't cable
themselves: frightened of <person name="John_Fisher">Fisher</person>: so I then and there drafted this to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>
from myself:--</p>

<p>"Our first step of landing under fire will be the most critical as well
as the most vital of the whole operations. If the Admiralty will
improvise and send us out post haste 20 to 30 large lighters difficulty
and duration of this phase will be cut down to at least one half. The
lighters should each be capable of conveying 400 to 500 men or 30 to 40
horses. They should be protected by bullet-proof armour."</p>

<p>Everyone agreed but <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> pointed out that, by sending this message,
we implied in so many words, that we would not land until the lighters
came out from <location country="England">England</location>. He assumed that we had definitely turned down any
plan of scrambling ashore forthwith, as best we could? I said, "Yes,"
and that the Navy were with me in that view, a statement confirmed by <person name="John_de_Robeck">de
Robeck</person> and <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Wemyss</person> who nodded their heads. <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> said he only wanted
to be quite clear about it, and there the matter dropped.</p>

<p>Actually I had thought a lot about that possibility. To a man of my
temperament there was every temptation to have a go in and revenge the
loss of the battleships forthwith. We might sup to-morrow night on <location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi
Baba</location>. With luck we really might. Had I been here for ten days instead of
five, and had I had any time to draft out any sort of scheme, I might
have had a dart. But the operation of landing in face of an enemy is the
most complicated and difficult in war. Under existing conditions the
whole attempt would be partial, _decousu_, happy-go-lucky to the last
degree. There are no small craft to speak of. There is no provision for
carrying water. There is no information _at all_ about springs or wells
ashore. There is no arrangement for getting off the wounded and my
Principal Medical Officer and his Staff won't be here for a fortnight.
My orders against piecemeal occupation are specific. But <unit type="division">the 29th</unit>
Division is our _piece de resistance_ and it won't be here, we
reckon--not complete--for another three weeks.</p>

<p>All the same, I might chance it, for, by taking all these off chances we
_might_ pull off the main chance of stealing a march upon the Turks.
What puts me off is not the chances of war but the certainties of
commonsense. If I did so handle my troops on the spot as to sup on <location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi
Baba</location> to-morrow night, I still could not counter the inevitable reaction
of numbers, time and space. The Turks would have at least a fortnight to
concentrate their whole force against my half force; to defeat them and
then to defy the other half.</p>

<p>I must wait for the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit>. By the time they come I can get
things straight for a smashing simultaneous blow and I am resolved that,
so far as in me lies, the orders and preparations will then be so
thoroughly worked out--so carefully rehearsed as to give every chance to
my men.[6]</p>

<p>If the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> were here--or near at hand--I could balance
shortage against the obvious evils of giving the Turks time to reinforce
and to dig. Could I hope for the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> within a week it might be
worth my while to fly in the face of <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> by grasping <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> firmly
by her toe: or,--had my staff and self been here ten days ago, we could
have already got well forward with our plans and orders, as well as with
the laying of our hands upon the thousand odds and ends demanded by the
invasion of a barren, trackless extremity of an Empire--odds and ends
never thought of by anyone until the spur of reality brought them
galloping to the front. Then the moment the Fleet cried off, we might
have had a dash in, right away, with what we have here. The onslaught
could have been supported from <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> and the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> might have
been treated as a reserve.</p>

<p>But, taking things as they are:--</p>

<p>(1). No detail thought out, much less worked out or practised, as to
form or manner of landing;</p>

<p>(2). Absence of <unit type="division">29th Division</unit>;</p>

<p>(3). Lack of gear (naval and military) for any landing on a large scale
or maintenance thereafter;</p>

<p>(4). Unsettled weather; my ground is not solid enough to support me
were I to put it to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> that I had broken away from his explicit
instructions.</p>

<p>The Navy, i.e., <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>, <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Wemyss</person> and <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>, entirely agree. They see as
well as we do that the military force ought to have been ready before
the Navy began to attack. What we have to do now is to repair a first
false step. <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">The Admiral</person> undertakes to keep pegging away at the Straits
whilst we in <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> are putting on our war paint. He will see to it,
he says, that they think more of battleships than of landings. He is
greatly relieved to hear _I_ have practically made up my mind to go for
the South of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> and to keep in closest touch with the Fleet.
<person name="Roger_Keyes">The Commodore</person> also seems well pleased: he told us he hoped to get his
Fleet Sweeps so reorganised as to do away with the danger from mines by
the 3rd or 4th of April; then, he says, with us to do the spotting for
the naval guns, the battleships can smother the Forts and will alarm the
Turkish Infantry as to that tenderest part of an Army--its rear. So<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>may say that all are in full agreement,--a blessing.</p>

<p>Have cabled home begging for more engineers, a lot of hand grenades,
trench mortars, periscopes and tools. The barbed wire bothers me! Am
specially keen about trench mortars; if it comes to close fighting on
<location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> with its restricted area trench mortars may make up for
our lack of artillery and especially of howitzers. Luckily, they can be
turned out quickly.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_23rd March, 1915. <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">H.M.S. "Franconia.</location>"_ At 9 a.m. <person name="Albert_d'Amade">General d'Amade</person> and
his Staff came aboard. <person name="Albert_d'Amade">D'Amade</person> had been kept yesterday by his own
pressing business from attending the Conference. I have read him these
notes and have shown him my cable of yesterday to Lord <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> in which I say
that "The <person name="Albert_d'Amade">French Commander</person> is equally convinced that a move to
<location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> is a practical necessity, although a point of honour makes it
impossible for him to suggest turning his back to the Turks to his own
Government." But, I say, "he will be enchanted if they give him the
order." <person name="Albert_d'Amade">D'Amade</person> says I have not quite correctly represented his views.
Not fantastic honour, he says, caused him to say we had better, for a
while, hold on, but rather the sense of prestige. He thought the
departure of the troops following so closely on the heels of the naval
repulse would have a bad moral effect on the Balkans. But he agrees
that, in practice, the move has now become imperative; the animals are
dying; the men are overcrowded, whilst <location coast="Mudros_Harbour">Mudros</location> is impossible as a base.
My cable, therefore, may stand.</p>

<p>At 10 o'clock <person name="Albert_d'Amade">he</person>, <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdie</person> and <person name="Ian_Hamilton">myself</person> landed to inspect a Battalion of
Australians (<unit type="battalion">9th Battalion</unit> of the <unit type="brigade">3rd Brigade</unit>). I made them carry out a
little attack on a row of windmills, and really, they did not show much
more imagination over the business than did Don Quixote in a similar
encounter. But the men are superb specimens.</p>

<p>Some of the troop transports left harbour for <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> during the
afternoon. Bad to see these transports sailing the wrong way. What a
d----d pity! is what every soldier here feels--and says. But to look
on the bright side, our fellows will be twice as well trained to boat
work, and twice as well equipped by the time the <unit type="division">29th</unit> turn up, and by
then the weather will be more settled. As <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person> said too, it will be
worth a great deal to us if the French troops get a chance of working a
little over the ground together with their British comrades before they
go shoulder to shoulder against the common enemy. All the same, if I had
my men and guns handy, I'd rather get at the Turks quick than be sure of
good weather and good _band-o-bast_ and be sure also of a well-prepared
enemy.</p>

<p>In the afternoon <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> brought me a draft cable for Lord <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> _re_
yesterday's Conference. I have approved. In it I say, "on the
thoroughness with which I can make the preliminary arrangements, of
which the proper allocation of troops, etc., to transports is not the
least important, the success of my plans will largely depend."
Therefore, I am going to <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>, as a convenient place for this work
and, "the Turks will be kept busy meanwhile by the <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral</person>."</p></entry>

<entry><p>_24th March, 1915. <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">H.M.S. "Franconia</location>."_ <person name="Albert_d'Amade">D'Amade</person> and Staff came aboard at
10 a.m. He has got leave to move and will sail to <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> forthwith.
<person name="Roger_Keyes">Roger Keyes</person> from the <location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">Flagship</location> came shortly afterward. He is sick as a
she-bear robbed of her cubs that his pets: battleships, T.B.s,
destroyers, submarines, etc., should have to wait for the Army. Well, we
are not to blame! Keyes has been shown my cables to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> and is pleased
with them. He accepts the fact, I think, that the Army must tackle the
mobile artillery of the Turks before the Navy can expect to silence the
light guns protecting the mine fields and then clear out the mines with
the present type of mine sweeper. But the <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral's</person> going to fix up the
mine sweeper question while we are away. Once he has done that, Keyes
believes the Fleet can knock out the Forts; wipe out the protective
batteries and sweep up the mines quite comfortably. He said one
illuminating and encouraging thing to <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>; viz., that he had
never felt so possessed of the power of the Navy to force a passage
through the Narrows as in the small hours of the 19th when he got back
to the Flagship after trying in vain to salve the <location ship="H.M.S._Ocean">_Ocean_</location> and the
<location ship="H.M.S._Irresistible">_Irresistible_</location>.</p>

<p>Keyes brought me a first class letter from the Admiral--very much to the
point:--</p>

<p>                                                "<location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">H.M.S. _Q.E._</location>
                                                     _24th March, 15._</p>

<p>  "My Dear General,</p>

<p>"I hear the Authorities at 'Home' have been sending hastening telegrams
to you. They most unfortunately did the same to us and probably if our
work had been slower and more thorough it would have been better. If
only they were on the _spot_, they would realise that to hurry would
write failure. In my very humble opinion, good co-operation and
organisation means everything for the future. A great triumph is much
better than scraping through and poor results! We are entirely with you
and can be relied on to give any assistance in our power. We will not be
idle!</p>

<p>                             "Believe me,
                                 "Yours sincerely,
                               (_Sd._) "<person name="John_de_Robeck">J.M. de Robeck</person>."</p>

<p>11-15. <person name="Cecil_Thursby">Admiral Thursby</person> (just arrived with the <location ship="H.M.S._Queen">_Queen_</location> and <location ship="H.M.S._Implacable">_Implacable_</location>)
came to make his salaams. We served together at <location island="Malta">Malta</location> and both broke
sinews in our calves playing lawn tennis--a bond of union.</p>

<p>Have cabled to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> telling him I am just off to Alexandria. Have
said that the ruling factor of my date of landing must be the arrival of
the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> "(see para. 2 of your formal instructions to me the
foresight of which appeals to me with double force now we are at close
quarters with the problem[7])." I have pointed out that <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood's</person>
Australians are very weak in artillery; that the <unit type="division">Naval Division</unit> has none
at all and that the guns of the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> make that body even more
indispensable than he had probably realised. I would very much like to
add that these are no times for infantry divisions minus artillery
seeing that they ought to have three times the pre-war complement of
guns, but <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite's</person> good advice has prevailed. As promised at the
Conference I express a hope that I may be allowed "to complete
<person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood's</person> <unit type="division">New Zealand Division</unit> with a <unit type="brigade">Brigade of Gurkhas</unit> who would work
admirably in the terrain" of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>. In view of what we have
gathered from <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>, I wind up by saying, "The <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral</person>, whose confidence
in the Navy seems to have been raised even higher by recent events, and
who is a thruster if ever there was one, is in agreement with this
telegram."</p>

<p>Actually <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person> will show him a copy; we will wait one hour before
sending it off and, if we don't hear then, we may take it <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> will
have endorsed the purport. Of course, if he does not agree the last
sentence must come out, and he will have to put his own points to the
Admiralty.</p>

<p>_Later_.--Have sent Doughty Wylie to <location city="Athens">Athens</location> to do "Intelligence": the
cable was approved by Navy; duly despatched; and now--up anchor!</p></entry>

<chapter n="3" heading="Egypt"> CHAPTER III</chapter>


<entry><p>_25th March, 1915. <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">H.M.S. "Franconia.</location>" At Sea._ A fine smooth sea and a
flowing tide. Have written to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> and <person name="Herbert_Asquith">Mr. Asquith</person>. Number two has caused
me _fikr_.[8] The <person name="Herbert_Asquith">P.M.</person> lives in another plane from us soldiers. So it
came quite easily to his lips to ask _me_ to write to him,--a high
honour, likewise an order. But <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> is my soldier chief. As C.-in-C. in
<location country="India">India</location> he refused point blank to write letters to autocratic John Morley
behind the back of the Viceroy, and Morley never forgave him. <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> told me
this himself and he told me also that he resented the correspondence
which was, he knew, being carried on, behind his (<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s) back, between
the army in <location country="France">France</location> and his (<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s) own <person name="Herbert_Asquith">political Boss</person>: that sort of
action was, he considered, calculated to undermine authority.</p>

<p>I have had a long talk with <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> _re_ this quandary. He strongly
holds that my first duty is to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> and that it is for us a question of <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>
and no one but <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> Were the S. of S. only a civilian (instead of being a
Field Marshal) the case _might_ admit of argument; as things are, it
does not. So have written the <person name="Herbert_Asquith">P.M.</person> on these lines and shall send <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> the
carbons of all my letters to him. To <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> himself I have written backing
up my cable and begging for a <unit type="brigade">Brigade of Gurkhas</unit>. Really, it is like
going up to a tiger and asking for a small slice of venison: I remember
only too well his warning not to make his position impossible by
pressing for troops, etc., but <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> is not <location country="England">England</location>; the Westerners
don't want the Gurkhas who are too short to fit into their trenches and,
last but not least, our landing is not going to be the simple,
row-as-you-please he once pictured. The situation in fact, is not in the
least what he supposed it to be when I started; therefore, I am
justified, I think, in making this appeal:--"I am very anxious, if
possible, to get <unit type="brigade">a Brigade of Gurkhas</unit>, so as to complete the New Zealand
Divisional organisation with a type of man who will, I am certain, be
most valuable on <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location>. The scrubby hillsides on the
South-west face of the plateau are just the sort of terrain where those
little fellows are at their brilliant best. There is already a small
Indian commissariat attached to the Mountain Batteries, so there would
be no trouble on the score of supply."</p>

<p>"As you may imagine, I have no wish to ask for anything the giving of
which would seriously weaken our hold on <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location>, but you will remember
that four Mounted Brigades belonging to Birdwood's force are being left
behind to look after the <location country="Egypt">land of the Pharaohs</location>, and a <unit type="brigade">Mounted Brigade</unit> for
a battalion seems a fair exchange. <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location>, in fact, so far as I can make
out, seems stiff with troops, and each little Gurkha might be worth his
full weight in gold at Gallipoli."</p>

<p>Wrote Fitz in much the same sense:--"We are desperately keen to extract
a <unit type="brigade">Gurkha Brigade</unit> out of <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> and you might lend a hand, not only to us,
but to all your own <unit type="regiment">Sikh</unit> and <unit type="regiment">Dogra</unit> Regiments, by making <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> see that the
Indian Army was never given a dog's chance in the mudholes. They were
benumbed: _it was not their show_. Here, in the warm sun; pitted against
the hereditary _dushman_[9] who comes on shouting 'Allah!' they would
gain much _izzat_.[10] _Now mind_, if you see any chance of an Indian
contingent for <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>, do everyone a good turn by rubbing these
ideas into <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>"</p>

<p><person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> has already picked up a number of useful hints from <person name="Roger_Keyes">Roger
Keyes</person>. His old friendship with <person name="Roger_Keyes"> the Commodore</person> should be a help. <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person> is
a fine fellow; radiating resolve to do and vigour to carry
through--hereditary qualities. His Mother, of whom he is an ugly
likeness, was as high-spirited, fascinating, clever a creature as ever<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>saw. Camel riding, hawking, dancing, making good _band-o-bast_ for a
picnic, she was always at the top of the hunt; the idol of the Punjab
Frontier Force. His Father, Sir Charles, grim old Paladin of the
Marshes, whose loss of several fingers from a sword cut earned him my
special boyish veneration, was really the devil of a fellow. My first
flutter out of the sheltered nest of safe <location country="England">England</location> into the outer sphere
of battle, murder and sudden death, took place under the auspices of
that warrior so famoused in fight when I was aged twenty. Riding
together in the early morning from the mud fort of Dera Ismail Khan
towards the Mountain of Sheikh Budin, we suddenly barged into a mob of
wild Waziri tribesmen who jumped out of the ditch and held us up--hand
on bridle. The old General spoke Pushtu fluently, and there was a
parley, begun by him, ordinarily the most silent of mankind. Where were
they going to? To buy camels at Dera Ghazi Khan. How far had they come?
Three days' march; but they had no money. The General simulated
amazement--"You have come all that distance to buy camels without money?
Those are strange tales you tell me. I fear when you pass through Dera
Ismail you will have to raise the wind by selling your nice pistols and
knives: oh yes, I see them quite well; they are peeping at me from under
your poshteens." The Waziris laughed and took their hands off our reins.
Instantly, the General shouted to me, "Come on--gallop!" And in less
than no time we were going hell for leather along the lonely frontier
road towards our next relay of horses. "That was a narrow squeak," said
the General, "but _you may take liberties with a Waziri if only you can
make him laugh_."</p></entry>

<entry><p>_26th March, 1915. <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">H.M.S. "Franconia</location>." At Sea._ Inspected troops on
board. A keen, likely looking lot. All <unit type="division">Naval Division</unit>; living monuments,
these fellows, to <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person> Churchill's contempt for convention.</p>

<p>Reached <location city="Port_Said">Port Said</location> about 3.30 p.m. Nipped into a "Special" which seems to
have become my "ordinary" vehicle and left for <location city="Cairo">Cairo</location>. Opened despatches
from <location city="London">London</location>. "Bullet-proof lighters cannot be provided." "I quite agree
that the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> with its artillery is necessary." Not a word
about <unit type="brigade">the Gurkhas</unit>. Arrived at 10 p.m., and was met by <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person>.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_27th March, 1915 <location city="Cairo">Cairo</location>._ Working hard at Headquarters all day till 6.15
p.m., when I made my salaam to the <person name="Sultan_Kamel">Sultan</person> at the Abdin Palace. A real
Generals' dinner--what we used to call a _burra khana_--at <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell's</person>
hospitable board:--</p>

<p>  <person name="William_Birdwood">General Birdwood</person>,
  <person name="Alexander_Godley">General Godley</person>,
  <person name="William_Bridges">General Bridges</person>,
  <person name="Haig_Douglas">General Douglas</person>,
  <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">General Braithwaite</person>,
  <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Myself</person>.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_28th March, 1915. <location city="Cairo">Cairo</location>._ Inspected <unit type="division">East Lancashire Division</unit> and a
<unit type="brigade">Yeomanry Brigade</unit> (Westminster Dragoons and Herts). How I envied <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person>
these beautiful troops. They will only be eating their heads off here,
with summer coming up and the desert getting as dry as a bone. <unit type="division">The
Lancashire men</unit> especially are eye-openers. How on earth have they
managed to pick up the swank and devil-may-care airs of crack regulars?
They _are_ Regulars, only they are bigger, more effective specimens than
Manchester mills or East Lancashire mines can spare us for the Regular
Service in peace time. Anyway, no soldier need wish to see a finer lot.
On them has descended the mantle of my old comrades[11] of
Elandslaagte and Caesar's Camp, and worthily beyond doubt they will wear
it.</p>


<p>The enthusiasm of the natives was a pleasing part of the show. During
four years of Egyptian Inspections I recall no single instance of any
manifestation of friendliness to our troops, or even of interest in
them, by Gyppies. But the Territorials seem, somehow, to have conquered
their goodwill. As each stalwart company swung past there was a
spontaneous effervescence of waving hands along the crowded street and
murmurs of applause from Bedouins, Blacks and Fellaheen.</p>

<p><person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> will have a fit if I ask for them! He will fall down in a fit, I
am sure. Already he is vexed at my having cabled and written <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> for
_his_ (<person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell's</person>) <unit type="brigade">Brigade of Gurkhas</unit>. To him I appear careless of his
(<person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell's</person>) position and of the narrowness of his margin of safety. For
the life of him <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> can't help putting his Lieutenants into this
particular cart. The same old story as the eight small columns in the
<location region="Transvaal">Western Transvaal</location>: co-equal and each thinking his own beat on the veldt
the only critical spot in <location country="South_Africa">South Africa</location>: and the funny thing is that
<person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> was then running the base at Vryberg and I was in command in the
field! But _there_ my word was law; _here_ <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> is entirely
independent of me, which is as much as to say, that the feet are not
under control of the head; i.e., that the expedition must move like a
drunken man. That is my fear: <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> will do what lies in him to help,
but in action it is better to order than to ask.</p>

<p>Grand lunch at the Abdin Palace with <person name="Sultan_Kamel">the Sultan</person>. Most of the Cabinet
present. The <person name="Sultan_Kamel">Sultan</person> spoke French well and seems clever as well as most
gracious and friendly. He assured me that the Turkish Forts at the
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> were absolutely impregnable. The words "absolute" and
"impregnable" don't impress me overmuch. They are only human opinions
used to gloss over flaws in the human knowledge or will. Nothing is
impregnable either--that's a sure thing. No reasons were given me by <person name="Sultan_Kamel">His
Highness</person>.</p>

<p>Have just written home about these things: midnight.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_29th March, 1915. 9.30 p.m. Palace Hotel, <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>._ Early start to
the Mena Camp to see the Australians. A devil of a blinding storm gave a
foretaste of dust to dust. That was when they were marching past, but
afterwards I inspected the Infantry at close quarters, taking a good
look at each man and speaking to hundreds. Many had been at my
inspections in their own country a year ago, but most were new hands who
had never worn uniform till they 'listed for the war. The troops then
marched back to Camp in mass of quarter columns--or rather swept by like
a huge yellow cloud at the heart of which sparkled thousands of
bayonets.</p>

<p>Next I reviewed the Artillery, Engineers and Cavalry; winding up with
the overhaul of the supply and transport column. This took time, and I
inspect a mixed Division of Australians and New Zealanders at
<location city="Heliopolis">Heliopolis</location>. <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> commanded. Great fun seeing him again. These fellows
made a real good show; superb physique: numbers of old friends
especially amongst the New Zealanders. Another scurry in the motor to
catch the 4.15 for Alexandria. Tiring day if I had it in my mind to be
tired, but this 30,000 crowd of <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood's</person> would straighten up the back
of a pacifist. There is a bravery in their air--a keenness upon their
clean cut features--they are spoiling for a scrap! Where they have
sprung from it is hard to say. Not in <location city="Brisbane">Brisbane</location>, <location city="Adelaide">Adelaide</location>, <location city="Sydney">Sydney</location>,
<location city="Melbourne">Melbourne</location> or <location city="Perth">Perth</location>--no, nor in <location city="Dunedin">Dunedin</location>, <location city="Christchurch">Christchurch</location>, <location city="Wellington">Wellington</location> or
<location city="Auckland">Auckland</location>, did I meet specimens like unto these. The spirit of War has
breathed its fires into their hearts; the drill sergeant has taken
thought and has added one cubit to their stature.</p>

<p><person name="Albert_d'Amade">D'Amade</person> has just been to make me known to a couple of Frenchmen about to
join my Staff. They seem to be nice fellows. The French have been here
some days and they are getting on well. <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> landed this
morning; his first batch of transports are in the harbour. I am to see
the French troops in four days' time; <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston's</person> <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> on
the fifth day. Neither Commander has yet worked out how long it will
take before he has reloaded his transports. They declare it takes three
times as long to repack a ship loaded at haphazard as it would have
taken to have loaded her on a system in the first instance. Six days per
ship is their notion of what they can do, butI trust to improve a bit
on that.</p>

<p><person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> had written me a letter from <location island="Malta">Malta</location> (just to hand) putting
it down in black and white that we have not a reasonable prospect of
success. He seemed keen and sanguine when we met and made no reference
to this letter: so it comes in now as rather a startler. But it is best
to have the black points thrust upon one's notice beforehand--so long
always as I keep it fixed in the back of my mind that there was never
yet a great thought or a great deed which was not cried down as
unreasonable before the fact by a number of reasonable people!</p></entry>

<entry><p>_30th March, 1915. <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>._ Have just dictated a long letter to Lord
<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> in the course of which I have forced myself to say something which
may cause the great man annoyance. I feel it is up to me to risk that.
One thing--he knows I am not one of those rotters who ask for more than
they can possibly be given so that, if things go wrong, they may
complain of their tools. I have promised <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> to help him by keeping my
demands down to bedrock necessities. I make no demand for ammunition on
the <location country="France">France</location> and Flanders scale but--we must have _some_! There must be a
depot somewhere within hail. Here is the crucial para.:--</p>

<p>"I realise how hard up you must be for ammunition, but I hope the M.G.O.
will have by now put in hand the building up of some reserves at our
base in <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>. If our batteries or battalions now serving in <location country="France">France</location>
run short, something, at a pinch, can always be scraped together in
<location country="England">England</location> and issued to them within 24 hours. Here it would be a question
of almost as many days, and, if it were to turn out that we have a long
and severe struggle, with no reserves nearer us than Woolwich--well--it
would not be pleasant! Moreover the number of howitzers, guns and rifles
in <location country="France">France</location> is so enormous that it is morally impossible they should all
be hotly engaged at the same time. Thus they automatically form their
own reserves. In other words, a force possessing only ten howitzers
ought to have at least twice the reserves of a force possessing a
hundred howitzers. So at least it seems to me."</p>

<p>In the same letter I tell him about "<person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood's</person> crowd" and of their
splendid physique; their growing sense of discipline, their exceeding
great keenness, and wind up by saying that, given a fair chance, they
will, for certain, "render a very good account of themselves."</p>

<p>Confabs with <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person> and <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person>. <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston's</person> "appreciation"
of the situation at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> is to be treated as an _ad interim_
paper; he wrote it, he says now, without the fuller knowledge he is
daily acquiring--knowledge which is tending to make him more sanguine.
His stay at <location island="Malta">Malta</location> and his talks with Officers there had greatly
impressed him with the hardness of the nut we have to try and crack; so
much so that his paper suggests an indefinite putting off of the attempt
to throw open the Straits.I asked him if he had laid his view before <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>
in <location city="London">London</location> and he said, No; that he had not then come to it and that he
had not definitely come to it now.</p>

<p><person name="Albert_d'Amade">D'Amade's</person> own inclinations would have led him to Asia. When he left
<location country="France">France</location> he did not know he was to be under me and he had made up his mind
to land at Adramiti. But now he waives all preconceived ideas and is
keen to throw himself heart and soul into <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.'s</person> ideas and mine. He
would rather I did not even refer to his former views as he sees they
are expressly barred by the tenor of my instructions. The French are
working to time in getting ship-shape. <unit type="division">The 29th Division</unit> are arriving up
to date and about one-third of them have landed. We are fixing up our
gear for floating and other piers and are trying to improvise ways and
means of coping with the water problem--this ugly nightmare of a water
problem. The question of the carriage and storage of water for thousands
of men and horses over a roadless, mainly waterless track of country
should have been tackled before we left <location country="England">England</location>.</p>

<p>To solve these conundrums we have had to recreate for ourselves a
special field service system of food, water and ammunition supply. As an
instance we have had to re-organise baggage sections of trains and fit
up store ships as substitutes for additional ammunition columns and
parks. We are getting on fairly fast with our work of telling off troops
to transports so that each boat load of men landed will be, so to say,
on its own; victualled, watered and munitioned. But it takes some doing.
Greatly handicapped by absence of any Administrative, or Q. Staff. The
General Staff are working double shifts, at a task for which they have
never been trained:--</p>

<p>  It's a way we have in the Aaarmy!
  It's a way we have in the NAAAAvy!!
  It's a way we have in the Eeeeeempire!!!
     That nobody can deny!!!!</p>

<p>What would my friends on the Japanese General Staff say--or my quondam
friends on the German General Staff--if they knew that a
Commander-in-Chief had been for a fortnight in touch with his troops,
engaged with them upon a huge administrative job, and that he had not
one administrative Staff Officer to help him, but was willynilly using
his General Staff for the work? They would say "mad Englishmen" and this
time they would be right. The British public services are poisoned by
two enormous fallacies: (_a_) if a man does well in one business, he
will do equally well or better in another; (_b_) if a man does badly in
one business he will do equally badly or worse in another. There is
nothing beyond a vague, floating reputation or public opinion to enable
a new Minister to know his subordinates. The Germans have tabulated the
experiences and deficiencies of our leaders, active and potential, in
peace and war--we have not! Every British General of any note is
analysed, characterised and turned inside out in the bureau records of
the great German General Staff in Berlin. We only attempt anything of
that sort with burglars. My own portrait is in those archives and is
very good if not very flattering; so a German who had read it has told
me. This is organisation: this is business; but official circles in
<location country="England">England</location> are so remote in their methods from these particular notions of
business that I must turn to a big newspaper shop to let anyone even
begin to understand what it is to run Q. business with a G.S. team.
Suppose <person name="Alfred_Harmsworth">Lord Northcliffe</person> decided to embark upon a journalistic campaign
in Canada and that his scheme turned upon time; that it was a question
of <person name="Alfred_Harmsworth">Northcliffe</person> catching time by the forelock or of time laying
Northcliffe by the heels. Suppose, further, that he had no first-hand
knowledge of Canada and had decided to place the conduct of the campaign
in the hands of his brother who would spy out the land; choose the best
site; buy a building; order the printing press; engage hands and start
the paper. Well; what staff would he send with him? A couple of leader
writers, a trio of special correspondents and half a dozen reporters?
Probably; but would there not also be berths taken in the Cunarder for a
manager trained in the business side of journalism? Quite a fair way of
putting the present case, although, on the other side, it is also fair
to add that British Officers have usually had to play so many parts in
the charade of square pegs in round holes, that they can catch a hold
anywhere, at any time, and carry on somehow.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_31st March, 1915. <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>._--Quill driving and dictating. Have made
several remonstrances lately at the way <person name="Henry_McMahon">McMahon</person> is permitting the
Egyptian Press to betray our intentions, numbers, etc. It is almost
incredible and <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> doesn't see his way clear to interfere. For the
last day or two they have been telling the Turks openly where we are
bound for. Sohave written <person name="Henry_McMahon">McMahon</person> the following:--</p>

<p>                   "General Headquarters,
                        "18 RUE EL CAIED GOHAR,
                            "<location city="Alexandria">ALEXANDRIA</location>, 31/3/15.</p>

<p>  "DEAR HIGH COMMISSIONER,</p>

<p>"I was somewhat startled a couple of mornings ago by an article in the
_Egyptian Gazette_ giving away the arrival of the French troops, and
making open references to <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location>. The very frankness of
such communications may of course mislead the Turk into thinking we mean
thereby to take his mind off some other place which is our real
objective, butI doubt it. He knows our usual methods too well.</p>

<p>"Consequently as it is very important at least to throw him into some
state of bewilderment as to our movements, I propose sending the
following cable to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord Kitchener</person>:--</p>

<p>"'Whether of set purpose or through inadvertence articles have appeared
in Egyptian Press openly discussing arrival of French and British troops
and naming Gallipoli as their destination. Is there any political
objection to my cautiously spreading rumour that our true objective is,
say, <location city="Smyrna">Smyrna</location>?'</p>

<p>"Before I despatch the wire, however, I think I should like you to see
it, in case you have any objections. I have all the facilities for
spreading any rumour I like through my Intelligence Branch, which would
be less suspected than information leaking out from political sources.</p>

<p>"Could you kindly send me a wire on receipt of this?</p>

<p>                                            "Yours sincerely,
                                               (_Sd._) <person name="Ian_Hamilton">"IAN HAMILTON."</person></p>

<p>"I only propose to ask <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> in case there may be political reasons
why I should not select any particular place about which to spread a
rumour of our landing."</p>

<p>Forgot to note a step taken yesterday--to nowhere perhaps--perhaps to
<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>. Yesterday the _Doris_ brought me a copy of a long cable
sent by <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person> to <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> six days ago, together with a copy of the
V.A.'s reply. <person name="Winston_Churchil">The First Lord</person> is clearly in favour of the Fleet going on
knocking the Forts to pieces whilst the Army are getting on with their
preparations; clearly also he thinks that, under rough handling from
<location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">Q.E.</location> and Co., the Turkish resistance might at any moment collapse. Then we
  should sail through as per<person name="Herbert_Kitchener"> Lord K.'s</person>programme. Well; nothing would suit
me so well. If we are to have an opposed landing better kill two birds
with one stone and land bang upon the <location straits="Bosphorus">Bosphorus</location>. The nearer to the heart
I can strike my first blow, the more telling it will be. Cable 140 puts
the case very well. <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person> hits the nail on the head, so it seems to
me, when he points out that the Navy is not tied to the apron strings of
the Army but that it is the other way about: i.e., if the Fleet makes
another big push whilst we are getting ready, they can still fall back
on the combined show with us if they fail; whereas, if they succeed they
will save us all the loss of life and energy implied by an opposed
landing at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>. Certainly <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> and I had understood
that <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> would work to that end; that this is what he was driving
at when he said he would not be idle but would keep the Turks busy
whilst we were getting ready. Nothing will induce me to volunteer
opinions on Naval affairs. But <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>'s reply to <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person> might be
read as if I _had_ expressed an opinion, so I am bound to clear up that
point--definitely.</p>

<p>  "_From_ <person name="Ian_Hamilton">GENERAL SIR IAN HAMILTON</person>.
  "_To_ <person name="John_de_Robeck">VICE-ADMIRAL SIR JOHN DE ROBECK</person></p>

<p>"Copy of number 140 from Admiralty received AAA I had already
communicated outline of our plan to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord Kitchener</person> and am pushing on
preparations as fast as possible AAA War Office still seems to cherish
hope that you may break through without landing troops AAA Therefore, as
regards yourself I think wisest procedure will be to push on
systematically though not recklessly in attack on Forts AAA It is always
possible that opposition may crumple up AAA If you should succeed be
sure to leave light cruisers enough to see me through my military attack
in the event of that being after all necessary AAA If you do not succeed
then I think we quite understand one another AAA
                                                       "<person name="Ian_Hamilton">IAN HAMILTON</person>."</p></entry>

<entry><p>_1st April, 1915. <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>._ <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">The _Arcadian_</location> has arrived bringing my
A.G. and Q.M.G. with the second echelon of the Staff. God be praised for
this immense relief! The General Staff can now turn to their legitimate
business--the enemy, instead of struggling night and day with A.G. and
Q.M.G. affairs; allocating troops and transports; preparing for water
supply; tackling questions of procedure and discipline. We are all sorry
for the Q. Staff who, through no fault of their own, have been late for
the fair, _their_ special fair, the preparation, and find the show is
practically over. On paper at least, the Australians and New Zealanders
and the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> are properly fixed up. We should begin embarking
these formations within the next three days. After that will come <unit type="division">the
Naval Division</unit> from <location city="Port_Said">Port Said</location> and <unit type="division">the French Division</unit> from here.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_2nd April, 1915. <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>._ Hard at it all day in office. Am leaving
to-night by special train for Port Said to hurry things along.</p>

<p>A cable in from the Foreign Office telling me that the Russian part of
my force consists of a complete Army Corps under General
Istomine--evidently War and Foreign Offices still work in watertight
compartments!</p>

<p>Left <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> last night at 11 and came into <location city="Port_Said">Port Said</location> at dawn. After
breakfast mounted an Arab charger which seems to have emerged out of the
desert to meet my wishes just as do special trains and banquets: as if I
wore on my finger the magic ring of the Arabian fairy tale: so I do I
suppose, in the command it has pleased <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, Imperial Grand Vizier, to
bestow upon this humble but lively speck of dust. Mounting we cantered
through the heavy sand towards the parade ground near the docks. Here,
like a wall, stood <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston's</person> far-famed <unit type="division">Naval Division</unit> drawn up in its
battle array. <person name="Archibald_Paris">General Paris</person> received me backed by Olivant and Staff.
After my inspection <unit type="division">the Division marched</unit> past, and marched past very
well indeed, much better than they did when I saw them some months ago
in Kent, although the sand was against them, muffling the stamp of feet
which binds a Company together and telling unevenly on different parts
of the line. Admiral Pierce and his Flag Captain, Burmeister, honoured
the occasion: they were on foot and so, not to elevate the stature of
the Army above that of the Senior Service, I took the salute dismounted.</p>

<p>Next had a look round camp. Found things so, so. Saw <person name="Arthur_Asquith">Arthur Asquith</person> and
<person name="Rupert_Brooke">Rupert Brooke</person> of the <unit type="battalion">Howe Battalion</unit>, both sick, neither bad. Asked
<person name="Rupert_Brooke">Brooke</person> to join my personal Staff, not as a fire insurance (seeing what
happened to Ronnie Brooke at Elandslaagte and to Ava at Waggon Hill) but
still as enabling me to keep an eye on the most distinguished of the
Georgians. <person name="Rupert_Brooke">Young Brooke</person> replied, as a _preux chevalier_ would naturally
reply,--he realised the privileges he was foregoing, but he felt bound
to do the landing shoulder-to-shoulder with his comrades. He looked
extraordinarily handsome, quite a knightly presence, stretched out there
on the sand with the only world that counts at his feet.</p>

<p>Lunched on the <location ship="H.M.S._Franconia">_Franconia_</location> and conversed with <person name="Lt.Col.Matthews">Lieutenant-Colonel
Matthews</person> and <person name="Maj.Mewes">Major Mewes</person> of the <unit type="battalion">Plymouth Battalion</unit>; also with <person name="Maj.Palmer">Major
Palmer</person>. To see with your eyes; to hear with your ears; to touch with
your fingers enables you to bring the truth home to yourself. Five
minutes of that personal touch tells a man more than five weeks of
report reading. In five minutes I gained from these Officers five times
more knowledge about <location town="Sedd-el-Bahr">Sedd-el-Bahr</location> and<location town=" Kum Kale"> Kum Kale</location> than all their own bald
despatches describing their own landings and cutting-out enterprises had
given me. <person name="Archibald_Paris">Paris'</person> account had not helped me much either, the reason being
that it was not first hand,--was only so many words that he had
heard,--was not what he had _felt_. Now, I do really, at last and for
the first time, realistically grasp the lie of the land and of the
Turks. The prospect is not too rosy, but <person name="Wolfe_Murray">Wolfe</person>, I daresay, saw blue as
he gazed over the water at his problem, without map or General Staff
plan to help him. There lay Quebec; within cannon shot; but that enemy
was thrice his strength; entrenched in a fortress--there they lay
confident--a landing was "impossible!" But all things are possible--to
faith. He had faith in Pitt; faith in his own bright particular star;
faith in the British Fleet standing resolute at his back:--he launched
his attack; he got badly beaten at the landing; he pulled himself
together; he met a thousand and one mishaps and delays, and when, at the
long last, he fell, he had the plum in his pocket.</p>

<p>The Turks lie close within a few yards of the water's edge on the
Peninsula. <person name="Lt.Col.Matthews">Matthews</person> smiled sarcastically at the War Office idea that no
Turks can exist South of <location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi Baba</location>! At <location town="Sedd-el-Bahr">Sedd-el-Bahr</location>, the first houses
are empty, being open to the fire of the Fleet, but the best part of the
other houses are defiladed by the ground and a month ago they were held.
Glad I did not lose a minute after seeing the ground in asking <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person>
and <person name="Paul_Methuen">Methuen</person> to make me some trench mortars. <person name="Paul_Methuen">Methuen</person> says he can't help,
but <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell's</person> Ordnance people have already fixed up a sample or
two--rough things, but better than nothing. We have too little shrapnel
to be able to spare any for cutting entanglements. Trench mortars may
help where the Fleet can't bring their guns to bear. The thought of all
that barbed wire tucked away into the folds of the ground by the shore
follows me about like my shadow.</p>

<p>Left <location city="Port_Said">Port Said</location> for <location city="Kantara">Kantara</location> and got there in half an hour. <person name="Herbert_Cox">General Cox</person>,
an old Indian friend of the days when I was A.D.C. to Sir Fred., met me
at the station. He commands the Indian troops in <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location>. We nipped into a
launch on the Canal, and crossed over to inspect the Companies of the
<unit type="battalion">Nelson</unit>, <unit type="battalion">Drake</unit>, <unit type="battalion">Howe</unit> and <unit type="battalion">Anson</unit> Battalions in their Fort, whilst <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person>
hurried off to fix up a parade of his own.</p>

<p><unit type="brigade">The Indian Brigade</unit> were drawn up under <person name="Brg.Gen.Mercer">Brigadier-General Mercer</person>. After
inspection, the troops marched past headed by the band of the <unit type="battalion">14th
Sikhs</unit>. No one not a soldier can understand what it means to an old
soldier who began fighting in the Afghan War under Roberts of Kandahar
to be in touch once again with Sikhs and Gurkhas, those splendid
knights-errant of India.</p>

<p>After about eighteen years' silence, I thought my Hindustani would fail
me, but the words seemed to drop down from Heaven on to my tongue. Am
able now to understand the astonishment of St. Paul when he found
himself jabbering nineteen to the dozen in lingo, Greek to him till
then. But he at least was exempt from my worst terror which was that at
any moment I might burst into German!</p>

<p>After our little _durbar_, the men were dismissed to their lines and I
sounded (I had not told anyone of my intention) so the swift yet smooth
fall-in to danger posts was a feather in <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person>'s helmet.</p>

<p>Back to main camp and there saw troops not manning the Fort. There were
the:--</p>

<p>  Queen Victoria's Own
  <unit type="battalion">Sappers </unit>                 <person name="Cpt.Hogg">Captain Hogg, R.E.</person>,
  <unit type="battalion">69th Punjabis</unit>            <person name="Col.Harding">Colonel Harding</person>,
  <unit type="battalion">89th Punjabis</unit>            <person name="Col.Campbell">Colonel Campbell</person>,
  <unit type="battalion">14th K.G.O. Sikhs</unit>        <person name="Col.Palin">Colonel Palin</person>,
  <unit type="battalion">1st Bn. 6th Gurkhas</unit>      <person name="Col.Bruce">Colonel Bruce</person>,
  <unit type="battery">29th Mountain Battery</unit>
  and the Bikaner Camel
  Corps                                                  <person name="Maj.Bruce">Major Bruce</person>.</p>

<p>Had a second good talk to the Native Officers, shaking hands all round.
Much struck with the turn-out of the <unit type="battery">29th Mountain Battery</unit> which is to
come along with the Australian and New Zealand Army Corps to the
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>.</p>

<p>From the platform of the Fort the lines of our defences and the way the
Turks attacked them stood out very clearly to a pair of field glasses.
Why, with so many mounted men some effort was not made to harry the
enemy's retreat, <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person> cannot tell me. There were no trenches and the
desert had no limits.</p>

<p>_Now_ (in the train on my way back to <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>) I must have one more
try at <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> about these Gurkhas! My official cable and letter asking for
<unit type="brigade">the Gurkha Brigade</unit> have fallen upon stony ground. No notice of any sort
has been vouchsafed to my modest request. Has _any_ action been taken
upon them? Possibly the matter has been referred to <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> for opinion?
If so, he has said nothing about it, which does not promise well. <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person>
has heard nothing from <location city="Cairo">Cairo</location>; only no end of camp rumours. Most likely
<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> is vexed with me for asking for these troops at all, and thinks I am
already forgetting his warning not to put him in the cart by asking for
too many things. <location country="France">France</location> must not be made jealous and <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> ditto, I
letter. The whole is _most_ disappointing. Here is <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person> and here are his
men, absolutely wasted and frightfully keen to come. There are the
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> short-handed; there is the <unit type="division">New Zealand Division</unit> short of a
Brigade. If surplus and deficit had the same common denominator, say
"<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>" or "G.S." they would wipe themselves out to the instant
simplification of the problem. As it is, they are kept on separate
sheets of paper;</p>

<p>  too many troops        too few troops
      <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person>               <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Hamilton</person></p>



<p>Have just finished dictating a letter to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, giving him an account of my
inspection of the Indian troops and of how "they made my mouth water,
especially the 6th Gurkhas." I ask him if I could not anyway have _them_
"as a sort of escort to the <unit type="battery">Mountain Battery</unit>," and go on to say, "The
desert is drying up, <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person> tells me; such water as there is is becoming
more and more brackish and undrinkable; and no other serious raid, in
his opinion, will be possible this summer." I might have added that once
we open the ball at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> the old Turks must dance to our
tune, and draw in their troops for the defence of <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> but it
does not do to be too instructive to one's Grandmother. So there it is:
I have done the best I can.</p></entry>
<entry>
  <p>_4th April, 1915. <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>._ Busy day in office. Things beginning to
hum. A marvellous case of "two great minds." <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> has proffered his advice
upon the tactical problem, and how it should be dealt with, and, as I
it in one, even down to details, only I have not shells enough to cut
through barbed wire with my field guns or howitzers." I say also, "I
should much like to have some hint as to my future supply of gun and
rifle ammunition. <unit type="division">The Naval Division</unit> has only 430 rounds per rifle and
the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> only 500 rounds which means running it fine."</p>

<p>What might seem, to a civilian, a marvellous case of coincidence or
telepathy were he ever to compare my completed plan with <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s cabled
suggestion is really one more instance of the identity of procedure born
of a common doctrine between two soldiers who have worked a great deal
together. Given the same facts the odds are in favour of these facts
being seen eye to eye by each.</p>

<p>Forgot to note that <person name="Henry_McMahon">McMahon</person> answered my letter of the 31st personally,
on the telephone, saying he had no objection to my cabling <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> or
spreading any reports I liked through my Intelligence, but that he is
not keeper of the _Egyptian Gazette_ and must not quarrel with it as
Egypt is not at war! No wonder he prefers the telephone to the telegram
I begged him to send me if he makes these sort of answers. Egypt is in
the war area and, if it were not, <person name="Henry_McMahon">McMahon</person> can do anything he likes. The
_Gazette_ continues to publish full details of our actions and my only
hope is that the Turks will not be able to believe in folly so
incredible.</p></entry>
  
<entry><p>_5th April, 1915. <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>._ Motored after early breakfast to French
Headquarters at the Victoria College. Here I was met by <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person> and an
escort of Cuirassiers, and, getting on to my Australian horse, trotted
off to parade.</p>

<p>Coming on to the ground, the French trumpeters blew a lively fanfare
which was followed by a roll of drums. Never was so picturesque a
parade, the verdict of one who can let his mind rove back through the
military pageants of India, Russia, Japan, Germany, Austria,
Switzerland, China, Canada, U.S.A., Australia, and New Zealand. Yes,
<location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> has seen some pretty shows in its time; Cleopatra had an eye
to effect and so, too, had the great Napoleon. But I doubt whether the
townsfolk have ever seen anything to equal the _coup d'oeil_ engineered
by <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person>. Under an Eastern sun the colours of the French uniforms,
gaudy in themselves, ran riot, and the troops had surely been posted by
one who was an artist in more than soldiering. Where the yellow sand was
broken by a number of small conical knolls with here and there a group,
and here and there a line, of waving palms, there, on the knolls, were
clustered the Mountain Batteries and the Batteries of Mitrailleuses. The
Horse, Foot and Guns were drawn up, Infantry in front, Cavalry in rear,
and the Field Artillery--the famous 75s--at right angles.</p>

<p>Infantry of the Line in grey; Zouaves in blue and red; Senegalese wore
dark blue and the Foreign Legion blue-grey. The Cavalry rode Arabs and
barbs mostly white stallions; they wore pale blue tunics and bright
scarlet breeches.</p>

<p>I rode down the lines of Infantry first and then galloped through the
heavy sand to the right of the Cavalry and inspected them, by <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade's</person>
request, at a trot, winding up with the six Batteries of Artillery. On
reaching the Saluting Base, I was introduced to the French Minister
whilst <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person> presented colours to two Regiments (<unit type="regiment">175th Regiment de
marche d'Afrique</unit> and the <unit type="regiment">4th Colonial Regiment</unit>) making a short and
eloquent speech.</p>

<p>He then took command of the parade and marched past me at the head of
his forces. Were all the Houris of Paradise waving lily hands on the one
side, and were these French soldiers on the other side, I would give my
cold shoulder to the Houris.</p>

<p>The Cavalry swung along at the trot to the cadence of the trumpets and
to the clink-clank and glitter of steel. The beautiful, high-stepping
barbs; the trembling of the earth beneath their hoofs; the banner
streaming; the swordsmen of <location country="France">France</location> sweeping past the saluting base;
breaking into the gallop; sounding the charge; charging; _ventre a
terre_; out into the desert where, in an instant, they were snatched
from our sight and changed into a pillar of dust!</p>

<p>High, high soared our hopes. <location city="Jerusalem">Jerusalem</location>--<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>? No limit to what
these soldiers may achieve. The thought passed through the massed
spectators and set enthusiasm coursing through their veins. Loudly they
cheered; hats off; and hurrah for the Infantry! Hurrah, hurrah for the
Cavalry!! Hurrah, hurrah, hurrah for the 75s!!!</p>

<p>At the end I said a few farewell words to the French Minister and then
galloped off with <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person>. The bystanders gave us, too, the warmest
greetings, the bulk of them (French and Greek) calling out <person name="Albert_d'Amade">"d'Amade!"</person>
and the Britishers also shouting all sorts of things at the pitch of
their voices.</p>

<p>Almost lost my temper with <person name="Gen.Woodward">Woodward</person>, my new A.G., and this was the
thusness thereof:--</p>

<p>Time presses: <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> prods us from the rear: the Admiral from the front. To
their eyes we seem to be dallying amidst the fleshpots of Egypt whereas,
really, we are struggling like drowning mariners in a sea of chaos;
chaos in the offices; chaos on the ships; chaos in the camps; chaos
along the wharves; chaos half seas over rolling down the Seven Sisters
Road. The powers of Maxwell as C.-in-C., Egypt; of the <person name="Sultan_Kamel">Sultan</person> and
<person name="Henry_McMahon">McMahon</person>, High Commissioner of Egypt, and of myself, C.-in-C., M.E.F.,
not to speak of the powers of our police civil and military, have all to
be defined and wheeled into line. We cannot go rushing off into space
leaving Pandemonium behind us as our Base! I know these things from a
very long experience. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> believes in the principle as a student
and ex-teacher of students. And yet that call to the front!</p>

<p>We've _got_ to tackle the landing scheme on the spot and quick. Luckily
the problems at <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> are _all_ non-tactical; pure A.G. and Q.M.G.
Staff questions; whereas, at present, the problems awaiting me at the
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> are mainly tactical; G.S. questions. So I am going to treat
G.H.Q. as Solomon threatened to treat the baby; i.e., leave the
Administrative Staff here until they knock their pidgin more or less
into shape and send off the G.S. to pluck _their_ pidgin at the Straits.
The Q. people have still to commandeer offices for <person name="Gen.Woodward">Woodward</person>'s men, three
quarters of whom stay here permanently to do the casualty work; they
have to formulate a local code of discipline; take up buildings for base
hospitals and arrange for their personnel and equipment; outline their
schemes for getting sick and wounded back from the front; finish up the
loading of the ships, etc., etc., etc., _ad infinitum_. Whilst the Q.
Staff are thus pulling their full weight, the G. Staff will sail off
quickly and put their heads together with the Admiral and his Staff. As
to myself, I'm off: I cannot afford to lose more time in getting into
touch with the sailors, and the scene of action.</p>

<p>All was well until the Commander-in-Chief said he was going, but that
moment arose the good old trouble--the trouble which muddled our start
for the Relief of Chitral and ruined the Tirah Campaign. Everyone wants
to rush off to the excitement of the firing line--(a spasm usually cured
by the first hard fight), and to leave the hum-drum business of the Base
and Line of Communication to shift for itself. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, of all
people, was good natured enough to plead for the Administration. He came
to tell me that it might tend towards goodwill amongst the charmed
circle of G.H.Q. if even now, at the eleventh hour, I would sweeten
<person name="Gen.Woodward">Woodward</person> by bringing him along. I said, yes, if he, <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, would
stand surety that he, <person name="Gen.Woodward">Woodward</person>, had fixed up his base hospitals and
third echelon, but if not, no! Next came <person name="Gen.Woodward">Woodward</person> himself. With great
pertinacity he represented that his subordinates could do all that had
to be done at the base. He says he speaks for the Q.M.G., as well as for
the Director General of Medical Services, and that they all want to
accompany me on my reconnaissance of the coasts of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>. I was
a little sharp with him. These heads of Departments think they must be
sitting in the C.-in-C.'s pocket lest they lose caste. But I say the
Departments must be where their work lies, or else the C.-in-C. will
lose caste, and luckily he can still put his own Staff where he will.
Finally, I agreed to take with me the Assistant to the Director of
Medical Services to advise his own Chief as to the local bearings of his
scheme for clearing out the sick and wounded; the others stay here until
they get their several shows into working order, and with that my A.G.
had fain to be content.</p>

<p>D'Amade and two or three Frenchmen are dining with me to-night. Sir John
Maxwell has just arrived.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_6th April, 1915. <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>._ Started out at 9.15 with d'Amade and Sir
John to review the Mounted troops of the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit>. We first saw
them march down the road in column of route. What a contrast between
these solid looking men on their magnificent weight-carrying horses and
our wiry little Allies on their barbs and Arabs. The R.H.A. were superb.</p>

<p>After seeing the troops I motored to Mex Camp and inspected the <unit type="brigade">86th</unit> and
<unit type="brigade">87th Infantry Brigades</unit>. There was a strong wind blowing which tried to
spoil the show, but could not--that Infantry was too superb! Alexander,
Hannibal, Caesar, Napoleon; not one of them had the handling of
legionaries like these. <unit type="brigade">The Fusilier Brigade</unit> were the heavier. If we
don't win, I won't be able to put it on the men.</p>

<p><person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> left at 4 p.m. for <location city="Cairo">Cairo</location>. I have pressed him hard about <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person>'s
<unit type="brigade">Indian Brigade</unit> and told him of my conversation with <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person> himself and of
how keen all ranks of the <unit type="brigade">Brigade</unit> are to come. No use. He expects, so he
says, a big attack on <location straits="Suez">the Canal</location> any moment; he has heard nothing from
<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>; the fact that <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> has ignored my direct appeal to him shows he would
not approve, etc., etc., etc. All this is just the line I myself would
probably take--I admit it--if asked by another General to part with my
troops. The arrangement whereby I have to sponge on <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> for men if<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>want them is a detestable arrangement. At the last he consented to cable
<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> direct on the point himself and then he is to let me know. Two things
are quite certain; <unit type="brigade">the Brigade</unit> are not wanted in <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location>. Old campaigners
versed in Egyptian war lore tell me that the drying up of the wells must
put the lid on to any move across the desert until the winter rains,
and, apart from this, how in the name of the beard of their own false
prophet can the Turks attack <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> whilst we are at the gates of
<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>?</p>

<p>But if the Brigade are not wanted on the Canal, we are bound to be the
better for them at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>, whatever course matters there may
take. Concentration is the cue! The German or Japanese General Staffs
would tumble to these truths and act upon them presto. <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> sees them too,
but nothing can overcome his passion for playing off one Commander
against another, whereby <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> of <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> keeps all reins in his hands and
remains sole arbiter between them.</p>

<p>Birdwood has just turned up. We're off to-morrow evening.</p>

<p>'Phoned Maxwell last thing telling him to be sure not to forget to jog
<person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s elbow about <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person> and his Gurkhas.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_7th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian."</location> 10 p.m._ <person name="Albert_d'Amade">D'Amade</person> looked in to say
good-bye.</p>

<p>On my way down to the harbour I overhauled the Assyrian Jewish Refugee
Mule Corps at the Wardian Camp. Their Commander, author of that
thrilling shocker, "The Man-killers of Tsavo," finds Assyrians and mules
rather a mouthful and is going to tabloid bipeds and quadrupeds into
"The Zion Corps." The mules look very fit; so do the Assyrians and,
although I did not notice that their cohorts were gleaming with purple
or gold, they may help us to those habiliments: they may, in fact, serve
as ground bait to entice the big Jew journalists and bankers towards our
cause; the former will lend us the colour, the latter the coin. Anyway,
so far as I can, I mean to give the chosen people a chance.</p>

<p>Got aboard at 5.15, but owing to some hitch in the arrangements for
filling up our tanks with fresh water, we are held up and won't get off
until to-morrow morning.</p>

<p>If there drops a gnat into the ointment of the General, be sure there
are ten thousand flies stinking the ointment of the troops.</p></entry>
  
<entry><p>_8th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian</location>."_ Sailing free to the Northwards. A
fine day and a smooth sea. What would not Richard Coeur de Lion or
Napoleon have given for the <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">_Arcadian_</location> to take them to St. Jean d'Acre
and <location city="Jerusalem">Jerusalem</location>?</p>

<p>As we were clearing harbour a letter was brought out to us by a launch:</p>

<p>                                                       "UNION CLUB,
                                                          "<location city="Alexandria">ALEXANDRIA</location>.</p>

<p>"The following telephone received from General Maxwell, Cairo:--Your
message re <person name="Herbert_Cox">Cox</person>, I will do my best to meet your wishes. Will you in your
turn assist me in getting the seaplanes arriving here in _Ganges_?<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>have wired to <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral de Robeck</person>, I want them badly, so please help me if
you can.</p>

<p>                 "_Forwarded by_ ADMIRAL ROBINSON."</p>

<p>Cutlet for cutlet! I wish it had occurred to me sooner to do a deal with
some aeroplanes. But, then I have none. No matter: I should have
promised him <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>'s! South Africa repeats itself! Egypt and Mudros
are not one but two. <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> and I are co-equal allies; _not_ a combine
under a Boss!</p></entry>

<chapter n="4" heading="CLEARING FOR ACTION"> CHAPTER IV</chapter>
  
<entry><p>_9th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian</location>."_ Isles of the Aegean; one more lovely
than the other; weather warm; wireless off; a great ship steaming fast
towards a great adventure--why do I walk up and down the deck feeling a
ton's weight of trouble weighing down upon my shoulders? Never till
to-day has solicitude become painful. This is the fault of Birdwood,
Hunter-Weston and Paris. I read their "appreciations of the situation"
some days ago, but until to-day I have not had the unbroken hour needed
to digest them. Birdwood begins by excusing himself in advance against
any charge of vacillation. At our first meeting he said he was convinced
our best plan would be to go for the South of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location>.
Now he has, in fact, very much shifted his ground under the influence of
a new consideration, "(which I only learned after leaving <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>) that
the Turks now have guns or howitzers on the Asiatic side which could
actually command our transports should they anchor off <location coast="Morto_Bay">Morto Bay</location>." "As<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>told you," he says, "after thinking it out thoroughly, I was convinced
our best plan would be to go for the South of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location>,"
but now he continues, he finds his Staff "all seem to be keen on a
landing somewhere between <location coast="Saros_Gulf">Saros Bay</location> and Enos. For this I have no use, as
though I think we should doubtless be able to effect a landing there
pretty easily, yet I do not see that we shall be any 'forrarder' by
doing so. We might put ourselves in front of the <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location> Lines, but there
would be far less object in attacking them and working South-west with
the Navy only partially able to help us, than by working up from the
other end with the Navy on either flank."</p>

<p>Birdwood himself rather inclines towards a landing on the Asiatic side,
for preference somewhere South of <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location>. The attractive part of his
idea is that if we did this the Turks must withdraw most of their mobile
artillery from <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> to meet us, which would give the Navy just
the opportunity they require for mine-sweeping and so forcing the
Narrows forthwith. They know they can give the superstition of old Forts
being stronger than new ships its quietus if only they can clear a
passage through the minefield. There are forts and forts, ships and
ships, no doubt. But from what we have done already the sailors know
that our ships here can knock out those forts here. But first they must
tackle the light guns which protect the minefield from the sweepers.
Birdwood seems to think we might dominate <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> from the country
round Chunuk. In his P.S. he suggests that anyway, if we are beaten off
in our attempt to land on <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> we may have this Asiatic scheme
in our mind as a second string. Disembarkation plans already made would
"probably be suitable _anywhere_ with very slight modifications. We
might perhaps even think of this--if we try the other first and can't
pull it off?"</p>

<p>In my answer, I say I am still for taking the shortest, most direct
route to my objective, the Narrows.</p>

<p>First, because "I have no roving commission to conquer Asia Minor." My
instructions deny me the whole of that country when they lay down as a
principle that "The occupation of the Asiatic side by military forces is
to be strongly deprecated."</p>

<p>Secondly, because I agree that a landing between <location coast="Saros_Gulf">Saros Bay</location> and Enos
would leave us no "forrarder." There we should be attacked in front from
Rodosto; in flank from Adrianople; in rear from <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>; whilst, as we
advanced, we would lose touch with the Fleet. But if our scheme is to be
based on severance from the Fleet we must delay another month or six
weeks to collect pack transport.</p>

<p>Thirdly, the Asiatic side _does not_ dominate <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> whereas the
  <location heights="Kilid Bahr">Kilid Bahr plateau</location>  _does_ dominate the Asiatic narrows.</p>

<p>Fourthly, the whole point of our being here is to work hand-in-glove
with the Fleet. We are here to help get the Fleet through the
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> in the first instance and to help the Russians to take
<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location> in the second. The War Office, the Admiralty, the
Vice-Admiral and the French Commander-in-Chief all agree now that the
Peninsula is the best place for our first step towards these objects.</p>

<p><person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston's</person> appreciation, written on his way out at Malta, is a
masterly piece of work. He understands clearly that our true objective
is to let our warships through the Narrows to attack <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>.
"The immediate object," he says, "of operations in the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> is to
enable our warships, with the necessary colliers and other unarmoured
supply ships--without which capital ships cannot maintain themselves--to
pass through the Straits in order to attack <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>."</p>

<p>And again:--</p>

<p>"It is evident that land operations at this stage must be directed
entirely towards assisting the Fleet; and no operations should be
commenced unless it is clear that their result will be to enable our
warships, with their necessary colliers, etc., to have the use of the
Straits."</p>

<p>The Fleet, he holds, cannot do this without our help because of:--</p>

<p>  (1). Improvement of the defences.
  (2). The mobile howitzers.
  (3). The Leon floating mines.</p>

<p>Things being so, he sets himself to consider how far the Army can help,
in the light of the following premises:--</p>

<p>"The Turkish Army having been warned by our early bombardments and by
the landings carried out some time ago, has concentrated a large force
in and near <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location>."</p>

<p>"It has converted <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> into an entrenched camp, has, under
German direction, made several lines of entrenchments covering the
landing places, with concealed machine gun emplacements and land mines
on the beach; and has put in concealed positions guns and howitzers
capable of covering the landing places and approaches with their fire."</p>

<p>"The Turkish Army in <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> is being supplied and reinforced from
the Asiatic side and from the Sea of Marmora and is not dependent on the
Isthmus of <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>. The passage of the Isthmus of <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location> by troops and
supplies at night cannot be denied by the guns of our Fleet."</p>

<p>After estimates of our forces and of the difficulties they may expect to
encounter, Hunter-Weston comes to the conclusion that, "the only landing
places worth serious consideration are:</p>

<p>  "(1). Those near Cape Suvla,
   (2). Those near <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location>."</p>

<p>Of these two he advises <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Helles</location>, because:--"the Fleet can also surround
this end of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> and bring a concentrated fire on any Turks
holding it. We, therefore, should be able to make sure of securing the
<location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi Baba</location> position." Also, because our force is too weak to hold the big
country round <location coast="Suvla_Bay">Suvla Bay</location> and at the same time operate against <location heights="Kilid Bahr">Kilid Bahr</location>.</p>

<p>If this landing at <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Helles</location> is successful, he considers the probable
further course of the operations. Broadly, he thinks that we are so
short of ammunition and particularly of high explosive shell that there
is every prospect of our getting tied up on an extended line across the
Peninsula in front of the <location heights="Kilid Bahr">Kilid Bahr</location> trenches. Should the enemy
submarines arrive we should be "up a tree."</p>

<p>The cards in the game of life are the characters of men. Staking on
those cards I take my own opinions--always. But when we play the game of
death, things are our counters--guns, rivers, shells, bread, roads,
forests, ships--and in totting up the values of these my friend
Hunter-Weston has very few equals in the Army.</p>

<p>Therefore, his conclusion depresses me very much, but not so much as it
would have done had I not seen him. For certainly during his conference
on the 30th March with <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person> and myself he never said or implied in
any way that under conditions as he found them and as they were then set
before him, there was no reasonable prospect of success:--quite the
contrary. Here are the conclusions as written at Malta:--</p>

<p>"Conclusion. The information available goes to show that if this
Expedition had been carefully and secretly prepared in <location country="England">England</location>, <location country="France">France</location>
and <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location>, and the Naval and Military details of organisation, equipment
and disembarkation carefully worked out by the General Staff and the
Naval War Staff, and if no bombardment or other warning had been given
till the troops, landing gear, etc., were all ready and despatched, (the
troops from <location country="England">England</location> ostensibly for service in <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> and those in <location country="Egypt">Egypt</location>
ostensibly for service in <location country="France">France</location>) the capture of the Gallipoli
Peninsula and the forcing of the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> would have been successful.</p>

<p>"Von der Goltz is reported to have visited the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> on 11th
February and before that date it appears that very little had been done.</p>

<p>"Now big guns have been brought from <location region="Chatalja">Chatalja</location>, <location city="Adrianople">Adrianople</location> and
elsewhere,--roads have been made,--heavy movable armaments
provided,--troops and machine guns have been poured into the
Peninsula,--several lines of trenches have been dug,--every landing
place has been trenched and mined, and all that clever German Officers
under Von der Goltz can design, and hard working diggers like the Turks
can carry out, has been done to make <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> impregnable.</p>

<p>"The prizes of success in this Expedition are very great.</p>

<p>"It was indeed the most hopeful method of finishing the war.</p>

<p>"No loss would be too heavy and no risks too great if thereby success
would be attained.</p>

<p>"But if the views expressed in this paper be sound, there is not in
present circumstances a reasonable chance of success. (The views are
founded on the information available to the writer at the time of
leaving <location island="Malta">Malta</location>, and may be modified by further information at first hand
on arrival at Force Head Quarters.)</p>

<p>"The return of the Expedition when it has gone so far will cause
discontent, much talk, and some laughter; will confirm Roumania and
Greece in the wisdom of their neutrality, and will impair the power of
our valuable friend M. Venezelos. It will be a heavy blow to all of us
soldiers, and will need great strength and moral courage on the part of
the Commander and Government.</p>

<p>"But it will not do irreparable harm to our cause, whereas to attempt a
landing and fail to secure a passage through the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> would be a
disaster to the Empire.</p>

<p>"The threat of invasion by the Allies is evidently having considerable
effect on the Balkan States.</p>

<p>"It is therefore advisable to continue our preparations;--to train our
troops for landing, and to get our expedition properly equipped and
organised for this difficult operation of war; so as to be ready to take
advantage of any opportunity for successful action that may occur.</p>

<p>"But I would repeat; no action should be taken unless it has been
carefully thought out in all its possibilities and details and unless
there is a reasonable _probability_ of success.</p>

<p>                                              "<person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">A. HUNTER-WESTON, M.G.</person>"</p>

<p><person name="Archibald_Paris">Paris's</person> appreciation gives no very clear lead. "The enemy is of strength
unknown," he says, "but within striking distance there must be 250,000."
He also lays stress on the point that the enemy are expecting
us--"Surprise is now impossible--.... The difficulties are now increased
a hundredfold.... To land would be difficult enough if surprise was
possible but hazardous in the extreme under present conditions." He
discusses <location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location> as a landing place; also <location city="Smyrna">Smyrna</location>, and <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>. On the
whole, he favours <location town="Sedd-el-Bahr">Sedd-el-Bahr</location> as it "is the only place where transports
could come in close and where the actual landing may be unopposed. It is
open to question whether a landing could be effected elsewhere. With the
aid of the Fleet it may be possible to land near <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location> almost
unopposed and an advance of ten miles would enormously facilitate the
landing of the remainder South of <location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location>."</p>

<p>The truth is, every one of these fellows agrees in his heart with old
Von der Goltz, the Berlin experts, and the <person name="Sultan_Kamel">Sultan of Egypt</person> that the
landing is impossible. Well, we shall see, D.V., we shall see!! One
thing is certain: we must work up our preparations to the _n_th degree
of perfection: the impossible can only be overborne by the
unprecedented; i.e., by an original method or idea.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_10th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian</location>." <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ Cast anchor at 7 a.m. After
breakfast went on board the _Queen Elizabeth_ where <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> and<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>worked for three hours with <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral de Robeck</person>, Admiral Wemyss and
<person name="Roger_Keyes">Commodore Roger Keyes</person>.</p>

<p>Last time <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">the Admiral</person> made the running; to-day it was my turn for I had
to unfold my scheme and go through it point by point with the sailors.
But first I felt it my duty to read out the appreciations of
Hunter-Weston, Birdwood and Paris. Then I gave them my own view that
history had never offered any nation so clean cut a chance of bringing
off an immeasurably big coup as she had done by putting our Fleet and
Army precisely where it was at present on the map of the war world. Half
that unique chance had already been muddled away by the lack of secrecy
and swiftness in our methods. With check mate within our grasp we had
given two moves to the enemy. Still, perhaps; nay, probably, there was
time. Were we to prolong hesitation, or, were we, now that we had done
the best we could with the means under our hands, to go boldly forward?
Here was the great issue: there was no use discussing detail until the
principle was settled. By God's mercy the <person name="John_de_Robeck">Vice-Admiral</person>, <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Wemyss</person> and <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>
were all quite clear and quite determined. They rejected <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>; they
rejected Asia; most of all they spurned the thought of further delay or
of hanging about hoping for something to turn up.</p>

<p>So I then told them my plan. The more, I said, I had pondered over the
map and reflected upon the character, probable numbers and supposed
positions of the enemy, the more convinced I had become that the first
and foremost step towards a victorious landing was to upset the
equilibrium of Liman von Sanders, the enemy Commander who has succeeded
Djavad in the Command of the Fifth Army. I must try to move so that he
should be unable to concentrate either his mind or his men against us.
Here I was handicapped by having no knowledge of my opponent whereas the
German General Staff is certain to have transferred the "life-like
picture" Schroeder told me they had of me to <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>. Still, sea
power and the mobility it confers is a great help, and we ought to be
able to rattle the enemy however imperturbable may be his nature and
whatever he knows about us if we throw every man we can carry in our
small craft in one simultaneous rush against selected points, whilst
using all the balance in feints against other likely places. Prudence
here is entirely out of place. There will be and can be no
reconnaissance, no half measures, no tentatives. Several cautious
proposals have been set before me but this is neither the time nor the
place for paddling about the shore putting one foot on to the beaches
with the idea of drawing it back again if it happens to alight upon a
land mine. No; we've got to take a good run at <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> and jump
plump on--both feet together. At a given moment we must plunge and stake
everything on the one hazard.</p>

<p>I would like to land my whole force in one,--like a hammer stroke--with
the fullest violence of its mass effect--as close as I can to my
  objective, the <location heights="Kilid Bahr">Kilid Bahr plateau</location> . But, apart from lack of small craft,
the thing cannot be done; the beach space is so cramped that the men and
their stores could not be put ashore. I have to separate my forces and
the effect of momentum, which cannot be produced by cohesion, must be
reproduced by the simultaneous nature of the movement. From the South,
<location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi Baba</location> mountain is our first point of attack, and the direct move
against it will start from the beaches at <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location> and <location town="Sedd-el-Bahr">Sedd-el-Bahr</location>.
As it is believed that the Turks are there in some force to oppose us,
envelopment will be attempted by landing detachments in <location coast="Morto_Bay">Morto Bay</location> and
opposite <location town="Krithia">Krithia</location> village. At the same time, also, the A. and N.Z. Corps
will land between <location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location> and Fisherman's Hut to try and seize the
high backbone of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> and cut the line of retreat of the enemy
on the <location heights="Kilid Bahr">Kilid Bahr plateau</location>. In any case, the move is bound to interfere
with the movements of Turkish reinforcements towards the toe of the
Peninsula. While these real attacks are taking place upon the foot and
at the waist of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>, the knife will be flourished at its neck.
Transports containing troops which cannot be landed during the first two
days must sail up to <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>; make as much splash as they can with their
small boats and try to provide matter for alarm wires to <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>
and the enemy's Chief.</p>

<p>So much for Europe. Asia is forbidden but I hold myself free, as a
measure of battle tactics, to take half a step Troywards. The French are
to land a Brigade at<location town=" Kum Kale"> Kum Kale</location> (perhaps a Regiment may do) so as, first,
to draw the fire of any enemy big guns which can range <location coast="Morto_Bay">Morto Bay</location>;
secondly, to prevent Turkish troops being shipped across the Narrows.</p>

<p>With luck, then, within the space of an hour, the enemy Chief will be
beset by a series of S.O.S. signals. Over an area of 100 miles, from
five or six places; from <location town="Krithia">Krithia</location> and <location coast="Morto_Bay">Morto Bay</location>; from <location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location>; from
<location town="Bulair">Bulair</location> and from<location town=" Kum Kale"> Kum Kale</location> in Asia, as well as, if the French can manage
it, from <location coast="Besica_Bay">Besika Bay</location>, the cables will pour in. I reckon Liman von
Sanders will not dare concentrate and that he will fight with his local
troops only for the first forty-eight hours. But what is the number of
these local troops? Alas, there is the doubtful point. We think forty
thousand rifles and a hundred guns, but, if my scheme comes off, not a
tenth of them should be South of <location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi Baba</location> for the first two days. Hints
have been thrown out that we are asking the French cat to pull the
hottest chestnut out of the fire. Not at all. At<location town=" Kum Kale"> Kum Kale</location>, with their
own ships at their back, and the deep <location coast="Mendere_River">Mendere River</location> to their front,
<person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade's</person> men should easily be able to hold their own for a day or
two,--all that we ask of them.</p>

<p>The backbone of my enterprise is the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit>. At dawn I intend to
land the covering force of that Division at <location town="Sedd-el-Bahr">Sedd-el-Bahr</location>, <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location>
and, D.V., in <location coast="Morto_Bay">Morto Bay</location>. I tack my D.V. on to <location coast="Morto_Bay">Morto Bay</location> because the
transports will there be under fire from Asia unless the French succeed
in silencing the guns about Troy or in diverting their aim. Whether then
our transports can stick it or not is uncertain, like everything else in
war, only more so. They must if they can and if they can they must; that
is all that can be said at present.</p>

<p>As to the effort to be made to envelop the enemy's right flank along the
coast between <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Helles</location> and <location town="Krithia">Krithia</location>, I have not yet quite fixed on the
exact spot, but I am personally bent upon having it done as even a small
force so landed should threaten the line of retreat and tend to shake
the confidence of any Turks resisting us at the Southernmost point.
Some think these cliffs along that North-west coast unclimbable, but<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>am sure our fellows will manage to scramble up, and I think their losses
should be less in doing so than in making the more easy seeming lodgment
at <location town="Sedd-el-Bahr">Sedd-el-Bahr</location> or Helles. The more broken and precipitous the glacis,
the more the ground leading up to the objective is dead. The guns of the
Fleet can clear the crest of the cliffs and the strip of sand at their
foot should then be as healthy as Brighton. If the Turks down at Helles
are nervous, even a handful landing behind their first line (stretching
from the old Castle Northwards to the coast) should make them begin to
look over their shoulders.</p>

<p>As to the A. and N.Z. landing, that will be of the nature of a strong
feint, which may, and we hope will, develop into the real thing. My
General Staff have marked out on the maps a good circular holding
position, starting from Fisherman's Hut in the North round along the
Upper Spurs of the high ridges and following them down to where they
reach the sea, a little way above <location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location>. If only Birdwood can seize
this line and fix himself there for a bit, he should in due course be
able to push on forward to Kojah Dere whence he will be able to choke
the Turks on the Southern part of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> with a closer grip and a
more deadly than we could ever hope to exercise from far away <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>.</p>

<p>We are bound to suffer serious loss from concealed guns, both on the sea
and also during the first part of our landing before we can win ground
for our guns. That is part of the hardness of the nut. The landings at
<location coast="Gaba Tepe">Gaba Tepe</location> and to the South will between them take up all our small craft
and launches. So I am unable to throw <unit type="division">the Naval Division</unit> into action at
the first go off. They will man the transports that sail to make a show
at <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>.</p>

<p>This is the substance of my opening remarks at the meeting: discussion
followed, and, at the end, the Navy signified full approval. Neither <person name="John_de_Robeck">de
Robeck</person>, <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Wemyss</person> nor <person name="Roger_Keyes">Roger Keyes</person> are men to buy pigs in pokes; they wanted
to know all about it and to be quite sure they could play their part in
the programme. Their agreement is all the more precious. They (the
Admirals and the Commodore) are also, I fancy, happier in their minds
now that they know for sure what we soldiers are after. Rumours had been
busy in the Fleet that we were shaping our course for <location town="Bulair">Bulair</location>. Had that
been the basis of my plan, we should have come to loggerheads, I think.
As it is, the sailors seem eager to meet us in every possible way. So
now we've got to get our orders out.</p>

<p>On maps and charts the scheme may look neat and simple. On land and
water, the trouble will begin and only by the closest thought and
prevision will we find ourselves in a position to cope with it. To throw
so many men ashore in so short a time in the teeth of so rapid a current
on to a few cramped beaches; to take the chances of finding drinking
water and of a smooth sea; these elemental hazards alone would suffice
to give a man grey hairs were we practising a manoeuvre exercise on
the peaceful Essex coast. So much thought; so much _band-o-bast_; so
much dove-tailing and welding together of naval and military methods,
signals, technical words, etc., and the worst punishment should any link
in the composite chain give way. And then--taking success for
granted--on the top of all this--comes the Turk; "unspeakable" he used
to be, "unknowable" now. But we shall give him a startler too. If only
our plans come off the Turk won't have time to turn; much less to bring
into play all the clever moves foreseen for him by some whose stomachs
for the fight have been satisfied by their appreciation of its dangers.</p>

<p>Units of the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> have been coming along in their transports
all day. The bay is alive with ships.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_11th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian.</location>"_ One of those exquisite days when
the sunlight penetrates to the heart. <person name="Emile_Guepratte">Admiral Guepratte</person>, commanding the
French Fleet, called at 9.45 and in due course I returned his visit,
when I was electrified to find at his cabin door no common sentry but a
Beefeater armed with a large battleaxe, dating from about the period of
Charlemagne. The Admiral lives quite in the old style and is a
delightful personage; very gay and very eager for a chance to measure
himself against the enemy. <person name="Emile_Guepratte">Guepratte</person>, though he knows nothing
officially, believes that his Government are holding up their sleeve a
second French Division ear-marked Gallipoli! But why bottle up trumps;
trumps worth a King's ransome, or a Kaiser's? He gives twice who gives
quickly (in peace); he gives tenfold who gives quickly (in war). The
devil of it is the French dare not cable home to ask questions, and as
for myself, I have not been much encouraged--so far!</p>

<p>During the afternoon Admirals <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> and <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Wemyss</person> came on board to work
together with the General Staff on technical details. They too have
heard these rumours about the second French Division, and Wemyss is in
dismay at the thought of having to squeeze more ships into <location coast="Mudros_Harbour">Mudros
harbour</location>. His anxiety has given me exactly the excuse I wanted, so I have
dropped this fly just in front of <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s nose, telling him that "There are
persistent rumours here amongst the French that <person name="Albert_d'Amade">General d'Amade</person>'s
Command is to be joined by another French Division. Just in case there
is truth in the report you should know that <location coast="Mudros_Harbour">Mudros harbour</location> is as full as
it will hold until our dash for <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> has been made." We will
see what he says. If the Division exists, then the Naval people will
recommend Bizerta for their base; the ships can sail right up to the
Peninsula from there and land right away until things on <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location> and
<location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location> have shaken themselves down.</p>

<p>Our first Taube: it passed over the harbour at a great height. One of
our lumbering seaplanes went up after it like an owl in sunlight, but
could rise no higher than the masts of the Fleet.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_12th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian."</location> <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ The _Queen Elizabeth_ has
been having some trouble with her engines and in the battle of the 18th
was only able to use one of her propellers. Now she has been overhauled
and the Admiral has asked me to come on board for her steam trials.
These are to take place along the coastline of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location> and I have
got leave to bring with me a party selected from Divisions and Brigades.
So when I went aboard this morning at 8.30 there were about thirty-five
Officers present. Starting at once, we steamed at great pace half way up
the <location coast="Saros_Gulf">Gulf of Saros</location> and about 1 o'clock turned to go back, slowing down
and closing in to let me take a second good look at the coast. Our
studies were enlivened by an amusing incident. Nearing <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location>, the
_Queen Elizabeth_ went astern, so as to test her reverse turbines. The
enemy, who must have been watching us like a mouse does a cat, had the
ill-luck to select just this moment to salute us with a couple of
shells. As they had been allowing for our speed they were ludicrously
out of it, the shot striking the water half a mile ahead. We then lay
off <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location> whilst a very careful survey of the whole of that
section was being made. The Turks, disgusted by their own bad aim, did
not fire again. On our way back we passed three fakes, old liners
painted up, funnelled and armed with dummy guns to take off the _Tiger_,
the _Inflexible_ and the _Indomitable_. Riding at anchor there, they had
quite the man-o'-war air and if they draw the teeth of enemy submarines
(their torpedoes), as they are meant to do, the artists should be given
decorations. At 6 p.m. dropped anchor and I transhipped myself to the
<location ship="S.S._Arcadian">_Arcadian_</location>. Birdwood and Hunter-Weston had turned up during the day; the
latter dined and is now more sanguine than myself. He has been getting
to know his new command better and he says that he did not appreciate
the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> when he wrote his appreciation!</p></entry>

<entry><p>_13th April, <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">1915. S.S. "Arcadian."</location>_ Heavy squalls of rain and wind last
night. _Band-o-bast_ badly upset; boats also bottoms upwards and at
dawn--here in harbour--we found ourselves clean cut off from the shore.
What a ticklish affair the great landing is going to be! How much at the
mercy of the winds and waves! Aeolus and Neptune have hardly lost power
since Greeks and Trojans made history out yonder!</p>

<p>Have sent <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> an electrical pick-me-up saying that the height of the
_Queen Elizabeth_ fire control station had enabled me to see the lie of
the land better than on my previous reconnaissance, and that, given good
luck, we hope to get ashore without too great a loss.</p>

<p>In the afternoon the wind moderated and I spent an hour or two watching
practice landings by Senegalese. Our delay is loss, but yet not clear
loss; that's a sure thing. These niggy-wigs were as awkward as
golly-wogs in the boats. Every extra hour's practice will save some
lives by teaching them how to make short work of the ugliest bit of
their job.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_14th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian,"</location> <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ A day so exquisitely lovely
that it should be chronicled in deathless verse. But we gaze at the
glassy sea and turn to the deep blue cloudless sky, victory our only
thought.</p>

<p>Colonel Dick, King's Messenger, has arrived bringing letters up to 3rd
instant. Or rather, he was supposed to have brought them, and it was
hoped the abundance of his intelligence would have borne some relation
to the cost of his journey,--about L80 it has been reckoned. As a matter
of fact, apart from some rubbish, he brings _one_ letter for me; none
for any of the others. Not even a file of newspapers; not even a
newspaper! In India many, many years ago, we used to call Dick _Burra
dik hai_, Hindustani for, _it is a great worry_. So he is only playing
up to his sobriquet. The little ewe lamb is an epistle from Fitz giving
me a lively sketch of the rumpus at the War Office when its pontiffs
grasped for the first time the true bearing of their own orders. There
was a rush to saddle poor us with the delay as soon as the Cabinet began
to show impatience. They seem to have expected the <unit type="division">29th Division</unit> to
arrive at top speed in a united squadron to rush straightway ashore.
They don't yet quite realise, I daresay, that not one of their lovely
ships has yet put in an appearance. That the men who packed the
transports and fixed their time tables should say we are too slow is
hardly playing the game.</p>

<p>Never lose your hair: that is a good soldier's motto. My cable of last
night, wherein I tried to calm their minds by telling them the sea was
rough and that, even if every one had been here with gaiter buttons
complete, I must have waited for a change in the weather, has answered
Fitz's letter by anticipation.</p>

<p>Worked all day in my office like a nigger and by mid-day had got almost
as black as my simile! We are coaling and life has grown dark and noisy.
In the middle of it, Ashmead-Bartlett came aboard to see me. He has his
quarters on the _Queen Elizabeth_ as one of the Admiralty authorised
Press Correspondents, or rather, as the only authorised correspondent.
In Manchuria he was known and his writing was well liked. When he had
gone, <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> and I put through a good lot of business very smoothly.
A little later on, Captain Ivanoff, commanding H.I.M.S. _Askold_, (a
Russian cruiser well-known to fame in Manchurian days), did me the
honour to call.</p>

<p>After lunch went ashore and saw parties of Australians at embarking and
disembarking drill. Colonel Paterson, the very man who bear-led me on
tour during my Australian inspection, was keeping an eye on the "Boys."
The work of the Australians and Senegalese gave us a good object lesson
of the relative brain capacities of the two races. Next I went and
inspected the Armoured Car Section of the <unit type="division">Royal Naval Division</unit> under
Lieutenant-Commander Wedgwood. He is a mighty queer chap. Took active
part in the South African War. Afterwards became a pacifist M.P.; here
he is again with war paint and tomahawk. Give me a Pacifist in peace and
a Jingo in war. Too often it is the other way about.</p>

<p>All this took me on to 5.30 p.m. and when I came back on board,
Hunter-Weston was here. He has been out since last night on <location ship="H.M.S._Dathmouth">H.M.S.
_Dartmouth_</location> to inspect the various landing places. His whole tone about
the Expedition has been transformed. Now he has become the most sanguine
of us all. He has great hopes that we shall have <location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi Baba</location> in our hands
by sunset on the day of landing. If so he thinks we need have no fear
for the future.</p>

<p>All is worked out now and I do not quite see how we could improve upon
our scheme with the means at our disposal. If these "means" included a
larger number of boats and steam launches, then certainly, by
strengthening our forces on either flank, viz., at <location coast="Morto_Bay">Morto Bay</location> (where we
are sending only one Battalion) and at a landing under the cliffs a mile
West of <location town="Krithia">Krithia</location> (where we are sending one Battalion), we should greatly
better our chances. Also, a battery of field guns attached to the Morto
Bay column, and a couple of mountain guns added to the <location town="Krithia">Krithia</location> column
would add to our prospects of making a real big scoop. But we cannot
spare the sea transport except by too much weakening and delaying the
landing at the point of <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>; nor dare I leave myself without
any reserve under my own hand. I am inclined, all the same, to squeeze
one Marine Battalion out of the <unit type="division">Naval Division</unit> to strengthen our threat
to <location town="Krithia">Krithia</location>. Hunter-Weston will be in executive command of everything
South of <location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi Baba</location>; Birdwood of everything to the North.</p>

<p>I went very closely with Hunter-Weston into the question of a day or
night attack. My own leanings are in favour of the first boat-loads
getting ashore before break of dawn, but Hunter-Weston is clear and
strong for daylight. There is a very strong current running round the
point; the exact lie of the beaches is unknown and he thinks the
confusion inseparable from any landing will be so aggravated by
attempting it in the dark that he had rather face the losses the men in
boats must suffer from aimed fire. Executively he is responsible and he
is backed by his naval associates.</p>

<p>Birdwood, on the other hand, is of one mind with me and is going to get
his first boat-loads ashore before it is light enough to aim. He has no
current to trouble him, it is true, but he is not landing on any
surveyed beach and the opposition he will meet with is even more unknown
than in the case of Helles and <location town="Sedd-el-Bahr">Sedd-el-Bahr</location>.</p>

<p>When a sportsman goes shark fishing, he should beware lest he be
mistaken for the bait. Gaily I cast my fly over <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> and now he has
snapped off my head. That story about a second French Division was
false. <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> merely quotes the number of my question and adds, "The rumour
is baseless." Well, "_tant pis_," as Guepratte would say with a shrug of
his shoulders. Our first step won't have the weight behind it we had
permitted ourselves for some hours to hope. _Everywhere_ the first is
the step that counts but _nowhere_ more so than in an Oriental War.</p>

<p>Now that the French Division has been snuffed out, how about the Grand
Duke Nicholas, General Istomine and their Russian Divisions? Are they
also to prove phantoms? Certainly, in some form or another, they ought
to be brought into our scheme and, even if only at a distance, bring
some pressure to bear upon the Turks at the time of our opening move.<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>think my best way of getting into touch will be by wireless from de
Robeck to the Russian Admiral in the Black Sea.</p>

<p>Dick dines, also Birdwood.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_15th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian."</location> <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ Boarded <location ship="H.M.S._Dublin">H.M.S. _Dublin_</location>
(Captain Kelly) at 9.30 this morning, where <person name="John_de_Robeck">Admiral de Robeck</person> met me.
Sailed at once and dropped anchor off <location island="Tenedos">Tenedos</location> at noon.</p>

<p>Landed and made a close inspection of the Aerodrome where we were taken
round by two young friends of mine, Commander Samson and Captain Davies,
Naval Air Service. By a queer fluke these are the very two men with whom<person name="Ian_Hamilton">
I </person>did my very first flight! On that never to be forgotten day Samson
took up <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person> and Davies took me. Like mallards we shot over the
Medway and saw the battleships as if they were little children's
playthings far away down below us. Now the children are going to use
their pretty toys and will make a nice noise with them in the world.</p>

<p>After lunch spent the best part of two hours in a small cottage with
Samson and <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person> trying to digest the honey brought back by our busy
aeroplane bees from their various flights over Gallipoli. The Admiral
went off on some other naval quest.</p>

<p>Samson and Davies are fliers of the first water--and not only in the
air. They carry the whole technique of their job at their finger tips.
The result of <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>'s washing his hands of the Air is that the Admiralty
run that element entirely. Samson is Boss. He has brought with him two
Maurice Farmans and three B.E.2s. The Maurice Farmans with 100 H.P.
Renaults; the B.E.2s with 70 Renaults. These five machines are good
although one of the B.E.2s is dead old.</p>

<p>Also, he brought eight Henri Farmans with 80 Gnome engines. He took them
because they were new and there was nothing else new; but they are no
use for war.</p>

<p>Two B.E.2C.s with 70 Renaults: these are absolutely useless as they
won't take a passenger.</p>

<p>One Broguet 200 H.P. Canton engine; won't fly.</p>

<p>Two Sopwith Scouts: 80 Gnome engines; very old and can't be used owing
to weakness of engine mounting.</p>

<p>One very old but still useful Maurice Farman with 140 Canton engine.
That is the demnition total and it pans out at five serviceable
aeroplanes for the Army. There are also some seaplanes with us but they
are not under Samson, and are purely for naval purposes. Amongst those
are two good "Shorts," but the others are no use, they say, being wrong
type and underpowered.</p>

<p>The total nominal strength of Samson's Corps is eleven pilots and one
hundred and twenty men. As everyone knows, no Corps or Service is ever
up to its nominal strength; least of all an Air Corps. The dangerous
shortage is that in two-seater aeroplanes as we want our Air Service now
for spotting and reconnaissances. If, _after_ that requirement had been
met, we had only a bombing force at our disposal, the Gallipoli
Peninsula, being a very limited space with only one road and two or
three harbours on it, could probably be made untenable.</p>

<p>Commander Samson's estimate of a minimum force for this "stunt," as he
calls our great enterprise, is 30 good two-seater machines; 24 fighters;
40 pilots and 400 men. So equipped he reckons he could take the
Peninsula by himself and save us all a vast lot of trouble.</p>

<p>But, strange as it may seem, flying is not my "stunt." I dare not even
mention the word "aeroplane" to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>, and I have cut myself off from
correspondence with <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person>. I did this thing deliberately as
<person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> reminds me every time I am tempted to sit down and unbosom
myself to one who would sympathise and lend us a hand if he could: in
truth, I am torn in two about this; but I still feel it is wiser and
better so; not only from the <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> point of view but also from <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>'s.
He (<person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>) might be quite glad I should write once to <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston</person> on one
subject but he would never be sure afterwards I was not writing on
others. On the way back I spoke to the Admiral, but I don't know whether
he will write himself or not. Ventured also a little bit out of my own
element in another direction, and begged him not to put off sending the
submarine through the Straits until the day of our landing, but to let
her go directly she was ready. He does not agree. He has an idea (I hope
a premonition) that the submarine will catch Enver hurrying down to the
scene of action if we wait till the day of the attack.</p>

<p>Even more than in the Fleet I find in the Air Service the profound
conviction that, if they could only get into direct touch with <person name="Winston_Churchil">Winston Churchill</person>
, all would be well. Their faith in the <person name="Winston_Churchil">First Lord</person> is, in every
sense, _touching_. But they can't get the contact and they are
thoroughly imbued with the idea that the Sea Lords are at the best
half-hearted; at the worst, actively antagonistic to us and to the whole
of our enterprise. The photographs, etc., I have studied make it only
too clear that the Turks have not let the grass grow under their feet
since the first bombardment; <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Peninsula</location>, in fact, is better defended
than it was. _Per contra_ the momentum, precision, swiftness and staying
power of our actual attack will be at least twice as great now as it
would have been at the end of March.</p>

<p>Returned to <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location> about 7.30 p.m.</p>

<p>While we were away my Staff got aboard the destroyer <location ship="H.M.S._Colne">_Colne_</location> and steamed
in her to the mouth of the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>. There the whole precious load of
red tabs transshipped to <location ship="H.M.S._Triumph">H.M.S. _Triumph_</location> (Captain Fitzmaurice), who
forthwith took up her station opposite <location coast="Morto_Bay">Morto Bay</location> and began firing salvos
with her 6-inch guns at the trenches on the face of the hill. At first
the Staff watched the show with much enjoyment from the bridge, but
when howitzers from the Asiatic side began to lob shell over the ship,
the Captain hustled them all into the conning tower. The Turks seem to
have shot pretty straight. The first three fell fifty yards short of the
ship; the fourth shell about twenty yards over her. The next three got
home. One cut plumb through the bridge (where all my brains had been
playing about two minutes previously) and burst on the deck just outside
the conning tower. Some cordite cartridges were lying outside of it and
these went off with a great flare. Another struck the funnel and the
third came in on the waterline. Fifteen more shells were then fired with
just a little bit too much elevation and passed over. Only two men were
wounded,--fractured legs. Captain Fitzmaurice now decided that honour
and dignity were satisfied and so fell back slowly towards <location peninsula="Cape_Helles">Cape Helles</location>
to try the effect of his guns on the barbed wire entanglements. A good
deal of ammunition was expended but only one hit on the entanglement was
registered, and that did not seem to do any harm. The fire was described
to me as inaccurate. The fact is, as was agreed between the two services
at <location island="Malta">Malta</location>, the whole principle of naval gunnery is different from the
principles of garrison or field artillery shooting. Before they will be
much good at landmarks, the sailors will have to take lessons in the
art.</p>

<p>Passed a very interesting evening, every one excited, I with my
aeroplane reports; the Staff with the powder they had smelt.</p>

<p>Two of the Australian Commanding Officers dined and I showed them the
aerial photographs of the enemy trenches, etc. The face of one of them
grew very long; so long, in fact, that I feared he was afraid; for I own
these photos are frightening. So I said, "You don't seem to like the
look of that barbed wire, Colonel?" To which he replied, "I was worrying
how and where I would feed and water the prisoners."</p></entry>
  
<entry><p>_16th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian."</location> <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ Spent the forenoon in
interviews beginning at 10 a.m. with <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> and Mr. Fitzmaurice, late
dragoman at the Embassy at <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>. Mr. Fitzmaurice says the
Turks will put up a great fight at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>. They had believed in
the British Navy, and, a month ago, they were shaking in their shoes.
But they had not believed in the British Army or that a body so
infinitely small would be so saucy as to attack them on their own chosen
ground. Even now, he says, they can hardly credit their spies, or their
eyes, and it ought to be easy enough to make them think all this is a
blind, and that we are really going to <location city="Smyrna">Smyrna</location> or Adramiti. They are fond
of saying, "If the English are fools enough to enter our mouth we only
have to close it." Enver especially brags he will make very short work
with us if we set foot so near to the heart of his Empire, and gives it
out that the whole of us will be marching through the streets of
<location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>, not as conquerors, but as prisoners, within a week from
the date of our making the attempt. All the same, despite this bragging,
the Turks realise that if we were to get the Fleet through the Narrows;
or, if it were to force its own way through whilst we absorb the
attention of their mobile guns, the game would be up. So they are
straining every nerve to be ready for anything. The moral of all these
rather contradictory remarks is just what I have said time and again
since South Africa. The fact that war has become a highly scientific
business should not blind us to the other fact that its roots still draw
their nutriment from primitive feelings and methods; the feelings and
methods of boy scouts and Red Indians. It is a huge handicap to us here
that our great men keep all their tricks for their political friends and
have none to spare for their natural enemies. There has been very little
attempt to disguise our aims in <location country="England">England</location>, and <person name="John_Maxwell">Maxwell</person> and <person name="Henry_McMahon">McMahon</person> in
<location country="Egypt">Egypt</location> have allowed their Press to report every arrival of French and
British troops, and to announce openly that we are about to attack at
Gallipoli. I have protested and reported the matter to <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person> but nothing in
the strategic sphere can be done now although, in the tactical sphere,
we have several deceptions ready for them.</p>

<p>Colonel Napier, Military Attache at Sofia, and <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> came in after
these pseudo-secrets had been discussed and joined in the conversation.<person name="Ian_Hamilton">
I </person>doubt whether either Fitzmaurice or Napier have solid information as
to what is in front of us, and their yarns about Balkan politics are
neither here nor there. John Bull is quite out of his depth in the
defiles of the Balkans. With just so much pull over the bulk of my
compatriots as has been given me by my having spent a little time with
their Armies, I may say that the Balkan nations loathe and mistrust one
another to so great a degree that it is sheer waste of time to think of
roping them all in on our side, as Fitzmaurice and Napier seem to
propose. We may get Greece to join us, and Russia may get <location country="Romania">Roumania</location> to
join her--_if we win here_--but then we make an enemy of <location country="Bulgaria">Bulgaria</location>, and
_vice versa_. If they will unearth my 1909 report at the War Office they
will see that, at that time, one Bulgarian Battalion of Infantry was
worth two Battalions of Roumanian Infantry--which may be a help to them
in making their choice. The Balkan problem is so intricate that it must
be simply handled. The simple thing is to pay your money and pick the
best card, knowing you can't have a full hand. So let us have no more
beating about the bush and may we be inspired to make use of the big
boom this Expedition has given to Great Britain in the Balkans to pick
out a partner straightway.</p>

<p><person name="William_Birdwood">Birdie</person> came later and we took stock together of ways and means. We see
eye to eye now on every point. Just before lunch we heard the transport
_Manitou_ had been attacked by a Turkish torpedo boat from <location city="Smyrna">Smyrna</location>. The
first wireless came in saying the enemy had made a bad shot and only a
few men had been drowned lowering the boats. <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Admiral Rosy Wemyss</person> and
Hope, the Flag-Captain, of the <location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">Q.E.</location> were my guests and naturally they
were greatly perturbed. Late in the evening we heard that the Turkish
T.B. had been chased by our destroyers and had run ashore on a Greek
Island where she was destroyed (international laws notwithstanding) by
our landing parties.</p>

<p>At 7.30 p.m. <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> came along and I had the best part of an hour
with him.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_17th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian."</location> <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ Hunter-Weston came over
early to finish off business left undone last night. Admiral Wemyss also
took part in our discussions over the landing. Picture puzzles are
child's play compared with this game of working an unheard of number of
craft to and fro, in and out, of little bits of beaches. At mid-day the
_Manitou_ steamed into harbour and Colonel Peel, Commander of the
troops, came on board and reported fully to me about the attack by the
Turkish torpedo boat. The Turks seem to have behaved quite decently
giving our men time to get into their boats and steaming some distance
off whilst they did so. During the interval the Turks must have got wind
of British warships, for they rushed back in a great hurry and fired
torpedoes at so short a range that they passed under the ship. Very
exciting, we were told, watching them dart beneath the keel through the
crystal clear water. I can well believe it.</p>

<p>Went ashore in the afternoon to watch the Australian Artillery embark.
Spoke to a lot of the men, some of whom had met me during my tour
through Australia last year.</p>

<p><person name="Archibald_Paris">General Paris</person> came to see me this evening.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_18th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian.</location>" <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ Working all morning in
office. In the afternoon inspected embarkation of some howitzers.
D'Amade turned up later from the _Southland_. We went over the landing
at<location town=" Kum Kale"> Kum Kale</location>. He is in full sympathy and understands. Winter, <person name="Gen.Woodward">Woodward</person>
and their administrative Staffs also arrived in the _Southland_ and have
taken up their quarters on this ship. They report everything fixed up at
<location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> before they sailed. We are all together now and their coming
will be a great relief to the General Staff.</p>

<p>Quite hot to-day. Sea dead smooth. The usual ebb and flow of visitors.
Saw the three Corps Commanders and many Staff Officers. We are rather on
wires now that the time is drawing near; <person name="Gen.Woodward">Woodward</person>, though he has only
been here one night, is on barbed wires. His cabin is next the
signallers and he could not get to sleep. He wants some medical
detachments sent up post haste from <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location>. I have agreed to cable
for them and now he is more calm. A big pow-wow on <location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">the "Q.E."</location> (<person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person>,
<person name="William_Birdwood">Birdie</person>, <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person>, <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person>, <person name="William_Bridges">Bridges</person>, <person name="Emile_Guepratte">Guepratte</person>, Thursby, <person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Wemyss</person>,
Phillimore, <person name="Arthur_Vyvian">Vyvian</person>, Dent, Loring), whereat the 23rd was fixed for our
attack and the naval landing orders were read and fully threshed out.<person name="Ian_Hamilton"> I
</person>did not attend as the meeting was rather for the purpose of going point
by point into orders already approved in principle than of starting any
fresh hares. Staff Officers who have only had to do with land operations
would be surprised, I am sure, at the amount of original thinking and
improvisation demanded by a landing operation. The Naval and Military
Beach Personnel is in itself a very big and intricate business which
has no place in ordinary soldier tactics. The diagrams of the ships and
transports; the lists of tows; the action of the Destroyers; tugs;
lighters; signal arrangements for combined operations: these are
unfamiliar subjects and need very careful fitting in. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> came
back and reported all serene; everyone keen and cooperating very
loyally. <person name="Albert_d'Amade">D'Amade</person> has now received the formal letter I wrote him
yesterday after my interview and sees his way clear about<location town=" Kum Kale"> Kum Kale</location>.</p>

<p>Went ashore in the afternoon and saw big landing by Australians, who
took mules and donkeys with them and got them in and out of lighters.
These Australians are shaping into Marines in double quick time and
Cairo high jinks are wild oats sown and buried. Where everyone wants to
do well and to do it in the same way, discipline goes down as slick as
Mother's milk. Action is a discipline in itself.</p>

<p>The three Officers forming the French Mission to my Headquarters made
salaams, viz., Captain Bertier de Sauvigny, Lieutenant Pelliot and
Lieutenant de la Borde. The first is a man of the world, with manners
suave and distinguished; the second is a savant and knows the habits of
obscure and out of the way people. What de la Borde's points may be, I
English.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_20th April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian."</location> <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ A big wind rose in the
night.</p>

<p>A clerk from my central office at the Horse Guards developed small pox
this morning. No doubt he has been in some rotten hole in <location city="Alexandria">Alexandria</location> and
this is the result,--a disgusting one to all of us as we have had to be
vaccinated.</p>

<p>Ready now, but so long as the wind blows, we have to twiddle our thumbs.</p>

<p>Got the full text of <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amades'</person> orders for his<location town=" Kum Kale"> Kum Kale</location> landing as well
as for the <location coast="Besica_Bay">Besika Bay</location> make-believe.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_21st April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian."</location> <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ Blowing big guns. The event
with which old mother time is in labour is so big that her pains are
prodigious and prolonged out of all nature. So near are we now to our
opening that the storm means a twenty four hours' delay.</p>

<p>Have issued my orders to the troops. Yesterday our plans were but plans.
To-day the irrevocable steps out on to the stage.</p>

<p>                                                General Headquarters,
                                                   _21st April, 1915._</p>

<p>    _Soldiers of France and of the King._</p>

<p>Before us lies an adventure unprecedented in modern war. Together with
our comrades of the Fleet, we are about to force a landing upon an open
beach in face of positions which have been vaunted by our enemies as
impregnable.</p>

<p>The landing will be made good, by the help of God and the Navy; the
positions will be stormed, and the War brought one step nearer to a
glorious close.</p>

<p>"Remember," said <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">Lord Kitchener</person> when bidding adieu to your Commander,
"Remember, once you set foot upon <location peninsula="Gallipoli_Peninsula">the Gallipoli Peninsula</location>, you must
fight the thing through to a finish."</p>

<p>The whole world will be watching your progress. Let us prove our selves
worthy of the great feat of arms entrusted to us.
                                              IAN HAMILTON, _General_.</p></entry>

<entry><p>_22nd April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian</location>." <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ Wind worse than ever, but
weather brighter. Another twenty four hours' delay. Russian Military
Attache from Athens (Makalinsky) came to see me at 2.30 p.m. He cannot
give me much idea of how the minds of the Athenians are working. He says
our Russian troops are of the very best. Delay is the worst
nerve-cracker.</p>

<p>Charley Burn, King's Messenger, came; with him a Captain Coddan, to be
liaison between me and Istomine's Russians.</p>

<p>The King sends his blessing.</p>

<p>                       SPECIAL ORDER,</p>

<p>                                  General Headquarters,
                                         _22nd April, 1915._</p>

<p>The following gracious message has been received to-day by the General
Commanding:--</p>

<p>"The King wishes you and your Army every success, and you are
constantly in His Majesty's thoughts and prayers."</p></entry>

<entry><p>_23rd April, 1915. <location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. "Arcadian."</location> <location island="Lemnos">Lemnos</location>._ A gorgeous day at last;
fitting frame to the most brilliant and yet touching of pageants.</p>

<p>All afternoon transports were very, very slowly coming out of harbour
winding their way in and out through the other painted ships lying thick
on the wonderful blue of the bay. The troops wild with enthusiasm and
tremendously cheering especially as they passed the warships of our
Allies.</p>

<p>_Nunc Dimittis_, O Lord of Hosts! Not a man but knows he is making for
the jaws of death. They know, these men do, they are being asked to
prove their enemies to have lied when they swore a landing on
Gallipoli's shore could never make good. They know that lie must pass
for truth until they have become targets to guns, machine guns and
rifles--huddled together in boats, helpless, plain to the enemy's sight.
And they are wild with joy; uplifted! Life spins superbly through their
veins at the very moment they seek to sacrifice it for a cause. O death,
where is thy sting? O grave, where is thy victory?</p>

<p>A shadow has been cast over the wonders of the day by a wireless to say
that Rupert Brooke is very dangerously ill--from the wording we fear
there can be no hope.</p>

<p>Dent, principal Naval Transport Officer, left to-day to get ready.
<person name="Rosslyn_Wemyss">Wemyss</person> said good-bye on going to take up command of his Squadron.</p>

<p>Have got <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade's</person> revised orders for the landing at<location town=" Kum Kale"> Kum Kale</location> and also
for the feint at <location coast="Besica_Bay">Besika Bay</location>. Very clear and good.</p>

<p>At 7.15 p.m. we got this message from <person name="Herbert_Kitchener">K.</person>:--</p>

<p>"Please communicate the following messages at a propitious moment to
each of those concerned.</p>

<p>"(1) My best wishes to you and all your force in carrying to a
successful conclusion the operations you have before you, which will
undoubtedly have a momentous effect on the war. The task they have to
perform will need all the grit Britishers have never failed to show, and<person name="Ian_Hamilton">
I </person>am confident your troops will victoriously clear the way for the Fleet
to advance on <location city="Constantinople">Constantinople</location>.</p>

<p>"(2) Convey to <person name="John_de_Robeck">the Admiral</person> my best wishes that all success may attend
the Fleet. The Army knows they can rely on their energy and effective
co-operation while dealing with the land forces of the enemy.</p>

<p>"(3) Assure <person name="Albert_d'Amade">General d'Amade</person> and the French troops of our entire
confidence that their courage and skill will result in the triumph of
their arms.</p>

<p>"(End of message)--" Personal:</p>

<p>"All my thoughts will be with you when operations begin."</p>

<p>We, here, think of<person name="Herbert_Kitchener"> Lord K.</person> too. May his shadow fall dark upon the
Germans and strike the fear of death into their hearts.</p>

<p>Just got following from the Admiral:--</p>

                                          <p> "<location ship="H.M.S._Queen_Elizabeth">H.M.S. _Queen Elizabeth_</location>,
                                            "_23rd April, 1915._
</p>
<p>  "My dear General,</p>

<p>"I have sent orders to all Admirals that operations are to proceed and
they are to take the necessary measures to have their commands in their
assigned positions by Sunday morning, April 25th!</p>

<p>"I pray that the weather may be favourable and nothing will prevent our
proceeding with the scheme. 'May heaven's light be our guide' and God
give us the victory.</p>

<p>"Think everything is ready and in some ways the delay has been useful,
as we have now a few more lighters and tugs available.</p>

                       <p> "Yours sincerely,</p>
                          <p>(_Sd._) " <person name="John_de_Robeck">J. M. de Robeck</person>."</p>

<p>I have sent a reply:--</p>

<p>                                      "<location ship="S.S._Arcadian">S.S. _Arcadian_</location>,
                                    _23rd April, 1915._</p>

<p>  "My dear Admiral,</p>

<p>"Your note just received gives expression to my own sentiments. The
sooner we get to work now the better and may the best cause win.</p>

<p>                        "Yours sincerely,
                              (_Sd._) "<person name="Ian_Hamilton">Ian Hamilton.</person>"</p>

<p><person name="Rupert_Brooke">Rupert Brooke</person> is dead. Straightaway he will be buried. The rest is
silence.</p>

<p>Twice was "the sight" vouchsafed me:--in <location city="London">London</location> when I told Eddie I
would bespeak the boy's services; at <location city="Port_Said">Port Said</location> when I bespoke them.</p>

<p>Death on the eve of battle, death on a wedding day--nothing so tragic
save that most black mishap, death in action after peace has been
signed. Death grins at my elbow. I cannot get him out of my thoughts. He
is fed up with the old and sick--only the flower of the flock will serve
him now, for God has started a celestial spring cleaning, and our star
is to be scrubbed bright with the blood of our bravest and our best.</p>

<p>Youth and poetry are the links binding the children of the world to come
to the grandsires of the world that was. War will smash, pulverise,
sweep into the dustbins of eternity the whole fabric of the old world:
therefore, the firstborn in intellect must die. Is _that_ the reading of
the riddle?</p>

<p>Almighty God, Watchman of the Milky Way, Shepherd of the Golden Stars,
have mercy upon us, smallest of the heavenly Shiners. Our star burns dim
as a corpse light: the huge black chasm of space closes in: if only by
blood ...? Thy Will be done. _En avant_--at all costs--_en avant_!</p></entry>

</root>
