Gallipoli Chapter 9-12

<chapter>CHAPTER IX</chapter>

<p>SUBMARINES</p>

<p>
_22nd May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ News in to say that yesterday,
whilst Herbert was here to take orders about an armistice, some sort of
an informal parley actually took place. Both sides suddenly got panic
stricken, thinking the others were treacherous, and fire was opened,
some stretcher bearers being killed. Nothing else was to be expected
when things are done in this casual and unauthorized way. I felt very
much annoyed, but Aubrey Herbert was still on board and I saw him before
breakfast and told him Walker seemed to have taken too much upon himself
parleying with the Turks and that Birdwood must now make this clear to
everyone for future guidance. Although Aubrey Herbert is excessively
unorthodox he quite sees that confabs with enemies must be carried out
according to Cocker.</p>

<p>After breakfast landed at Cape Helles. Inspected the detachment of the
Works Department of the Egyptian Army as it was on its way to the French
Headquarters. Colonel Micklem was in charge. At Sedd-el-Bahr lunched
with Gouraud and his Staff. General Bailloud rode up just as I was about
to enter the porch of the old Fort. He was in two minds whether or not
to embrace me, being in very high feather, his men having this morning
carried the Haricot redoubt overlooking the Kereves Dere. At lunch he
was the greatest possible fun, bubbling over with jokes and witty
sallies. Just as we were finishing, news came through the telephone that
Bailloud's Brigade had been driven in by a big Turkish counter-attack,
with a loss of 400 men and some first class officers. Most of us showed
signs, I will not say of being rattled, but of having stumbled against a
rattlesnake. Gouraud remained unaffectedly in possession of himself as
host of a lunch party. He said, "We will not take the trenches by not
taking the coffee. Let us drink it first, and then we will consider." So
we drank our coffee; lit our smokes, and afterwards Gouraud, through
Girodon, issued his orders in the most calm and matter-of-fact way. He
declares the redoubt will be in our hands again to-morrow.</p>

<p>Our lunch was to furnish us with yet another landmark for bad luck. As
we were leaving, a message came in to say that an enemy submarine had
been sighted off Gaba Tepe. The fresh imprint of a tiger's paw upon the
pathway gives the same sort of feel to the Indian herdsman. Tall stories
from neighbouring villages have been going the round for weeks, only
half-believed, but here is the very mark of the beast; the horror has
suddenly taken shape. He mutters the name of God, wondering what eyes
may even now be watching his every movement; he wonders whose turn will
come first--and when--and where. This was the sort of effect of the
wireless and in a twinkling every transport round the coast was steering
full steam to Imbros. In less than no time we saw a regatta of
skedaddling ships. So dies the invasion of England bogey which, from
first to last, has wrought us an infinity of harm. Born and bred of
mistrust of our own magnificent Navy, it has led soldiers into heresy
after fallacy and fallacy after heresy until now it is the cause of my
Divisions here being hardly larger than Brigades, whilst the men who
might have filled them are "busy" guarding London! If one rumoured
submarine can put the fear of the Lord into British transports how are
German or any other transports going to face up to a hundred British
submarines? The theory of the War Office has struggled with the theory
of the Admiralty for the past five years: now there is nothing left of
the War Office theory; no more than is left of a soap bubble when you
strike it with a battleaxe. Some other stimulus to our Territorial
recruiting than the fear of invasion will have to be invented in future.</p>

<p>After lunch went to the Headquarters of the 29th Division where all the
British Divisional Generals had assembled together to meet me. The same
story everywhere--lack of men, meaning extra work--which again means
sickness and still greater lack of men. On my return found a letter from
the Turkish Commander-in-Chief giving his "full consent" to the
armistice he himself had asked me for! A save-face document, no doubt:
the wounded are all Turks as our men did not leave their trenches on
the 19th; the dead, also, I am glad to say, almost entirely Turks; but
anyway, one need not be too punctilious where it is a matter of giving
decent burial to so many men.</p>

<p>                                GRAND QUARTIER GENERAL DE LA 5me ARMEE
                                                         OTTOMANE.
                                                      _le 22 mai 1915._</p>

<p>    "EXCELLENCE!</p>

<p>     "J'ai l'honneur d'informer Votre Excellence que les propositions
     concernant la conclusion d'un armistice pour enterrer les morts et
     secourir les blesses des deux parties adverses, ont trouve mon
     plein consentement--et que seule nos sentiments d'humanite nous y
     ont determines.</p>

<p>     "J'ai investi le lieutenant-colonel Fahreddin du pouvoir de signer
     en mon nom.</p>

<p>     "J'ai l'honneur d'etre avec l'assurance de ma plus haute
     consideration.</p>

<p>                                           (_Sd._) "LIMAN VON SANDERS,</p>

<p>                                       "Commandant en chef de la 5me
                                                      Armee Ottomane.</p>

<p>  "Commandant en chef des Forces Britanniques,
      Sir John Hamilton, Excellence."</p>

<p>_23rd May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ Blazing hot. Wrote all day. Had an
hour and a half's talk with de Robeck--high politics as well as our own
rather anxious affairs. No one knows how the new First Lord will play
up, but Asquith, for sure, chucks away his mainspring if he parts with
Winston: as to Fisher, he too has energy but none of it came our way so
he will have no tears from us, though he has friends here too. The
submarine scare is full on; the beastly things have frightened us more
than all the Turks and all their German guns.</p>

<p>_24th May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ Vice-Admiral Nicol, French Naval
Commander-in-Chief, came aboard to pay me a visit.</p>

<p>Armistice from 9.30 a.m. to 4.30 p.m. for burial of Turkish dead. All
went off quite smoothly.... This moment, 12.40 p.m. the Captain has
rushed in to say that H.M.S. _Triumph_ is sinking! He caught the bad
news on his wireless as it flew. Beyond doubt the German submarine. What
exactly is about to happen, God knows. The fleet cannot see itself wiped
out by degrees; and yet, without the fleet, how are we soldiers to
exist? One more awful conundrum set to us, but the Navy will solve it,
for sure.</p>

<p>_25th May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ Bad news confirmed. The Admiral
came aboard and between us we tried to size up the new situation and to
readjust ourselves thereto. Our nicely worked out system for supplying
the troops has in a moment been tangled up into a hundred knotty
problems. Instead of our small craft working to and fro in half mile
runs, henceforth they will have to cover 60 miles per trip. Until now
the big ocean going ships have anchored close up to Helles or Anzac; in
future Mudros will be the only possible harbour for these priceless
floating depots. Imbros, here, lies quite open to submarine attacks, and
in a northerly gale, becomes a mere roadstead. The Admiral, who regards
soldiers as wayward water babes, has insisted on lashing a merchantman
to each side of the _Arcadian_ to serve as torpedo buffers. There are,
it seems, at least two German submarines prowling about at the present
moment between Gaba Tepe and Cape Helles. After torpedoing the _Triumph_
the same submarine fired at and missed the _Vengeance_. The _Lord
Nelson_ with the Admiral, as well as three French battleships,
zig-zagged out of harbour and made tracks for Mudros in the afternoon.
We are left all alone in our glory with our two captive merchantmen. The
attitude is heroic but not, I think, so dangerous as it is
uncomfortable. The big ocean liners lashed to port and starboard cut us
off from air as well as light and one of them is loaded with Cheddar.
When Mr. Jorrocks awoke James Pigg and asked him to open the window and
see what sort of a hunting morning it was, it will be remembered that
the huntsman opened the cupboard by mistake and made the reply, "Hellish
dark and smells of cheese." Well, that immortal remark hits us off to a
T. Never mind. Light will be vouchsafed. Amen.</p>

<p>The burial of 3,000 Turks by armistice at Anzac seems to have been
carried out without a hitch. All these 3,000 Turks were killed between
the 18th and 20th instant. By the usual averages this figure implies
over 12,000 wounded so the Lord has vouchsafed us a signal victory
indeed. Birdwood's men were all out and his reserves, or rather the lack
of them, would not permit him to counter-attack the moment the enemy's
assault was repulsed. When we read of battles in histories we feel, we
see, so clearly the value of counter-attack and the folly of passive
defence; but, in the field, the struggle has sometimes been so close
that the victorious defence are left gasping. The enemy were very polite
during the armistice, and by way of being highly solemn and correct, but
they could not refrain from bursting into laughter when the Australians
held up cigarettes and called out "baksheesh."</p>

<p>Last night the French and the Naval Brigade made a good advance with
slight loss. The East Lancs also pushed on a little bit.</p>

<p>_26th May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ Entertained a small party of
Australian officers as my private guests for 48 hours, my idea being to
give them a bit of a rest. Colonel Monash, commanding 4th Australian
Infantry Brigade, was the senior. He is a very competent officer. I have
a clear memory of him standing under a gum tree at Lilydale, near
Melbourne, holding a conference after a manoeuvre, when it had been
even hotter than it is here now. I was prepared for intelligent
criticisms but I thought they would be so wrapped up in the cotton wool
of politeness that no one would be very much impressed. On the contrary,
he stated his opinions in the most direct, blunt, telling way. The fact
was noted in my report and now his conduct out here has been fully up to
sample.</p>

<p>A horrid mishap. Landing some New Zealand Mounted Rifles at Anzac, the
destroyer anchored within range of the Turkish guns instead of slowly
steaming about out of range until the picket boats came off to bring the
men ashore. The Turks were watching and, as soon as she let go her
anchor, opened fire from their guns by the olive, and before the
destroyer could get under weigh six of these fine New Zealand lads were
killed and forty-five wounded. A hundred fair fighting casualties would
affect me less. To be knocked out before having taken part in a battle,
or even having set foot upon the Promised Land--nothing could be more
cruel.</p>

<p>A special order to the troops:--</p>

<p>                                                 GENERAL HEADQUARTERS,
                                                      _25th May, 1915._</p>

<p>1. Now that a clear month has passed since the Mediterranean
Expeditionary Force began its night and day fighting with the enemy, the
General Commanding desires me to explain to officers, non-commissioned
officers and men the real significance of the calls made upon them to
risk their lives apparently for nothing better than to gain a few yards
of uncultivated land.</p>

<p>2. A comparatively small body of the finest troops in the world, French
and British, have effected a lodgment close to the heart of a great
continental empire, still formidable even in its decadence. Here they
stand firm, or slowly advance, and in the efforts made by successive
Turkish armies to dislodge them the rotten Government at Constantinople
is gradually wearing itself out. The facts and figures upon which this
conclusion is based have been checked and verified from a variety of
sources. Agents of neutral powers possessing good sources of information
have placed both the numbers and the losses of the enemy much higher
than they are set forth here, but the General Commanding prefers to be
on the safe side and to give his troops a strictly conservative
estimate.</p>

<p>Before operations began the strength of the defenders of the Dardanelles
was:--</p>

<p>  Gallipoli Peninsula          34,000 and about 100 guns.
  Asiatic side of Straits      41,000</p>

<p>All the troops on the Gallipoli Peninsula and fifty per cent. of the
troops on the Asiatic side were Nizam, that is to say, regular first
line troops. They were transferable, and were actually transferred to
this side upon which the invaders disembarked. Our Expeditionary Force
effected its landing it will be seen, in the face of an enemy superior,
not only to the covering parties which got ashore the first day, but
superior actually to the total strength at our disposal. By the 12th
May, the Turkish Army of occupation had been defeated in several
engagements, and would have been at the end of their resources had they
not meanwhile received reinforcements of 20,000 infantry and 21
batteries of Field Artillery.</p>

<p>Still the Expeditionary Force held its own, and more than its own,
inflicting fresh bloody defeats upon the newcomers and again the Turks
must certainly have given way had not a second reinforcement reached the
Peninsula from Constantinople and Smyrna amounting at the lowest
estimate to 24,000 men.</p>

<p>3. From what has been said it will be understood that the Mediterranean
Expeditionary Force, supported by its gallant comrades the Fleet, but
with constantly diminishing effectives, has held in check or wrested
ground from some 120,000 Turkish troops elaborately entrenched and
supported by a powerful artillery.</p>

<p>The enemy has now few more Nizam troops at his disposal and not many
Redif or second class troops. Up to date his casualties are 55,000, and
again, in giving this figure, the General Commanding has preferred to
err on the side of low estimates.</p>

<p>Daily we make progress, and whenever the reinforcements close at hand
begin to put in an appearance, the Mediterranean Expeditionary Force
will press forward with a fresh impulse to accomplish the greatest
Imperial task ever entrusted to an army.</p>

<p>_27th May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ The _Majestic_ has been torpedoed
and has sunk off Cape Helles. Got the news at mid-day. Fuller, my
Artillery Commander, and Ashmead-Bartlett, the correspondent, were both
on board, and both were saved--minus kit! About 40 men have gone under.
Bad luck. A Naval Officer who has seen her says she is lying in shallow
water--6 fathoms--bottom upwards looking like a stranded whale. He says
the German submarine made a most lovely shot at her through a crowd of
cargo ships and transports. Like picking a royal stag out of his harem
of does. To my Staff, they tell me, he delivered himself further but, as
I said to the Officer who repeated these criticisms to me, "judge not
that ye be not judged."</p>

<p>_28th May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ Went for a walk with the Admiral.
He refuses any longer to accept the responsibility of keeping us afloat.
As Helles, Anzac and Tenedos have each been ruled out, we are going to
doss down on this sandbank opposite us. One thing, it will be central to
both my theatres of work.</p>

<p>_29th May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ The Commodore, Roger Keyes, arrived
mid-day and invited me to come over to Helles with him on a destroyer,
H.M.S. _Scorpion._ He was crossing in hopes--_in hopes,_ if you
please--of hitting off the submarine. The idea that it might hit him had
not seemed to occur to him. On the way we were greatly excited to see
the bladder of an indicator net smoking. So we rushed about the place
and bombs were got ready to drop. But the net remained motionless and,
as the water was too deep for the submarine to be lying at the bottom,
it seemed (although no one dared to say so) that a porpoise had been
poking fun at the Commodore.</p>

<p>Landing at Helles inspected the various roads, which were in the making.
Next saw Hunter-Weston. Canvassed plans with him and felt myself
refreshed. Then went on to Gouraud's Headquarters, taking the Commodore
with me. My Commanders are an asset which cancels many a debit. Gouraud
is in excellent form and gave us tea. Walked down to "V" Beach at 6 p.m.</p>

<p>When we got on to the pier, which ends in the _River Clyde_, we found
another destroyer, the _Wolverine_, under Lieutenant-Commander Keyes,
the brother of the Commodore. She was to take us across, and (of all
places in the world to select for a berth!) she had run herself
alongside the _River Clyde_ which was, at that moment, busy playing
target to the heavy guns of Asia. I imagined that taking aboard a boss
like the Commander-in-Chief, as well as that much bigger boss (in naval
estimates) his own big brother, the Commodore, our Lieutenant-Commander
would nip away presto. Not a bit of it! No sooner had he got us aboard
than he came out boldly and very, very slowly, stern first, from the lee
of the _River Clyde_ and began a duel against Asia with 4-inch lyddite
from the _Wolverine's_ after gun. The fight seems quite funny to me now
but, at the time, serio-comic would have better described my
impressions. Shells ashore are part of the common lot; they come in the
day's work: on the water; in a cockleshell--well, you can't go to
ground, anyway!</p>

<p>[Illustration: VIEW OF "V" BEACH, TAKEN FROM S.S. "RIVER CLYDE"
_"Central News" photo._]</p>

<p>Heavy fighting at Anzac. The Turks fired a mine under Quinn's Post and
then rushed a section of the defence isolated by the explosion. At 6 in
the morning the crater was, Birdie says, most gallantly retaken with the
bayonet. There are excursions and alarms; attacks and counter-attacks;
bomb-showers to which the bayonet charge is our only retort--but we hold
fast the crater!</p>

<p>When I tell them at home that if they will give me munitions enough to
let me advance two miles I will give them Constantinople, that is the
truth. On paper, the Turks no doubt might assert with equal force that
if they got forces enough together to drive the Australians back a short
two hundred yards they could give the Sultan the resounding prestige of
a Peninsula freed from the Giaour. But that would require more Turks
than the Turks could feed, whereas we know we could do it now, as we
are--given the wherewithal--trench mortars, hand grenades and bombs, for
example.</p>

<p>A message from Hanbury Williams, who is with the Grand Duke Nicholas, to
say that all idea of sending me a Russian Army Corps to land at the
Bosphorus has been abandoned!!!</p>

<p>_30th May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ Went to Anzac in a destroyer. The
Cove was being heavily shelled, and the troops near the beach together
with the fatigue parties handling stores and ammunition, had dashed
into their dugouts like marmots at the shadow of an eagle. Birdwood came
out to meet me on this very unhealthy spot; indeed, in spite of my
waving him back, he walked right on to the end of the deserted pier.
Just as we were getting near his quarters, a couple of shrapnel burst at
an angle and height which, by the laws of gravity, momentum and velocity
ought to have put a fullstop to this chronicle. Actually, we walked
on--through the "Valley of Death"--past the spot where the brave Bridges
bit the dust, to the Headquarters of the 4th Australian Infantry
Brigade. Thence I could see the enemy trenches in front of Quinn's Post,
and also a very brisk bomb combat in full flame where the New Zealand
Mounted Rifles were making good the Turkish communicating post they had
seized earlier in the day. Nothing more strange than this inspection.
Along the path at the bottom of the valley warning notices were stuck
up. The wayfarer has to be as punctilious about each footstep as
Christian in the "Pilgrim's Progress." Should he disregard the placards
directing him to keep to the right or to the left of the track, he is
almost certainly shot. Half of the pathway may be as safe as Piccadilly,
whilst he who treads the other had far better be up yonder at hand grips
with the Turks. Presumably some feature of the ground defilades one
part, for the enemy cannot see into the valley, although, were they only
20 yards nearer the edge of the cliff, they would command its whole
extent. The spirit of the men is invincible. Only lately have we been
able to give them blankets: as to square meals and soft sleeps, these
are dreams of the past, they belonged to another state of being. Yet I
never struck a more jovial crew. Men staggering under huge sides of
frozen beef; men struggling up cliffs with kerosine tins full of water;
men digging; men cooking; men card-playing in small dens scooped out
from the banks of yellow clay--everyone wore a Bank Holiday
air;--evidently the ranklings and worry of mankind--miseries and
concerns of the spirit--had fled the precincts of this valley. The
Boss--the bill--the girl--envy, malice, hunger, hatred--had scooted far
away to the Antipodes. All the time, overhead, the shell and rifle
bullets groaned and whined, touching just the same note of violent
energy as was in evidence everywhere else. To understand that awful din,
raise the eyes 25 degrees to the top of the cliff which closes in the
tail end of the valley and you can see the Turkish hand grenades
bursting along the crest, just where an occasional bayonet flashes and
figures hardly distinguishable from Mother earth crouch in an irregular
line. Or else they rise to fire and are silhouetted a moment against the
sky and then you recognize the naked athletes from the Antipodes and
your heart goes into your mouth as a whole bunch of them dart forward
suddenly, and as suddenly disappear. And the bomb shower stops dead--for
the moment; but, all the time, from that fiery crest line which is
Quinn's, there comes a slow constant trickle of wounded--some dragging
themselves painfully along; others being carried along on stretchers.
Bomb wounds all; a ceaseless, silent stream of bandages and blood. Yet
three out of four of "the boys" have grit left for a gay smile or a
cheery little nod to their comrades waiting for their turn as they pass,
pass, pass, down on their way to the sea.</p>

<p>There are poets and writers who see naught in war but carrion, filth,
savagery and horror. The heroism of the rank and file makes no appeal.
They refuse war the credit of being the only exercise in devotion on the
large scale existing in this world. The superb moral victory over death
leaves them cold. Each one to his taste. To me this is no valley of
death--it is a valley brim full of life at its highest power. Men live
through more in five minutes on that crest than they do in five years of
Bendigo or Ballarat. Ask the brothers of these very fighters--Calgoorlie
or Coolgardie miners--to do one quarter the work and to run one
hundredth the risk on a wages basis--instanter there would be a riot.
But here,--not a murmur, not a question; only a radiant force of
camaraderie in action.</p>

<p>The Turks have heaps of cartridges and more shells, anyway, than we
have. They have as many grenades as they can throw; we have--a dozen per
Company. There is a very bitter feeling amongst all the troops, but
especially the Australians, at this lack of elementary weapons like
grenades. Our overseas men are very intelligent. They are prepared to
make allowances for lack of shell; lack of guns; lack of high
explosives. But they know there must be something wrong when the Turks
carry ten good bombs to our one bad one; and they think, some of them,
that this must be my fault. Far from it. _Directly_ after the naval
battle of the 18th March--i.e., over two months ago, I wrote out a cable
asking for bombs. I sent this on my own happy thought, and I had hoped
for a million by the date of landing five weeks later. But I got,
practically, none; nor any promise for the future. In default of help
from home, we have tried to manufacture these primitive but very
effective projectiles for ourselves with jam pots, meat tins and any old
rubbish we can scrape together. De Lothbiniere has shown ingenuity in
thus making bricks without straw. The Fleet, too, has played up and de
Robeck has guaranteed me two thousand to be made by the artificers on
the battleships. Maxwell in Egypt has been improvising a few; Methuen at
Malta says they can't make them there. But what a shame that the sons of
a manufacturing country like Great Britain should be in straits for
engines so simple.</p>

<p>Yesterday and to-day we have fired, for us, a terrible lot of shells
(1,800 shrapnel) but never was shot better spent. We reckon the enemy's
casualties between 1,000 and 2,000 mainly caused by our guns playing on
the columns which came up trying to improve upon their lodgment in
Quinn's Post. Add this to the 3,000 killed, and, say, 12,000 wounded on
the 18th instant, and it is clear no troops in the world can stand it
very long. But we are literally at the end of our shrapnel; and as to
high explosive, according to the standards of the gunners, we have never
had any!</p>

<p>Left on a picket boat with Birdie to board my destroyer to an
accompaniment of various denominations of projectiles. One or two shells
burst hard by just as we were scrambling up her side.</p>

<p>Vice-Admiral Nicholls called after my return. Courtauld Thomson, the Red
Cross man, dined; very helpful; very well stocked with comforts and
everyone likes him, even the R.A.M.C.</p>

<p>_31st May, 1915. H.M.T. "Arcadian."_ Worked in the forenoon. Gouraud,
Girodon and Hunter-Weston lunched and we spent the afternoon at the
scheme for our next fight. Each of us agreed that Fortune had not been
over kind. By one month's hard, close hammering we had at last made the
tough _moral_ of the Turks more pliant, when lo and behold, in broad
daylight, thousands of their common soldiery see with their own eyes two
great battleships sink beneath the waves and all the others make an exit
more dramatic than dignified. Most of the Armada of store ships had
already cleared out and now the last of the battleships has offed it
over the offing; a move which the whole of the German Grand Fleet could
not have forced them to make! What better pick-me-up could Providence
have provided for the badly-shaken Turks? No more inquisitive cruisers
ready to let fly a salvo at anything that stirs. No more searchlights by
night; no more big explosives flying from the Aegean into the
Dardanelles!</p>

<p>_1st June, 1915. Imbros._ Came ashore and stuck up my 80-lb. tent in the
middle of a sandbank whereon some sanguine Greek agriculturalist has
been trying to plant wheat.</p>

<p>We shall live the simple life; the same life, in fact, as the men, but
are glad to be off the ship and able to stretch our legs.</p>

<p>Hard fighting in the North zone and the South. Both outposts captured by
us on the 29th May at Anzac and on the French right at Helles heavily
attacked. In the North we had to give ground, but not before we had made
the enemy pay ten times its value in killed and wounded. Had we only had
a few spare rounds of shrapnel we need never have gone back. The War
Office have called for a return of my 4.5 howitzer ammunition during the
past fortnight, and I find that, since the 14th May, we have expended
477 shell altogether at Anzac and Helles combined. In the South the
enemy twice recaptured the redoubt taken by the French on the 29th, but
Gouraud, having a nice little parcel of high explosive on hand, was able
to drive them out definitely and to keep them out.</p>

<p>_2nd June, 1915. Imbros._ Working all day in camp. Blazing hot, tempered
by a cool breeze towards evening. De Robeck came ashore and we had an
hour together in the afternoon. Everything is fixed up for our big
attack on the 4th. From aeroplane photographs it would appear that the
front line Turkish trenches are meant more as traps for rash forlorn
hopes than as strongholds. In fact, the true tug only begins when we try
to carry the second line and the flanking machine guns. Gouraud has
generously lent us two groups of 75s with H.E. shell, and I am cabling
the fact to the War Office as it means a great deal to us. When I say
they are lent to us, I do not mean that they put the guns at our
disposal. They are only ours for defensive purposes; that is to say,
they remain in their own gun positions in the French lines and are to
help by thickening the barrage in front of the Naval Division.</p>

<p>De Robeck and Keyes are quite as much at sea as Braithwaite and myself
about this original scheme of the British Government for treating a
tearing, raging crisis; i.e., by taking no notice of it. I guess that
never before in the history of war has a Commander asked urgently that
his force might be doubled and then got no orders; no answer of any sort
or kind!</p>

<p>When I sent K. my M.F. 234 of the 17th May asking for two Corps, or for
Allies, one or the other, I got a reply by return expressing his
disappointment; since then, nothing. During that fortnight of silence
the whole of the Turkish Empire has been moving--closing in--on the
Dardanelles. Then, by a side-wind I happen to hear of the abstraction of
a Russian Army Corps from my supposed command; an Army Corps, who by the
mere fact of "being," held off a large force of Turks from Gallipoli.</p>

<p>So I have put down a few hard truths. Unpalatable they may be but some
day they've got to be faced and the sooner the better. Time has slipped
away, but to-day is still better than to-morrow.</p>

<p>What a change since the War Office sent us packing with a bagful of
hallucinations. Naval guns sweeping the Turks off the Peninsula; the
Ottoman Army legging it from a British submarine waving the Union Jack;
Russian help in hand; Greek help on the _tapis_. Now it is our Fleet
which has to leg it from the German submarine; there is no ammunition
for the guns; no drafts to keep my Divisions up to strength; my Russians
have gone to Galicia and the Greeks are lying lower than ever.</p>

<p>"No. M.F. 288. From General Sir Ian Hamilton to Earl Kitchener. With
reference to my telegrams No. M.F. 274 of 29th May, and No. M.F. 234 of
17th May. If the information sent by Hanbury-Williams, to which I
referred in my No. M.F. 274, is correct it is advisable that I should
send you a fresh appreciation of the situation.</p>

<p>"I assumed in my No. M.F. 234 that you had adequate forces at your
disposal, but on the other hand I assumed that some 100,000 Turks would
be kept occupied by the Russians. By the defection of Russia, 100,000
Turks are set free in the Caucasus and European Turkey. After deduction
of casualties there are at least 80,000 Turks now against us in the
Peninsula. There are 20,000 Turks on the Bulgarian frontier which,
assuming that Bulgaria remains neutral, are able to reinforce Gallipoli;
some, in fact, have already arrived showing the restoration of Turkish
confidence in King Ferdinand. Close by on the Asiatic side there remain
10,000 Turks, making a total of 210,000, to which must be added 65,000
who are under training in Europe.</p>

<p>"The movement of the Turkish troops has already begun. There are
practically no troops left in Smyrna district, and there are already in
the field numbers of troops from European garrisons, while recently it
was reported that more are coming.</p>

<p>"The movement of a quarter of a million men against us seems to be well
under way, and although many of these are ill-trained still with
well-run supply and ammunition columns and in trenches designed by
Germans the Turk is always formidable.</p>

<p>"As regards ammunition, the enemy appears to have an unlimited supply of
small-arm ammunition and as many hand-grenades as they can fling. Though
there is some indication that gun ammunition is being husbanded, it was
reported as late as 27th May, that supplies of shells were being
received _via_ Roumania, and yesterday it was suggested that artillery
ammunition can be manufactured at Constantinople where it is reported
that over two hundred engineers have arrived from Krupp's.</p>

<p>"At the same time, the temporary withdrawal of our battleships owing to
enemy submarines has altered the position to our disadvantage; while not
of the highest importance materially this factor carries considerable
moral weight.</p>

<p>"Taking all these factors into consideration, it would seem that for an
early success some equivalent to the suspended Russian co-operation is
vitally necessary. The ground gained and the positions which we hold are
not such as to enable me to envisage with soldierly equanimity the
probability of the large forces adumbrated above being massed against my
troops without let or hindrance from elsewhere. Fresh light may be shed
on the matter by the battle now imminent, but I am cabling on reasoned
existing facts. Time is an object, but if Greece came in, preferably
_via_ Enos, the problem would be simplified. It is broadly my view that
we must obtain the support of a fresh ally in this theatre, or else
there should be got ready British reinforcements to the full extent
mentioned in my No. M.F. 234, though as stated above the disappearance
of Russian co-operation was not contemplated in my estimate."</p>

<p>_3rd June, 1915. Imbros._ Meant to go to Anzac; sea too rough; in the
afternoon saw de Robeck and Roger Keyes. Braithwaite came over and we
went through my cable of yesterday. The sailors would just as soon I had
left out that remark about the enemy being bucked up by the retreat of
our battleships. But the passage implied also that their mere visible
presence was shown to be most valuable. Both of them agree that I am
well within the mark in saying what I did about the loss of my Russian
Army Corps. Roger Keyes next launched a dry land criticism. He rightly
thinks that the weakness of our _present_ units is _the_ real weakness:
he thinks we are far more in need of drafts than of fresh units; he
suggests that a rider be sent now to insist that the estimates in
yesterday's cable were only made on the assumption that my present force
is kept up to strength. I did press that very point in my first cable of
17th May, which is referred to in the opening of this cable; further, we
keep on saying it every week in our War Office cable giving strengths.
After all, K. is 65. He still believes "A man's a man and a rifle's a
rifle"; I still believe that half the value of every human being depends
upon his environment:--we are not going to convert one another now.</p>

<p>As we were actually talking, Williams brought over an answer:--</p>

<p>"No. 5104, cipher. From Earl Kitchener to General Sir Ian Hamilton. With
reference to your No. M.F. 288. Owing to the restricted nature of the
ground you occupy and the experience we have had in Flanders of
increased forces acting in trench positions, I own I have some doubts of
an early decisive result being obtained by at once increasing the forces
at your disposal, but I should like your views as soon as you
can--to-day if possible. Are you convinced that with immediate
reinforcements to the extent you mention you could force the Kilid Bahr
position and thus finish the Dardanelles operations?</p>

<p>"You mentioned in a previous telegram that you intended to keep
reinforcements on islands, is this your intention with regard to the
Lowland Division, now on its way to you, and the other troops when
sent?"</p>

<p>K.'s brief cable is _intensely_ characteristic. I have taken down
hundreds of his wires. We are face to face here with his very self at
_first hand_. How curiously it reveals the man's instinct, or
genius--call it what you will.</p>

<p>K. sees in a flash what the rest of the world does not seem to see so
clearly; viz., that the piling up of increased forces opposite
entrenched positions is a spendthrift, unscientific proceeding. He
wishes to know if I mean to do this. To draw me out he assumes if I get
the troops, I _would_ at once commit them to trench warfare by crowding
them in behind the lines of Helles or Anzac. Actually I intend to keep
the bulk of them on the islands, so as to throw them unexpectedly
against some key position which is _not_ prepared for defence. But I
have to be very careful what I say, seeing that the Turks got wind of
the date of our first landing from London _via_ Vienna. Least said to a
Cabinet, least leakage.</p>

<p>That is not all. Curt as is the cable it has yet scope to show up a
little more of our great K.'s outfit. His infernal hurry. "To-day":--I
am to reply, to-day! He has taken some two and a half weeks to answer my
request for two Army Corps and I am to answer a far more obscure
question in two and a half minutes. Why, since my appeal of 17th May the
situation has not stood still. A Commander in the field is like a cannon
ball. If he stops going ahead, he falls dead. You can't stop moving for
a fortnight and then expect to carry on where you left off; I think the
Duke of Wellington said this; if he didn't he should have. To err is to
be human and the troops, if sent at once, may or may not, fulfil our
hopes. All we here can say is this:--</p>

<p>(1) If the Army Corps had been sent at once (i.e., two weeks ago) the
results should have been decisive.</p>

<p>(2) If the Army Corps are not sent at once, there can be no early
decision.</p>

<p>Braithwaite, De Robeck and Keyes agree to (1) and (2) but the cabled
answer will not be so simple and, in spite of K.'s sudden impatience, I
must sleep over it first.</p>

<p>Written whilst Williams waits:--</p>

<p>"No. M.F. 292. From General Sir Ian Hamilton to Earl Kitchener. Secret.
To-morrow, 4th June, I am fighting a general action. Therefore I feel
sure that you will wish me to defer my answer to your telegram No. 5104,
cipher, until I see the result."</p>

<p>These lofty strategical questions must not make me forget an equally
vital munitions message just to hand. I have cabled K. twice in the past
day or two about shells. On the 1st instant I had said, "I still await
the information promised in your x. 4773, A. 5, of 19th instant. In my
opinion the supply of gun ammunition can hardly be considered adequate
or safe until the following conditions can be filled:--(1) That the
amounts with units and on the Lines of Communication should be made up
to the number of rounds per gun which is allowed in War Establishment
figures of 29th Division. (2) That these full amounts should be
maintained and despatched automatically without any further application
from us, beyond a weekly statement of the expenditure which will be
cabled to you every Saturday. (3) In view of the number and the extent
of the entrenchments to be dealt with it is necessary that a high
proportion of high explosive shell for 18 pounder and howitzers be
included in accordance with the report of my military advisers."</p>

<p>We now have his reply:--</p>

<p>"No. 5088, cipher. From Earl Kitchener to Sir Ian Hamilton. With
reference to your telegrams No. M.F. 281 and No. M.F.G.T. 967. We cannot
supply ammunition to maintain a 1,000 rounds a gun owing to the demands
from France, but consignments are being sent which amount to 17 rounds
per gun per day for the 18 pounder and 4.5.-inch howitzer; this is
considered by General Joffre and Sir John French as necessary. As much
as possible of other natures will be sent. As regards quantities, you
will be informed as early as possible. As available, H.E. shells will be
sent for 18 pounder guns and howitzers."</p>

<p>If we get 17 rounds per gun per day for the 18 pounders and 4.5
howitzers we shall indeed be on velvet. To be given what satisfies
Joffre and French--that sounds too good to be true. So ran my thoughts
and Braithwaite's on a first reading. Then came the C.R.A. who puts
another light on the proposal and points out that the implied comparison
with France is fallacious. We are undergunned here as compared with
France in the proportion of 1 to 3. I mean to say that, in proportion to
"bayonets" we have rather less than one third of the "guns."
_Therefore_, if we were really to have munitions on the scale
"considered necessary by General Joffre and Sir John French," we ought
to have three times 17 rounds per day per gun; i.e. 51 rounds per day
per gun. But never mind. _If we do get_ the 17 rounds we shall be
infinitely better off than we have been: "and so say all of us!" Putting
this cable together with yesterday's we all of us feel that the home
folk are beginning to yawn and rub their eyes and that ere long they may
really be awake.</p>

<p>_4th June, 1915. Imbros._ Left camp after breakfast and boarded the
redoubtable _Wolverine_ under that desperado Lieutenant-Commander Keyes.
The General Staff came alongside and we made our way to Cape Helles
through a blinding dust storm--at least, the dust came right out to sea,
but it was on shore that it became literally blinding.</p>

<p>On the pier I met Gouraud who walked up with me. Gouraud was very grave
but confident. My post of command had been "dug out" for me well forward
on the left flank by Hunter-Weston. In that hole two enormous tarantulas
and I passed a day that seems to me ten years. The torture of suspense;
the extremes of exaltation and of depression; the Red Indian necessity
of showing no sign: all this varied only by the vicious scream of shell
sailing some 30 feet over our heads on their way towards the 60 pounders
near the point. A Commander feels desperately lonely at such moments. On
him, and on him alone, falls the crushing onus of responsibility: to be
a Corps Commander is child's play in _that_ comparison. The Staff are
gnawed with anxiety too--are saying their prayers as fast as they can,
no doubt, as they follow the ebb and flow of the long khaki line through
their glasses. Yes, I have done that myself in the old days from
Charasia onwards. Yet how faintly is my anguish reflected in the mere
anxiety of their minds.</p>

<p>Chapters could be written about this furious battle fought in a
whirlwind of dust and smoke; some day I hope somebody may write them.
After the first short spell of shelling our men fixed bayonets and
lifted them high above the parapet. The Turks thinking we were going to
make the assault, rushed troops into their trenches, until then lightly
held. No sooner were our targets fully manned than we shelled them in
earnest and went on at it until--on the stroke of mid-day--out dashed
our fellows into the open. For the best part of an hour it seemed that
we had won a decisive victory. On the left all the front line Turkish
trenches were taken. On the right the French rushed the _"Haricot"_--so
long a thorn in their flesh; next to them the Anson lads stormed another
big Turkish redoubt in a slap-dash style reminding me of the best work
of the old Regular Army; but the boldest and most brilliant exploit of
the lot was the charge made by the Manchester Brigade[19] in the centre
who wrested two lines of trenches from the Turks; and then, carrying
right on; on to the lower slopes of Achi Baba, had _nothing_ between
them and its summit but the clear, unentrenched hillside. They lay
there--the line of our brave lads, plainly visible to a pair of good
glasses--there they actually lay! We wanted, so it seemed, but a reserve
to advance in their support and carry them right up to the top. We
said--and yet could hardly believe our own words--"We are through!"</p>

<p>Alas, too previous that remark. Everything began to go wrong. First the
French were shelled and bombed out of the _"Haricot"_; next the right of
the Naval Division became uncovered and they had to give way, losing
many times more men in the yielding than in the capture of their ground.
Then came the turn of the Manchesters, left in the lurch, with their
right flank hanging in the air. By all the laws of war they ought to
have tumbled back anyhow, but by the laws of the Manchesters they hung
on and declared they could do so for ever. How to help? Men! Men, not so
much now to sustain the Manchesters as to force back the Turks who were
enfilading them from the _"Haricot"_ and from that redoubt held for
awhile by the R.N.D. on their right. I implored Gouraud to try and make
a push and promised that the Naval Division would retake their redoubt
if he could retake the _"Haricot"_. Gouraud said he would go in at 3
p.m. The hour came; nothing happened. He then said he could not call
upon his men again till 4 o'clock, and at 4 o'clock he said definitely
that he would not be able to make another assault. The moment that last
message came in I first telephoned and then, to make doubly sure, ran
myself to Hunter-Weston's Headquarters so as not to let another moment
be lost in pulling out the Manchester Brigade. I had 500 yards to go,
and, rising the knoll, I would have been astonished, had I had any
faculty of astonishment left in me, to meet Beetleheim, the Turk, who
was with French in South Africa. I suppose he is here as an interpreter,
or something, but I didn't ask. Seeing me alone for the moment he came
along. He had quite a grip of the battle and seemed to hope I might let
the Manchesters try and stick it out through the night, as he thought
the Turks were too much done to do much more. But it was not good
enough. To fall back was agony; not to do it would have been folly.
Hunter-Weston felt the same. When Fate has first granted just a sip of
the wine of success the slip between the cup and lip comes hardest. The
upshot of the whole affair is that the enemy still hold a strong line of
trenches between us and Achi Baba. Our four hundred prisoners, almost
all made by the Manchester Brigade, amongst whom a good number of
officers, do not console me. Having to make the Manchesters yield up
their hard won gains is what breaks my heart. Had I known the result of
our fight before the event, I should have been happy enough. Three or
four hundred yards of ground plus four hundred prisoners are distances
and numbers which may mean little in Russia or France, but here, where
we only have a mile or two to go, land has a value all its own. Yes, I
should have been happy enough. But, to have to yield up the best
half--the vital half--of our gains--to have had our losses trebled on
the top of a cheaply won victory--these are the reverse side of our
medal for the 4th June.</p>

<p>Going back we fell in with a blood-stained crowd from the Hood, Howe and
Anson Battalions. Down the little gully to the beach we could only walk
very slowly. At my elbow was Colonel Crauford Stuart, commanding the
Hood Battalion. He had had his jaw smashed but I have seen men pull
longer faces at breaking a collar stud. He told me that the losses of
the Naval Division has been very heavy, the bulk of them during their
retreat. From the moment the Turks drove the French out of the
_"Haricot"_ the enfilade fire became murderous.</p>

<p>On the beach was General de Lisle, fresh from France. He is taking over
the 29th Division from Hunter-Weston who ascends to the command of the
newly formed 8th Army Corps. De Lisle seemed in very good form although
it must have been rather an eye-opener landing in the thick of this huge
stream of wounded. How well I remember seeing him galloping at the head
of his Mounted Infantry straight for Pretoria; and my rage when, under
orders from Headquarters, I had to send swift messengers to tell him he
must rein back for some reason never made clear.</p>

<p>_5th June, 1915. Imbros._ Best part of the day occupied in a hundred and
one sequels of the battle. The enemy have been quiet; they have had a
belly-full. De Robeck came off to see me at 5.30, to have a final talk
(amongst other things) as to the Enos and Bulair ideas before I send my
final answer to K. If we dare not advertise the detail of our proposed
tactics, we may take the lesser risk of saying what we are _not_ going
to attempt. The Admiral is perfectly clear against Bulair. There is no
protection there for the ships against submarines except Enos harbour
and Enos is only one fathom deep. After all, the main thing they want is
that I should commit myself to a statement that if I get the drafts and
troops asked for in my various cables, I will make good. That, I find
quite reasonable.</p>

<p>_6th June, 1915. Imbros._ A very hot and dusty day. Still sweeping up
the _debris_ of the battle. Besides my big cable have been studying
strengths with my A.G. The Battalions are dwindling to Companies and the
Divisions to Brigades.</p>

<p>The cable is being ciphered: not a very luminous document: how could it
be? The great men at home seem to forget that they cannot draw wise
counsels from their servants unless they confide in them and give them
_all_ the factors of the problem. If a client goes to a lawyer for
advice the first thing the lawyer asks him to do is to make a clean
breast of it. Before K. asks me to specify what I can do if he sends me
these unknown and--in Great Britain--most variable quantities,
Territorial or New Army Divisions, he ought to make a clean breast of it
by telling me:--</p>

<p>  (1) What he has.
  (2) What Sir John French wants.
  (3) Whether Italy will move--or Greece.
  (4) What is happening in the Balkans,--in the
        Caucasus,--in Mesopotamia.</p>

<p>After all, the Armies of the Caucasus and of Mesopotamia are not
campaigning in the moon. They are two Allied Armies working with me (or
supposed to be working with me) against a common enemy.</p>

<p>The first part of my cable I discuss the cause which led to the
disappointing end to the battle of the 4th already described and then go
on to say, "I am convinced by this action that with my present force my
progress will be very slow, but in the absence of any further important
alteration in the situation such as a definite understanding between
Turkey and Bulgaria, I believe the reinforcements asked for in my No.
234 will eventually enable me to take Kilid Bahr and will assuredly
expedite the decision. I entirely agree that the restricted nature of
the ground I occupy militates against me in success, however much I am
reinforced; that was why in my Nos. M.F. 214 and M.F. 234 I emphasized
the desirability of securing co-operation of new Allied Forces acting on
a second line of operations. I have been very closely considering the
possibility of opening a new line of operations myself, _via_ Enos, if
sufficient reinforcements should be available. The Vice-Admiral,
however, is at present strongly averse to the selection of Enos owing to
the open and unprotected nature of anchorage and to the presence of
enemy submarines. Otherwise Enos offers very favourable prospects, both
strategically and tactically, and is so direct a threat to
Constantinople as to necessitate withdrawal of Turkish troops from the
Peninsula to meet it. Smyrna or even Adramyti which are not open to the
same objections are too far from me, but the effect of entry of a fresh
Ally at either place would inevitably make itself felt before very long
in preventing further massing of the Turkish army against me, and
perhaps even in drawing off troops; a considerable moral and political
effect might also be produced, and all information points to those
districts being denuded of troops.</p>

<p>"With regard to the employment of the reinforcements asked for in my No.
M.F. 234, General Birdwood estimates that four Brigades are necessary to
clear and extend his front sufficiently to prepare a serious move
towards Maidos. I should therefore allocate a corps to the
Australian-New Zealand Army Corps as the other two brigades would be
required to give weight to his advance. The French Force as at present
constituted, and the Naval Division which has been roughly handled,
would be replaced in front of the line by the other corps. This
reinforcement to be exclusive of any help we may receive from Allied
troops operating on a second line of operations so distant as Smyrna.</p>

<p>"With reference to your last paragraph I have no alternative, until Achi
Baba is in my possession, but to keep reinforcements on islands or
elsewhere handy. I have made arrangements at present, however, for one
Infantry Brigade and Engineers of the Lowland Division on the Peninsula,
one Infantry Brigade at Imbros and the remaining Infantry Brigade at
Alexandria to be ready to start at 12 hours' notice whenever I telegraph
for it. Besides all the reasons given above, no troops in existence can
continue fighting night and day without respite."</p>

<p>Three weeks have passed now since I asked for two British Corps or for
Allies and still no reply or notice of any sort except that message of
the 3rd instant expressing doubts as to whether any good purpose will be
served by sending us help "at once." Well; there hasn't been much "at
once" about it but I have not played the Sybilline book trick or doubled
my demand with each delay as I ought perhaps to have done. Now I think
we are bound to hear something but I can't make out what has come over
K. of K. In the old days his prime force lay in his faculty of focusing
every iota of his energy upon the pivotal project, regardless (so it
used to appear) of the other planks of the platform. A "side show" to
him meant the non-vital part of the business, _at that moment_: it was
not a question of troops or of ranks of Generals. For the time being the
interests of an enterprise of five thousand would obliterate those of
fifty. No man ever went the whole hog better. He would turn the whole
current of his energy to help the man of the hour. The rest were bled
white to help him. If they howled they found that K. and his Staff were
deaf, and for the same reason, as the crew of Ulysses to the Sirens.
Several times in South Africa K., so doing, carried the Imperial
Standard to victory through a series of hair's breadth escapes. But
to-day, though he sees, the power of believing in his own vision and of
hanging on to it like a bulldog, seems paralysed. He hesitates. Ten
short years ago, if K.'s heart had been set on Constantinople, why, to
Constantinople he would have gone. Paris might have screamed; he would
not have swerved a hair's breadth till he had gripped the Golden Horn.</p>

<p>_7th June, 1915. Imbros._ Left camp early and went to Cape Helles on a
destroyer. On our little sandbag pier, built by Egyptians and Turkish
prisoners, I met General Wallace and his A.D.C. (a son of Walter
Long's). Wallace has come here to take up his duty as Inspector-General
of Communications. About ten days ago he was forced upon us. He is
reputed a good executive Brigadier of the Indian Army, but we want him,
not to train Sepoys but to create one of the biggest organizing and
administrative jobs in the world. His work will comprise the whole of
the transhipment of stores from the ships to small craft; their dispatch
over 60 miles of sea to the Peninsula, and the maintenance of all the
necessary machinery in good running order. The task is tremendous, and
here is a simple soldier, without any experience of naval men or
matters, or the British soldier, or of Administration on a large scale,
or even of superior Staff duties, sent me for the purpose. We want a
competent business man at Mudros, ready to grapple with millions of
public money; ready to cable on his own for goods or gear by the ten
thousand pounds worth. We want a man of tried business courage; a man
who can tackle contractors. We are sent an Indian Brigadier who has
never, so far as I can make out, in his longish life had undivided
responsibility for one hundred pounds of public belongings. I cabled to
K. my objection as strongly as seemed suitable, but he tells me to carry
on. He tells me to carry on and, in doing so, throws an amusing
sidelight upon himself. Into his cable he sticks the words, "Ellison
cannot be spared." K. believes that my protest _re_ Wallace has, at the
back of it, a wish to put in the Staff Officer he took from me when I
started. He doesn't believe in my zeal for efficiency at Mudros; he
thinks my little plan is to work General Ellison into the billet.
Certainly, I'd like an organizer of Ellison's calibre, but he had not,
it so happens, entered my mind till K. put him there!</p>

<p>Landing at "W" Beach, I walked over to the 9th Division and met Generals
Hunter-Weston, de Lisle and Doran. As we were having our confab, the
Turkish guns from Asia were steadily pounding the ridge just South of
Headquarters. One or two big fellows fell within 100 yards of the Mess.
After an A.1 lunch (for which much glory to Carter, A.D.C.) visited
Gouraud at French Headquarters. Going along the coast we were treated
to an exciting spectacle. The Turkish guns in Asia stopped firing at
Headquarters and turned on to a solitary French transport containing
forage, which had braved the submarines and instead of transhipping (as
is now the order) at Mudros, had anchored close to "V" Beach. After
several overs and unders they hit her three times running and set her on
fire. Destroyers and trawlers rushed to her help. Bluejackets boarded
her; got her fire under control; got her under steam and moved out. The
amazing part of the affair lay in the conduct of the Turks. Having made
their three hits, then was the moment to sink the bally ship. But no;
they switched back once more onto the Peninsula, and left their helpless
prize to make a leisurely and unmolested escape. Anyone but a Turk would
have opened rapid fire on seeking his target smoking like a factory
chimney, ringed round by a crowd of small craft. But these old Turks are
real freaks. Their fierce courage on the defensive is the only cert
about them. On all other points it becomes a fair war risk to presume
upon their happy-go-lucky behaviour. If this crippled ship had been full
of troops instead of hay they would equally have let her slip through
their fingers.</p>

<p>I stayed the best part of an hour with Gouraud. He can throw no light
from the French side upon the reason for the strange hesitations of our
Governments. As he says, after reporting an entirely unexpected and
unprepared for situation and asking for the wherewithal to cope with
it, a Commander should get fresh orders. Either: we cannot give you what
you ask, so fall back onto the defensive; or, go ahead, we will give you
the means. Taking leave we came back again by the 29th Headquarters
where I saw Douglas, commanding the 42nd Division. Got home latish. As I
was on my way to our destroyer took in a wireless saying that submarine
E.11 had returned safely after three fruitful weeks in the Marmora.</p>

<p>A most singular message is in:--</p>

<p>"(No. 5199).</p>

<p>"From Earl Kitchener to General Sir Ian Hamilton.</p>

<p>"With reference to your telegram No. M.F. 301, instead of sending such
telegrams reporting operations, privately to Earl Kitchener, will you
please send them to the Secretary of State. A separate telegram might
have been sent dealing with the latter part about Doran."</p>

<p>May the devil fly away with me if I know what that means! Braithwaite is
as much at a loss as myself. No one knows better than we do how much
store K. sets on having all these messages addressed to him personally.
There's more in this than meets the common or garden optic!</p>

<p>Very heavy firing on the Peninsula at 8 o'clock; a ceaseless tremor of
the air which--faint here--denotes tremendous musketry there.</p>

<p></p>


<chapter>CHAPTER X</chapter>

<p>A DECISION AND THE PLAN</p>

<p>
_8th June, 1915. Imbros._ We are getting "three Divisions of the New
Army"! The Cabinet "are determined to support" us! And why wouldn't they
be? Thus runs the cable:--</p>

<p>"(No. 5217, cipher). Your difficulties are fully recognized by the
Cabinet who are determined to support you. We are sending you three
divisions of the New Army. The first of these will leave about the end
of this week, and the other two will be sent as transport is available.</p>

<p>"The last of the three divisions ought to reach you not later than the
first fortnight in July. By that time the Fleet will have been
reinforced by a good many units which are much less vulnerable to
submarine attack than those now at the Dardanelles, and you can then
count on the Fleet to give you continuous support.</p>

<p>"While steadily pressing the enemy, there seems no reason for running
any premature risks in the meantime."</p>

<p>In face of K.'s hang-fire cable of the 3rd, and in face of this long
three weeks of stupefaction, thank God our rulers have got out of the
right side of their beds and are not going to run away.</p>

<p>The first thing to be done was to signal to the Admiral to come over. At
2 p.m. he and Roger Keyes turned up. The great news was read out and
yet, such is the contrariness of human nature that neither the hornpipe
nor the Highland Fling was danced. Three weeks ago--two weeks ago--we
should have been beside ourselves, but irritation now takes the fine
edge off our rejoicings. Why not three weeks ago? That was the tone of
the meeting. At first:--but why be captious in the very embrace of
Fortune? So we set to and worked off the broad general scheme in the
course of an hour and a half.</p>

<p>Just as the Admiral was going, Ward (of the Intelligence) crossed over
with a nasty little damper. The Turks keep just one lap ahead of us. Two
new Divisions have arrived and have been launched straightway at our
trenches. At the moment we get promises that troops asked for in the
middle of May will arrive by the middle of July the Turks get their
divisions in the flesh:--so much so that they have gained a footing in
the lines of the East Lanes: but there is no danger; they will be driven
out. We have taken some prisoners.</p>

<p>Dined on board the _Triad_. Sat up later than usual. Not only had we
news from home and the news from the Peninsula to thresh out, but there
was much to say and hear about E.11 and that apple of Roger Keyes' eye,
the gallant Nasmith. Their adventures in the sea of Marmora take the
shine out of those of the Argonauts.</p>

<p>Coming back along the well-beaten sandy track, my heart sank to see our
mess tent still lit up at midnight. It might be good news but also it
might not. Fortunately, it was pleasant news; i.e., Colonel Chauvel,
commanding 1st Australian Light Horse Brigade, waiting to see me. I had
known him well in Melbourne where he helped me more than anyone else to
get the hang of the Australian system. He stays the night.</p>

<p>_9th June, 1915. Imbros._ A cable saying the new Divisions will form the
9th Corps and asking me my opinion of Mahon as Corps Commander. I shall
reply at once he is good up to a point and brave, but not up to running
a Corps out here.</p>

<p>Have been sent a gas-mask and a mosquito-net. Quite likely the mask is
good bizz and may prolong my poor life a little bit, but this is
problematical whereas there's no blooming error about the net. This
morning instead of being awakened at 4.30 a.m. by a cluster of
house-flies having a garden party on my nose I just opened one eye and
looked at them running about outside my entrenchments, then closed it
and fell asleep again for an hour.</p>

<p>_10th June, 1915. Imbros._ Nothing doing but sheer hard work. The
sailors the same. Sent one pretty stiff cable as we all agreed that we
must make ourselves quite clear upon the question of guns and shell.
After all, any outsider would think it a plain sailing matter enough--a
demand, that is to say, from Simpson-Baikie at Helles that he should be
gunned and shell supplied on the same scale as the formations he quitted
on the Western Front only a few weeks ago. Simpson-Baikie has been
specially sent to us by Lord K., who has a high opinion of his merits. A
deep-thinking, studious and scientific officer. Well, Baikie says that
to put him on anything like the Western Front footing he wants another
forty-eight 18-pounders; eight 5-inch hows.; eight 4.5. hows.; eight
6-inch; four 9.2 hows.; four anti-aircraft guns and a thousand rounds a
month per field gun; these "wants" he puts down as an absolute minimum.
He also wishes me at once to cable for an aeroplane squadron of three
flights of four machines each, one flight for patrol work; the other two
for spotting.</p>

<p>There is no use enraging people for nothing and "nothing" I am sure
would be the result of this demand were it shot in quite nakedly. But I
have pressed Baikie's vital points home all the same, _vide_ attached:--</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 316).</p>

<p>"Your No. 5088. After a further consideration of the ammunition question
in light of the expenditure on the 4th and 5th June, I would like to
point out that I have only the normal artillery complement of two
divisions, although actually I have five divisions here. Consequently,
each of my guns has to do the work which two and a half guns are doing
in Flanders. Any comparison based on expenditure per gun must therefore
be misleading. Also a comparison based on numbers of troops would prove
to be beside the point, for conditions cannot be identical. Therefore,
as I know you will do your best for me and thus leave me contented with
the decision you arrive at, I prefer to state frankly what amount I
consider necessary. This amount is at least 30 rounds a day for 18-pr.
and 4.5 howitzer already ashore, and I hope that a supply on this scale
may be possible. The number of guns already ashore is beginning to prove
insufficient for their task, for the enemy have apparently no lack of
ammunition and their artillery is constantly increasing. Therefore I
hope that the new divisions may be sent out with the full complement of
artillery, but, if this is done, the ammunition supply for the artillery
of the fresh divisions need only be on the normal scale.</p>

<p>"Since the above was written, I have received a report that the enemy
has been reinforced by 1,300 Germans for fortress artillery; perhaps
their recent shooting is accounted for by this fact."</p>

<p>As to our Air Service, the way this feud between Admiralty and War
Office has worked itself out in the field is simply heart-breaking. The
War Office wash their hands of the air entirely (at the Dardanelles). I
cannot put my own case to the Admiralty although the machines are wanted
for overland tactics--a fatal blind alley. All I could do I did this
afternoon when the Admiral came to tea and took me for a good stiff walk
afterwards.</p>

<p>_11th June, 1915. Imbros._ Sailed over to Anzac with Braithwaite. Took
Birdwood's views upon the outline of our plan (which originated between
him and Skeen) for entering the New Army against the Turks. To do his
share, _durch und durch_ (God forgive me), he wants three new Brigades;
with them he engages to go through from bottom to top of Sari Bair.
Well, I will give him four; perhaps five! Our whole scheme hinges on
these crests of Sari Bair which dominate Anzac and Maidos; the
Dardanelles and the Aegean. The destroyers next took us to Cape Helles
where I held a pow wow at Army Headquarters, Generals Hunter-Weston and
Gouraud being present as well as Birdwood and Braithwaite. Everyone keen
and sanguine. Many minor suggestions; warm approval of the broad lines
of the scheme. Afterwards I brought Birdie back to Anzac and then
returned to Imbros. A good day's work. Half the battle to find that my
Corps Commanders are so keen. They are all sworn to the closest secrecy;
have been told that our lives depend upon their discretion. I have shown
them my M.F. 300 of the 7th June so as to let them understand they are
being trusted with a plan which is too much under the seal to be sent
over the cables even to the highest.</p>

<p>Every General I met to-day spoke of the shortage of bombs and grenades.
The Anzacs are very much depressed to hear they are to get no more bombs
for their six Japanese trench mortars. We told the Ordnance some days
ago to put this very strongly to the War Office. After all, bombs and
grenades are easy things to make if the tails of the manufacturers are
well twisted.</p>

<p>_12th June, 1915. Imbros._ Stayed in camp where de Robeck came to see
me. I wonder what K. is likely to do about Mahon and about ammunition.
When he told me Joffre and French thought 17 rounds per gun per day good
enough, and that he was going to give me as much, there were several
qualifications to our pleasure, but we _were_ pleased, because apart
from all invidious comparisons, we were anyway going to get more stuff.
But we have not yet tasted this new French ration of 17 rounds per gun.</p>

<p>Are we too insistent? I think not. One dozen small field howitzer
shells, of 4.5. calibre, save one British life by taking two Turkish
lives. And although the 4.5. are what we want the old 5-inch are none so
bad. Where would we be now, I wonder, had not Haldane against Press,
Public and four soldiers out of five stuck to his guns and insisted on
creating those 145 batteries of Territorial Field Artillery?</p>

<p>A depressing wire in from the War Office expressing doubt as to whether
they will be able to meet our wishes by embarking units complete and
ready for landing; gear, supplies, munitions all in due proportion, in
the transports coming out here from England. Should we be forced to
redistribute men and material on arrival, we are in for another spell of
delay.</p>

<p>Altogether I have been very busy on cables to-day. The War Office having
jogged my elbow again about the Bulair scheme, I have once more been
through the whole series of pros and cons with the Admiral who has
agreed in the reply I have sent:--clear negative. Three quarters of the
objections are naval; either directly--want of harbours, etc.; or
indirectly--as involving three lines of small craft to supply three
separate military forces. The number of small craft required are not in
existence.</p>

<p>_13th June, 1915. Imbros._ The War Office forget every now and then
other things about the coastline above the Narrows. I have replied:</p>

<p>"Your first question as to the fortification of the coast towards
Gallipoli can be satisfactorily answered only by the Navy as naval
aeroplane observation is the only means by which I can find out about
the coast fortifications. From time to time it has been reported that
torpedo tubes have been placed at the mouth of Soghan Dere and at Nagara
Point. These are matters on which I presume Admiral has reported to
Admiralty, but I am telegraphing to him to make sure as he is away
to-day at Mudros. I will ask him to have aeroplane reconnaissance made
regarding the coast fortifications you mention, to see if it can be
ascertained whether your informant's report is correct, but there are
but few aeroplanes and the few we have are constantly required for
spotting for artillery, photographing trenches, and for reconnaissances
of the troops immediately engaged with us."</p>

<p>I am being forced by War Office questions to say rather more than I had
intended about plans. The following cable took me the best part of the
morning. I hope it is too technical to effect a lodgment in the memories
of the gossips:--</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 328). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to War Office. With
reference to your No. 5441, cipher. From the outset I have fully
realized that the question of cutting off forces defending the Peninsula
lay at the heart of my problem. See my No. M.F. 173, last paragraph, and
paragraphs 2 and 7 of my instructions to General Officer Commanding
Australian and New Zealand Army Corps, of 13th April, before landing. I
still consider, as indicated therein, that the best and most practicable
method of stopping enemy's communications is to push forward to the
south-east from Australian and New Zealand Army Corps.</p>

<p>"The attempt to stop Bulair communications further North than the
Australian and New Zealand Army Corps position would give the Turks too
much room to pass our guns. An advance of little more than two miles in
a south-eastern direction would enable us to command the land
communications between Bulair and Kilid Bahr. This, in turn, would
render Ak Bashi Liman useless to the enemy as a port of disembarkation
for either Chanak or Constantinople. It would enable us, moreover, to
co-operate effectively with the Navy in stopping communication with the
Asiatic shore, since Kilia Liman and Maidos would be under fire from our
land guns.</p>

<p>"It was these considerations which decided me originally to land at
Australian and New Zealand Army Corps position, and in spite of the
difficulties of advancing thence, I see no reason to expect that a new
point of departure would make the task any easier. I have recently been
obliged by circumstances to concentrate my main efforts on pushing
forward towards Achi Baba so as to clear my main port of disembarkation
of shell fire. I only await the promised reinforcements, however, to
enable me to take the next step in the prosecution of my main plan from
the Australian and New Zealand Army Corps.</p>

<p>"I cannot extend the present Australian position until they arrive. See
my No. M.F. 300, as to estimate of troops required, and my No. 304, 7th
June, as to state of siege at Australian and New Zealand Army Corps. If
I succeed the enemy's communications _via_ Bulair and, with the Navy's
help, _via_ Asiatic coast should both be closed, as far as possible, by
the one operation. If, in addition, submarines can stop sea
communications with Constantinople the problem will be solved.</p>

<p>"With regard to supplies and ammunition which can be obtained by the
enemy across the Dardanelles, since Panderma and Karabingha are normally
important centres of collection of food supplies, both cereals and meat,
and since the Panderma-Chanak road is adequate, it would be possible to
provision the peninsula from a great supply depot at Chanak where there
are steam mills, steam bakeries and ample shallow draught craft. If
land communications were blocked near Bulair, ammunition could only be
brought by sea to Panderma, and thence by road to Chanak or by sea
direct to Kilid Bahr.</p>

<p>"Either for supplies or ammunition, however, the difficulty of
effectively stopping supply by sea may be increased by the large number
of shallow craft available at Rodosto, Chanak, Constantinople and
Panderma. But as soon as I can make good advance south-east from
Australian and New Zealand Army Corps, my guns, plus the submarines,
should be able to make all traffic from the Asiatic shore very difficult
for the enemy.</p>

<p>"It is vitally important that future developments should be kept
absolutely secret. I mention this because, although the date of our
original landing was known to hardly anyone here before the ships
sailed, yet the date was cabled to the Turks from Vienna."</p>

<p>The message took some doing and could not, therefore, get clear of camp
till 11 o'clock when I boarded the destroyer _Grampus_, and sailed for
Helles. Lunched with Hunter-Weston at his Headquarters, and then walked
out along the new road being built under the cliffs from "W" Beach to
Gurkha Gully. On the way I stopped at the 29th Divisional Headquarters
where I met de Lisle. Thence along the coast where the 88th Brigade were
bathing. In the beautiful hot afternoon weather the men were happy as
sandboys. Their own mothers would hardly know them--burnt black with the
sun, in rags or else stark naked, with pipes in their mouths. But they
like it! After passing the time of day to a lot of these boys, I climbed
the cliff and came back along the crests, stopping to inspect some of
the East Lancashire Division in their rest trenches.</p>

<p>Got back to Hunter-Weston's about 6 and had a cup of tea. There Cox of
the Indian Brigade joined me, and I took him with me to Imbros where he
is going to stay a day or two with Braithwaite.</p>

<p>_14th June, 1915. Imbros._ K. sends me this brisk little pick-me-up:--</p>

<p>"Report here states that your position could be made untenable by
Turkish guns from the Asiatic shore. Please report on this."</p>

<p>No doubt--no doubt! Yet I was once his own Chief of Staff into whose
hands he unreservedly placed the conduct of one of the most crucial, as
it was the last, of the old South African enterprises: I was once the
man into whose hands he placed the defence of his heavily criticized
action at the Battle of Paardeburg. There it is: he used to have great
faith in me, and now he makes me much the sort of remark which might be
made by a young lady to a Marine. The answer, as K. well knows, depends
upon too many imponderabilia to be worth the cost of a cable. The size
and number of the Turkish guns; their supplies of shell; the power of
our submarines to restrict those supplies; the worth of our own ship and
shore guns; the depth of our trenches; the _moral_ of our men, and so on
_ad infinitum_. The point of the whole matter is this:--the Turks
haven't got the guns--and we know it:--if ever they do get the guns it
will take them weeks, months, before they can get them mounted and
shells in proportion amassed.</p>

<p>K. should know better than any other man in England--Lord Bobs, alas, is
gone--that if there was any real fear of guns from Asia being able to
make us loosen our grip on the Peninsula, I would cable him quickly.
Then why does he ask? Well--and why shouldn't he ask? I must not be so
captious. Much better turn the tables on him by asking him to enable us
to knock out the danger he fears:--</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 331). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to Earl Kitchener. With
reference to your telegram No. 5460. As already reported in my telegram,
fire from the Asiatic shore is at times troublesome, but I am taking
steps to deal with it. Of course another battery of 6-inch howitzers
would greatly help in this."</p>

<p>By coincidence a letter has come in to me this very night, on the very
subject; a letter written by a famous soldier--Gouraud--the lion of the
Ardennes, who is, it so happens, much better posted as to the Asiatic
guns than the Jeremiah who has made K. anxious. The French bear the
brunt of this fire and Gouraud's cool decision to ignore it in favour of
bigger issues marks the contrast between the fighter who makes little of
the enemy and the writer who makes much of him. I look upon Gouraud more
as a coadjutor than as a subordinate, so it is worth anything to me to
find that we see eye to eye at present. For, there is much more in the
letter than his feelings about the guns of Asia: there is an outline
sketch, drawn with slight but masterly touches, covering the past,
present and future of our show:--</p>

<p>                                               _Q.G. le 13 juin 1915._</p>

<p>    Corps Expeditionnaire d'Orient.</p>

<p>     CABINE DU GENERAL.</p>

<p>       N. Cab.
       SECRET.</p>

<p>  Le General de Division Gouraud, Commandant le
  Corps Expeditionnaire d'Orient, a Sir Ian
  Hamilton, G.C.B., D.S.O., Commandant le
  Corps Expeditionnaire Mediterraneen.
                                     QUARTIER GENERAL.</p>

<p>       MON GENERAL,</p>

<p>     Vous avez bien voulu me communiquer une depeche de Lord Kitchener
     faisant connaitre que le Gouvernement anglais allait envoyer
     incessamment aux Dardanelles trois nouvelles divisions et des
     vaisseaux moins vulnerables aux sous-marins. D'apres les
     renseignements qui m'ont ete donnes, on annonce 14 de ces monitors;
     4 seraient armes de pieces de 35 a 38 m/ 4 de pieces de 24, les
     autres de 15.</p>

<p>     C'est donc sur terre et sur mer un important renfort.</p>

<p>     J'ai l'honneur de vous soumettre ci-dessous mes idees sur son
     emploi.</p>

<p>     Jetons d'abord un coup d'oeil sur la situation. Il s'en degage, ce
     me semble, deux faits.</p>

<p>     D'une part, le combat du 4 juin, qui, malgre une preparation
     serieuse n'a pas donne de resultat en balance avec le vigoureux et
     couteux effort fourni par les troupes alliees, a montre que, guides
     par les Allemands, les Turcs ont donne a leur ligne une tres grande
     force. La presqu'ile est barree devant notre front de plusieurs
     lignes de tranchees fortement etablies, precedees en plusieurs
     points de fil de fer barbeles, flanquees de mitrailleuses,
     communiquant avec l'arriere par des boyaux, formant un systeme de
     fortification comparable a celui du grand Front.</p>

<p>     Dans ces tranchees les Turcs se montrent bons soldats, braves,
     tenaces. Leur artillerie a constamment et tres sensiblement
     augmente en nombres et en puissance depuis trois semaines.</p>

<p>     Dans ces conditions, et etant donne que les Turcs ont toute liberte
     d'amener sur ce front etroite toute leur armee, on ne peut se
     dissimuler que les progres seront lents et que chaque progres sera
     couteux.</p>

<p>     Les Allemands appliqueront certainement dans les montagnes et les
     ravins de la presqu'ile le systeme qui leur a reussi jusqu'ici en
     France.</p>

<p>     D'autre part l'ennemi parait avoir change de tactique. Il a voulu
     au debut nous rejeter a la mer; apres les pertes enormes qu'il a
     subi dans les combats d'avril et de mai, il semble y avoir renonce
     du moins pour le moment.</p>

<p>     Son plan actuel consiste a chercher a nous bloquer de front, pour
     nous maintenir sur l'etroit terrain que nous avons conquis, et a
     nous y rendre la vie intenable en bombardant les camps et surtout
     les plages de debarquement. C'est ainsi que les quatre batteries de
     grosses pieces recemment installees entre Erenkeui et Yenishahr ont
     apporte au ravitaillement des troupes une gene qu'on peut dire
     dangereuse, puisque la consommation dans dernieres journees a
     legerement depasse le ravitaillement.</p>

<p>     Au resume nous sommes bloques de front et pris par derriere. Et
     cette situation ira en empirant du fait des maladies, resultant du
     climat, de la chaleur, du bivouac continuel, peut etre des
     epidemies, et du fait que la mer rendra tres difficile tout
     debarquement des la mauvaise saison, fin aout.</p>

<p>     Ceci pose, comment employer les gros renforts attendus. Plusieurs
     solutions se presentent a l'esprit.</p>

<p>     Primo, en Asie.</p>

<p>     C'est la premiere idee qui se presente; etant donne l'interet de se
     rendre maitre de la region Yenishahr-Erenkeui, qui prend nos plages
     de debarquement a revers.</p>

<p>     Mais c'est la une mesure d'un interet defensif, qui ne fera pas
     faire un pas en avant. Il est permis d'autre part de penser que les
     canons des monitors anglais, qui sont sans doute destines a
     detruire les defenses du detroit, commenceront par nous debarrasser
     des batteries de l'entree. Enfin nous disposerons d'ici peu d'un
     front de mer Seddul-Bahr Eski Hissarlick, dont les pieces
     puissantes contrebattront efficacement les canons d'Asie.</p>

<p>     Secundo, vers Gaba-Tepe.</p>

<p>     Au Sud de Gaba Tepe s'etend une plaine que les cartes disent
     accessible au debarquement. Des troupes debarquees la se trouvent a
     8 kilometres environ de Maidos, c'est a dire au point ou la
     presqu'ile est la plus etroite.</p>

<p>     Sans nul doute, trouveront elles devant elles les memes difficultes
     qu'ici et il sera necessaire notemment de se rendre maitre des
     montagnes qui dominent la plaine au Nord. Mais alors que la prise
     d'Achi Baba ne sera qu'un grand succes militaire, qui nous mettra
     le lendemain devant les escarpements de Kilid-Bahr, l'occupation de
     la region Gaba Tepe-Maidos nous placerait au dela des detroits,
     nous permettrait d'y constituer une base ou les sous-marins de la
     mer de Marmara pourraient indefiniment s'approvisionner.</p>

<p>     Si le barrage des Dardanelles n'etait pas brise, il serait tourne.</p>

<p>     Tertio, vers Boulair.</p>

<p>     Cette solution apparait comme le plus radicale, celui qui
     dejouerait le plan de l'ennemi. Constantinople serait directement
     menace par ce coup retentissant.</p>

<p>     Toute la question est de savoir si, avec leurs moyens nouveaux, les
     monitors, les Amiraux sont en mesure de proteger un debarquement,
     qui comme celui du 25 avril necessiterait de nombreux bateaux.</p>

<p>     En resume, j'ai l'honneur d'emettre l'avis de poser nettement aux
     Amiraux la question du debarquement a Boulair, d'y faire
     reconnaitre l'etat actuel des defenses par bateaux, avions et si
     possible agents, sans faire d'acte de guerre pour ne pas donner
     l'eveil.</p>

<p>     Au cas ou le debarquement serait juge impossible, j'emet l'avis
     d'employer les renforts dans la region Gaba-Tepe, ou les
     Australiens ont deja implante un solide jalon.</p>

<p>     Concurremment, je pense qu'il serait du plus vif interet pour hater
     la decision, de creer au Gouvernement Turc des inquietudes dans
     d'autres parties de l'Empire, pour l'empecher d'amener ici toutes
     ses forces.</p>

<p>     Dans cet ordre d'idees on peut envisager deux moyens. L'un, le plus
     efficace, est l'action russe ou bulgare. La Grece est mal placee
     geographiquement pour exercer une action sur la guerre. Seule la
     Bulgarie, par sa position geographique, prend les Turcs a revers.
     Sans doute, a voir la facon dont les Turcs amenent devant nous les
     troupes et les canons d'Adrianople, ont ils un accord avec la
     Bulgarie, mais la guerre des Balkans prouve que la Bulgarie n'est
     pas embarrassee d'un accord si elle voit ailleurs son interet. La
     question est donc d'offrir un prix fort a la Bulgarie.</p>

<p>     L'autre est de provoquer des agitations dans differentes parties de
     l'Empire, d'y faire operer des destructions par des bandes,
     d'obliger les Turcs a y envoyer du monde. Cela encore vaut la peine
     d'y mettre le prix.</p>

<p>     Je suis, avec un profond respect, mon General,</p>

<p>                                 Votre tres devoue,
                                      (_Sd._) GOURAUD.</p>

<p>Boarded a destroyer at 11.15 a.m. and sailed straight for Gully Beach.
Then into dinghy and paddled to shore where I lunched with de Lisle at
the 29th Divisional Headquarters. Hunter-Weston had come up to meet me
from Corps Headquarters.</p>

<p>With both Generals I rode a couple of miles up the Gully seeing the 87th
Brigade as we went. When we got to the mouth of the communication trench
leading to the front of the Indian Brigade, Bruce of the Gurkhas was
waiting for us, and led me along through endless sunken ways until we
reached his firing line.</p>

<p>Every hundred yards or so I had a close peep at the ground in front
through de Lisle's periscope. The enemy trenches were sometimes not more
than 7 yards away and the rifles of the Turks moving showed there was a
man behind the loophole. Many corpses, almost all Turks, lay between the
two lines of trenches. There was no shelling at the moment, but rifle
bullets kept flopping into the parapet especially when the periscope was
moved.</p>

<p>At the end of the Gurkha line I was met by Colonel Wolley Dod, who took
me round the fire trenches of the 86th Brigade. The Dublin Fusiliers
looked particularly fit and jolly.</p>

<p>Getting back to the head of the Gully I rode with Hunter-Weston to his
Corps Headquarters where I had tea before sailing.</p>

<p>When I got to Imbros the Fleet were firing at a Taube. She was only
having a look; flying around the shipping and Headquarters camp at a
great height, but dropping no bombs. After a bit she scooted off to the
South-east. Cox dined.</p>

<p>_15th June, 1915. Imbros._ Yesterday I learned some detail about the
conduct of affairs the other day--enough to make me very anxious indeed
that no tired or nervy leaders should be sent out with the new troops.
So I have sent K. a cable!--</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 334). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to Earl Kitchener.</p>

<p>"With reference to the last paragraph of your telegram No. 5250, cipher,
and my No. M.F. 313. I should like to submit for your consideration the
following views of the qualities necessary in an Army Corps Commander on
the Gallipoli Peninsula. In that position only men of good stiff
constitution and nerve will be able to do any good. Everything is at
such close quarters that many men would be useless in the somewhat
exposed headquarters they would have to occupy on this limited terrain,
though they would do quite good work if moderately comfortable and away
from constant shell fire. I can think of two men, Byng and Rawlinson.
Both possess the requisite qualities and seniority; the latter does not
seem very happy where he is, and the former would have more scope than a
cavalry Corps can give him in France."</p>

<p>Left camp the moment I got this weight off my chest; boarded the
_Savage_, or rather jumped on her ladder like a chamois and scrambled on
deck like a monkey. It was blowing big guns and our launch was very
nearly swamped. Crossing to Helles big seas were making a clean sweep of
the decks. Jolly to look at from the bridge.</p>

<p>After a dusty walk round piers and beaches lunched with Hunter-Weston
before inspecting the 155th and 156th Brigades. On our road we were met
by Brigadier-Generals Erskine and Scott-Moncrieff. Walked the trenches
where I chatted with the regimental officers and men, and found my
compatriots in very good form.</p>

<p>Went on to the Royal Naval Division Headquarters where Paris met me.
Together we went round the 3rd Marine Brigade Section under
Brigadier-General Trotman. These old comrades of the first landing gave
me the kindliest greetings.</p>

<p>Got back to 8th Corps Headquarters intending to enjoy a cup of tea _al
fresco_, but we were reckoning without our host (the Turkish one) who
threw so many big shell from Asia all about the mound that, (only to
save the tea cups), we retired with dignified slowness into our dugouts.
Whilst sitting in these funk-holes, as we used to call them at
Ladysmith, General Gouraud ran the gauntlet and made also a slow and
dignified entry. He was coming back with me to Imbros. As it was getting
late we hardened our hearts to walk across the open country between
Headquarters and the beach, where every twenty seconds or so a big
fellow was raising Cain. Fortune favouring we both reached the sea with
our heads upon our shoulders.</p>

<p>An answer is in to our plea for a Western scale of ammunition, guns and
howitzers. They cable sympathetically but say simply they can't. Soft
answers, etc., but it would be well if they could make up their minds
whether they wish to score the next trick in the East or in the West. If
they can't do that they will be doubly done.</p>

<p>A purely passive defence is not possible for us; it implies losing
ground by degrees--and we have not a yard to lose. If we are to remain
we must keep on attacking here and there to maintain ourselves! But; to
expect us to attack without giving us our fair share--on Western
standards--of high explosive and howitzers shows lack of military
imagination. A man's a man for a' that whether at Helles or Ypres. Let
me bring my lads face to face with Turks in the open field, we _must_
beat them every time because British volunteer soldiers are superior
individuals to Anatolians, Syrians or Arabs and are animated with a
superior ideal and an equal joy in battle. Wire and machine guns prevent
this hand to hand, or rifle to rifle, style of contest. Well, then the
decent thing to do is to give us shells enough to clear a fair field.
To attempt to solve the problem by letting a single dirty Turk at the
Maxim kill ten--twenty--fifty--of our fellows on the barbed
wire,--ten--twenty--fifty--_each of whom is worth several dozen Turks_,
is a sin of the Holy Ghost category unless it can be justified by dire
necessity. But there is no necessity. The supreme command has only to
decide categorically that the Allies stand on the defensive on the West
for a few weeks and then Von Donop can find us enough to bring us
through. Joffre and French, as a matter of fact, would hardly feel the
difference. If the supreme command can't do that; and can't even send us
trench mortars as substitutes, let them harden their hearts and wind up
this great enterprise for which they simply haven't got the nerve.</p>

<p>If only K. would come and see for himself! Failing that--if only it were
possible for me to run home and put my own case.</p>

<p>_16th June, 1915. Imbros._ Gouraud, a sympathetic guest, left for French
Headquarters in one of our destroyers at 3.30 p.m. He is a real Sahib; a
tower of strength. The Asiatic guns have upset his men a good deal. He
hopes soon to clap on an extinguisher to their fire by planting down two
fine big fellows of his own Morto Bay way: we mean to add a couple of
old naval six-inchers to this battery. During his stay we have very
thoroughly threshed out our hopes and fears and went into the plan which
Gouraud thinks offers chances of a record-breaking victory. If the
character of the new Commanders and the spirit of their troops are of
the calibre of those on his left flank at Helles he feels pretty
confident.</p>

<p>Talking of Commanders, my appeal for a young Corps Commander of a "good
stiff constitution" has drawn a startling reply:--</p>

<p>"(No. 5501, cipher). From Earl Kitchener to Sir Ian Hamilton. Your No.
M.F. 334. I am afraid that Sir John French would not spare the services
of the two Generals you mention, and they are, moreover, both junior to
Mahon, who commands the 10th Division which is going out to you. Ewart,
who is very fit and well, would I think do. I am going to see him the
day after to-morrow.</p>

<p>"Mahon raised the 10th Division and has produced an excellent unit. He
is quite fit and well, and I do not think that he could now be left
behind."</p>

<p>So the field of selection for the new Corps is to be restricted to some
Lieutenant-General senior to Mahon--himself the only man of his rank
commanding a Division and almost at the top of the Lieutenant-Generals!
Oh God, if I could have a Corps Commander like Gouraud! But this block
by "Mahon" makes a record for the seniority fetish. I have just been
studying the Army List with Pollen. Excluding Indians, Marines and
employed men like Douglas Haig and Maxwell, there _are_ only about one
dozen British service Lieutenant-Generals senior to Mahon, and, of that
dozen only two are _possible_--Ewart and Stopford! There _are_ no
others. Ewart is a fine fellow, with a character which commands respect
and affection. He is also a Cameron Highlander whose father commanded
the Gordons. As a presence nothing could be better; as a man no one in
the Army would be more welcome. But he would not, with his build and
constitutional habit, last out here for one fortnight. Despite his
soldier heart and his wise brain we can't risk it. We are unanimous on
that point. Stopford remains. I have cabled expressing my deep
disappointment that Mahon should be the factor which restricts all
choice and saying,</p>

<p>"However, my No. M.F. 334[20] gave you what I considered to be the
qualities necessary in a Commander, so I will do my best with what you
send me.</p>

<p>"With regard to Ewart. I greatly admire his character, but he positively
could not have made his way along the fire trenches I inspected
yesterday. He has never approached troops for fifteen years although I
have often implored him, as a friend, to do so. Would not Stopford be
preferable to Ewart, even though he does not possess the latter's calm?"</p>

<p>I begin to think I shall be recalled for my importunity. But, in for a
penny in for a pound, and I have fired off the following protest to a
really disastrous cable from the War Office saying that the New Army is
to bring _no_ 4.5-inch howitzers with it; no howitzers at all, indeed,
except sixteen of the old, inaccurate 5-inch Territorial howitzers, some
of which "came out" at Omdurman and were afterwards--the whole
category--found so much fault with in South Africa. Unless they are
going to have an August push in France they might at least have lent us
forty-eight 4.5 hows. from France to see the New Army through their
first encounter with the enemy. They could all be run back in a fast
cruiser and would only be loaned to us for three weeks or a month. If
the G.S. at Whitehall can't do those things, they have handed over the
running of a world war to one section of the Army. I attach my
ultimatum: I cannot make it more emphatic; instead of death or victory
we moderns say howitzers or defeat:--</p>

<p>"(No. 5489, cipher, M.G.O.) From War Office to General Officer
Commanding-in-Chief, Mediterranean Expeditionary Force. Your No. M.F.
316. It is impossible to send more ammunition than we are sending you.
528 rounds per 18-pr will be brought out by each Division. Instead of
4.5-inch howitzers we are sending 16 5-inch howitzers with the 13th
Division, as there is more 5-inch ammunition available. By the time that
the last of the three Divisions arrive we hope to have supplied a good
percentage of high explosive shells, but you should try to save as much
as you can in the meantime. Until more ammunition is available for them,
we cannot send you any 4.5-inch howitzers with the other two Divisions,
and even if more 5-inch were sent the fortnightly supply of ammunition
for them would be very small."</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 337). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to War Office. With
reference to your No. 5489, cipher. I am very sorry that you cannot
send the proper howitzers, and still more sorry for the reason, that of
ammunition. The Turkish trenches are deep and narrow, and only effective
weapon for dealing with them is the howitzer. I realize your
difficulties, and I am sure that you will supply me with both howitzers
and ammunition as soon as you are able to do so. I shall be glad in the
meantime of as many more trench mortars and bombs as you can possibly
spare. We realize for our part that in the matter of guns and ammunition
it is no good crying for the moon, and for your part you must recognize
that until howitzers and ammunition arrive it is no good crying for the
Crescent."</p>

<p>The Admiral and Godley paid me a visit; discussed tea and sea transport,
then a walk.</p>

<p>There is quite a break in the weather. Very cold and windy with a little
rain in the forenoon.</p>

<p>_17th June, 1915. Imbros._ Smoother sea, but rough weather in office. A
cable from the Master General of the Ordnance in reply to my petition
for another battery of 6-inch howitzers:--</p>

<p>"(No. 5537, cipher, M.G.O.) From War Office to the General Officer
Commanding-in-Chief, Mediterranean Expeditionary Force. Your telegram
No. M.F. 331. We can send out another battery of 6-inch howitzers, but
cannot send ammunition with it. Moreover, we cannot increase the present
periodical supply, so that if we send the additional howitzers you must
not complain of the small number of rounds per gun sent to you, as
experience has shown is sometimes done in similar cases. It is possible
that the Navy may help you with 6-inch ammunition. Please say after
consideration of the above if you want the howitzers sent."</p>

<p>My mind plays agreeably with the idea of chaining the M.G.O. on to a
rock on the Peninsula whilst the Asiatic batteries are pounding it. That
would learn him to be an M.G.O.; singing us Departmental ditties whilst
we are trying to hold our Asiatic wolf by the ears. I feel very
depressed; we are too far away; so far away that we lie beyond the
grasp of an M.G.O.'s imagination. That's the whole truth. Were the
Army in France to receive such a message, within 24 hours the
Commander-in-Chief, or at the least his Chief of the Staff, would walk
into the M.G.O.'s office and then proceed to walk into the M.G.O. I
can't do that; a bad tempered cable is useless; I have no weapon at my
disposal but very mild sarcasm:--</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 343). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to War Office. Your No.
5537, cipher, M.G.O. Please send the battery of 6-inch howitzers. Your
admonition will be borne in mind. Extra howitzers will be most useful to
replace pieces damaged by enemy batteries on the Asiatic side of the
Dardanelles. No doubt in time the ammunition question will improve. Only
yesterday prisoners reported that 14 more Turkish heavy guns were coming
to the Peninsula."</p>

<p>Have written another screed to French. As it gives a sort of summing up
of the state of affairs to-day I spatchcock (as Buller used to say) the
carbon:--</p>

<p>         "GENERAL HEADQUARTERS,
    "MEDITERRANEAN EXPEDITIONARY FORCE,
                      _17th June, 1915._</p>

<p>  "MY DEAR FRENCH,</p>

<p>"It must be fully a month since I wrote you but no one understands
better than you must do, how time flies under the constant strain of
these night and day excursions and alarms. Between the two letters there
has been a desperate lot of fighting, mostly bomb and bayonet work, and,
except for a good many Turks gone to glory, there is only a few hundred
yards of ground to show for it all at Anzac, and about a mile perhaps in
the southern part of the Peninsula. But taking a wider point of view, I
hope our losses and efforts have gained a good deal for our cause
although they may not be so measurable in yards. First, the Turks are
defending themselves instead of attacking Egypt and over-running Basra;
secondly, we are told on high authority, that the action of the Italians
in coming in was precipitated by our entry into this part of the
theatre; thirdly, if we can only hold on and continue to enfeeble the
Turks, I think myself it will not be very long before some of the Balkan
States take the bloody plunge.</p>

<p>"However all that may be, we must be prepared at the worst to win
through by ourselves, and it is, I assure you, a tough proposition. In
a manoeuvre battle of old style our fellows here would beat twice
their number of Turks in less than no time, but, actually, the
restricted Peninsula suits the Turkish tactics to a 'T.' They have
always been good at trench work where their stupid men have only simple,
straightforward duties to perform, namely, in sticking on and shooting
anything that comes up to them. They do this to perfection; I never saw
braver soldiers, in fact, than some of the best of them. When we
advance, no matter the shelling we give them, they stand right up firing
coolly and straight over their parapets. Also they have unlimited
supplies of bombs, each soldier carrying them, and they are not half bad
at throwing them. Meanwhile they are piling up a lot of heavy artillery
of very long range on the Asiatic shore, and shell us like the devil
with 4.5, 6-inch, 8, 9.2 and 10-inch guns--not pleasant. This
necessitates a very tough type of man for senior billets. X--Y--, for
instance, did not last 24 hours. Everyone here is under fire, and really
and truly the front trenches are safer, or at least fully as safe, as
the Corps Commander's dugout. For, if the former are nearer the
Infantry, the latter is nearer the big guns firing into our rear.</p>

<p>"Another reason why we advance so slowly and lose so much is that the
enemy get constant reinforcements. We have overcome three successive
armies of Turks, and a new lot of 20,000 from Syria are arriving here
now, with 14 more heavy guns, so prisoners say, but I hope not.</p>

<p>"I have fine Corps Commanders in Birdwood, Hunter-Weston and Gouraud.
This is very fortunate. Who is to be Commander of the new corps I cannot
say, but we have one or two terrifying suggestions from home.</p>

<p>"Last night a brisk attack headed by a senior Turkish Officer and a
German Officer was made on the 86th Brigade. Both these Officers were
killed and 20 or 30 of their men, the attack being repulsed. Against the
South Wales Borderers a much heavier attack was launched. Our fellows
were bombed clean out of their trenches, but only fell back 30 yards and
dug in. This morning early we got maxims on to each end of the place
they had stormed, and then the Dublins retook it with the bayonet. Two
hundred of their dead were left in the trench, and we only had 50
casualties--not so bad! A little later on in the day a d----d submarine
appeared and had some shots at our transports and store ships. Luckily
she missed, but all our landing operations of supplies were suspended.
These are the sort of daily anxieties. All one can do is to carry on
with determination and trust in providence.</p>

<p>"I hope you are feeling fit and that things are going on well generally.
Give my salaams to the great Robertson, also to Barry. Otherwise please
treat this letter as private. With all kind remembrance.</p>

<p>                       "Believe me,
                           "Yours very sincerely,
                               "(_Sd._) IAN HAMILTON."</p>

<p></p>


<chapterCHAPTER XI</chapter>

<p>BOMBS AND JOURNALISTS</p>

<p>
Our beautiful East Lancs. Division is in a very bad way. One more month
of neglect and it will be ruined: if quickly filled up with fresh drafts
it will be better than ever. Have cabled:--</p>

<p>"(M.F.A. 871). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to War Office. The
following is the shortage of officers and rank and file in each Brigade
of the XLIInd East Lancashire Division including the reinforcements
reported as arriving:--</p>

<p>  125th Brigade    50 Officers, 1,852 rank and file.
  126th Brigade    31 Officers, 1,714 rank and file.
  127th Brigade    50 Officers, 2,297 rank and file.</p>

<p>"A stage of wastage has now been reached in this Division, especially in
the 127th Manchester Brigade, when filling up with drafts will make it
as good or better than ever. If, however, they have to go on fighting in
their present condition and suffer further losses, the remnants will not
offer sufficiently wide foundation for reconstituting cadres.</p>

<p>"Lord Kitchener might also like to know this, that a satisfactory
proportion of the officers recently sent out to fill casualties are
shaping very well indeed."</p>

<p>An amalgam of veterans and fresh keen recruits, cemented by a common
county feeling as well as by war tradition, makes the best fighting
formation in the world. The veterans give experience and
steadiness;--when the battle is joined the old hands feel bound to make
good their camp-fire boastings to the recruits. The recruits bring
freshness and the spirit of competition;--they are determined to show
that they are as brave as the old fighters. But, if the East Lancs. go
on dwindling, the cadre will not retain strength enough to absorb and
shape the recruits who will, we must suppose, some day be poured into
it. A perishing formation loses moral force in more rapid progression
than the mere loss of members would seem to warrant. When a battalion
which entered upon a campaign a thousand strong,--all keen and
hopeful,--gets down to five hundred, comrades begin to look round at one
another and wonder if any will be left. When it falls to three hundred,
or less, the unit, in my experience, is better drawn out of the line.
The bravest men lose heart when, on parade, they see with their own eyes
that their Company--the finest Company in the Army--has become a
platoon,--and the famous battalion a Company. A mould for shaping young
enthusiasms into heroisms has been scrapped and it takes a desperate
long time to recreate it.</p>

<p>I want to be sure K. himself takes notice and that is why I refer to him
at the tail end of the cable. We have also cabled saying that the idea
of sending so many rounds per gun per day was excellent, but that "we
have received no notice of any despatch later than the S.S. _Arabian_,
which consignment" (whenever it might arrive?) "was only due to last
until the day before yesterday"! So this is what our famous agreement to
have munitions on the scale deemed necessary by Joffre and French pans
out at in practice. Two-fifths of their amount and that not delivered!</p>

<p>Dined with the Admiral on board the _Triad_. A glorious dinner. The
sailormen have a real pull over us soldiers in all matters of messing.
Linen, plate, glass, bread, meat, wine; of the best, are on the spot,
always: even after the enemy is sighted, if they happen to feel a sense
of emptiness they have only to go to the cold sideboard.</p>

<p>Coming back found mess tent brilliantly lit up and my staff entertaining
their friends. So I put on my life-saving waistcoat and blew it out;
clapped my new gas-mask on my head and entered. They were really
startled, thinking the devil had come for them before their time.</p>

<p>Just got a telegram saying that M. Venezelos has gained a big majority
in the Greek Election. Also, that the King of Greece is dying, and that,
therefore, the Greek Army can't join us until he has come round or gone
under.</p>

<p>_18th June, 1915. Imbros._ Went over to Kephalos Camp to inspect
Rochdale's 127th (Manchester) Brigade. The Howe Battalion of the 2nd
Naval Brigade were there (Lieutenant-Colonel Collins), also, the 3rd
Field Ambulance R.N.D. All these were enjoying an easy out of the
trenches and, though only at about half strength, had already quite
forgotten the tragic struggles they had passed through. In fattest peace
times, I never saw a keener, happier looking lot. I drew courage from
the ranks. Surely these are the faces of men turned to victory!</p>

<p>Some twenty unattached officers fresh from England were there: a likely
looking lot. One of the brightest a Socialist M.P.</p>

<p>The inspection took me all forenoon so I had to sweat double shifts
after lunch. Hunter-Weston came over from Helles at 7.15 p.m. and we
dined off crayfish. He was in great form.</p>

<p>The War Office can get no more bombs for our Japanese trench mortars! A
catastrophe this! Putting the French on one side, we here, in this great
force, possess only half a dozen good trench mortars--the Japanese.
These six are worth their weight in gold to Anzac. Often those fellows
have said to me that if they had twenty-five of them, with lots of
bombs, they could render the Turkish trenches untenable. Twice, whilst
their six precious mortars have been firing, I have stood for half an
hour with Birdie, watching and drinking in encouragement. About one bomb
a minute was the rate of fire and as it buzzed over our own trenches
like a monstrous humming bird all the naked Anzacs laughed. Then, _such_
an explosion and a sort of long drawn out ei-ei-ei-ei cry of horror from
the Turks. It was fine,--a real corpse-reviving performance and now the
W.O. have let the stock run out, because some ass has forgotten to order
them in advance. Have cabled a very elementary question: "Could not the
Japanese bombs be copied in England?"</p>

<p>Being the Centenary of Waterloo, the thoughts and converse of
Hunter-Weston and myself turned naturally towards the lives of the
heroes of a hundred years ago whose monument had given us our education,
and from that topic, equally naturally, to the boys of the coming
generation. Then wrote out greetings to be sent by wire on my own behalf
and on behalf of all Wellingtonians serving under my command here: this
to the accompaniment of unusually heavy shell fire on the Peninsula.</p>

<p>_Later._--Have just heard that after a heavy bombardment the Turks made
an attack and that fighting is going on now.</p>

<p>_19th June, 1915. Imbros._ The Turks expended last night some 500 H.E.
shells; 250 heavy stuff from Asia and some thousands of shrapnel. They
then attacked; we counter-attacked and there was some confused
in-and-out Infantry fighting. We hear that the South Wales Borderers,
the Worcesters, the 5th Royal Scots and the Naval Division all won
distinction. Wiring home I say, "If Lord Kitchener could tell the Lord
Provost of Edinburgh how well the 5th Bn. Royal Scots have done, the
whole of this force would be pleased." The Turks have left 1,000 dead
behind them. Prisoners say they thought so much high explosive would
knock a hole in our line: the bombardment was all concentrated on the
South Wales Borderers' trench.</p>

<p>Writing most of the day. Lord K. has asked the French Government to send
out extra quantities of H.E. shell to their force here; also, he has
begged them to order Gouraud to lend me his guns. In so far as the
French may get more H.E. this is A.1. But if K. thinks the British will
_directly_ benefit--I fear he is out of his reckoning: it would be fatal
to my relations with Gouraud, now so happy, were he even to suspect that
I had any sort of lien on his guns. Unless I want to stir up jealous
feelings, now entirely quiescent, I cannot use this cable as a lever to
get French guns across into our area. Gouraud's plans for his big attack
are now quite complete. A million pities we cannot attack
simultaneously. That we should attack one week and the French another
week is rotten tactically; but, practically, we have no option. We
British want to go in side by side with the French--are burning to do
so--but we cannot think of it until we can borrow shell from Gouraud;
and, naturally, he wants every round he has for his own great push on
the 21st. Walked down in the evening to see what progress was being made
with the new pier. Colonel Skeen, Birdwood's Chief of Staff, dined and
seems clever, as well as a very pleasant fellow.</p>

<p>_20th June, 1915. Imbros._ Rose early. Did a lot of business. The King's
Messenger's bag closed at 8 a.m. Told K. about the arrival of fresh
Turkish troops and our fighting on the 18th. The trenches remain as
before, but the Turks, having failed, are worse off.</p>

<p>I have also written him about war correspondents. He had doubted whether
my experiences would encourage me to increase the number to two or
three. But, after trial, I prefer that the public should have a
multitude of councillors. "When a single individual," I say, "has the
whole of the London Press at his back he becomes an unduly important
personage. When, in addition to this, it so happens, that he is inclined
to see the black side of every proposition, then it becomes difficult to
prevent him from encouraging the enemy, and from discouraging all our
own people, as well as the Balkan States. If I have several others to
counterbalance, then I do not care so much."</p>

<p>Fired off a second barrel through Fitz from whom I have just heard that
my Despatch cannot be published as it stands but must be bowdlerized
first, all the names of battalions being cut out. Instead of saying,
"The landing at 'W' had been entrusted to the 1st Bn. Lancashire
Fusiliers (Major Bishop) and it was to the complete lack of the sense of
danger or of fear of this daring battalion that we owed our astonishing
success," I am to say, "The landing, etc., had been entrusted to a
certain battalion."</p>

<p>The whole of this press correspondence; press censorship; despatch
writing and operations cables hang together and will end by hanging the
Government.</p>

<p>My operations cables are written primarily for K., it is true, but they
are meant also to let our own people know what their brothers and sons
are up against and how they are bearing up under unheard of trials.
There is not a word in those cables which would help or encourage the
enemy. I am best judge of that and I see to it myself.</p>

<p>What is the result of my efforts to throw light upon our proceedings? A
War Office extinguisher from under which only a few evil-smelling
phrases escape. As I say to Fitz:--</p>

<p>"You seem to see nothing beyond the mischief that may happen if the
enemy gets to know too much about us; you do not see that this danger
can be kept within bounds and is of small consequence when compared with
the keenness or dullness of our own Nation."</p>

<p>The news that the War Office were going to send us no more Japanese
bombs spread so great a consternation at Anzac that I have followed up
my first remonstrance with a second and a stronger cable:--</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 348). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to War Office. Your No.
5272, A.2.[21] I particularly request that you may reconsider your
proposal not to order more Japanese bombs. These bombs are most
effective and in high favour with our troops whose locally-made weapons,
on which they have frequently to rely, are far inferior to the bombs
used by the Turks. Our great difficulty in holding captured trenches is
that the Turks always counter-attack with a large number of powerful
bombs. Apparently their supply of these is limitless. Unless the delay
in arrival is likely to extend over several months, therefore, I would
suggest that a large order be sent to Japan. We cannot have too many of
these weapons, and this should not cancel my No. M.F.Q.T. 1321, which
should be treated as additional."</p>

<p>Drafted also a long cable discussing a diversion on the Asiatic shore of
the Dardanelles. So some work had been done by the time we left camp at
9.15 a.m., and got on board the _Triad_. After a jolly sail reached
Mudros at 2 p.m., landing on the Australian pier at 3 p.m. Mudros is a
dusty hole; _ein trauriges Nest_, as our German friends would say.</p>

<p>Worked like a nigger going right through Nos. 15 and 16 Stationary
Hospitals. Colonel Maher, P.M.O., came round, also Colonel Jones,
R.A.M.C., and Captain Stanley, R.A.M.C. Talked with hundreds of men:
these are the true philosophers.</p>

<p>_21st June, 1915. Mudros._ Went at it again and overhauled No. 2
Stationary Hospital under Lieutenant-Colonel White, as well as No. 1
Stationary Hospital commanded by Lieutenant-Colonel Bryant. The doctors
praised me for inventing something new to say to each man. But all the
time in my mind was the thought of Gouraud. I have wanted him to do it
absolutely on his own, and I could not emphasize this better than by
coming right away to Mudros. Back to the _Triad_ by 1 p.m. No news.
Weighed anchor at once, steaming for Imbros, where we cast anchor at
about 6 p.m. Freddie Maitland has arrived here, like a breath of air
from home, to be once more my A.D.C.; his features wreathed in the
well-known, friendly smile. The French duly attacked at dawn and the 2nd
Division have carried a series of redoubts and trenches. The 1st
Division did equally well but have been driven back again by
counter-attacks. Fighting is still going on.</p>

<p>While I have been away Braithwaite has cabled home in my name asking
which of the new Divisions is the best, as we shall have to use them
before we can get to know them.</p>

<p>_22nd June, 1915. Imbros._ An anxious night. Gouraud has done
splendidly; so have his troops. This has been a serious defeat for the
Turks; a real bad defeat, showing, as it does, that given a modicum of
ammunition we can seize the strongest entrenchments of the enemy and
stick to them.</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 357). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to Secretary of State for
War. After 24 hours' heavy and continuous fighting a substantial
success has been achieved. As already reported, the battle of 4th-5th
June resulted in a good advance of my centre to which neither my right
nor my left were able to conform, the reason being that the Turkish
positions in front of the flanks are naturally strong and exceedingly
well fortified. At 4.30 a.m. yesterday, General Gouraud began an attack
upon the line of formidable works which run along the Kereves Dere. By
noon the second French Division had stormed and captured all the Turkish
first and second line trenches opposite their front, including the
famous Haricot Redoubt, with its subsidiary maze of entanglements and
communication trenches. On their right, the first French Division, after
fierce fighting, also took the Turkish trenches opposite their front,
but were counter-attacked so heavily that they were forced to fall back.
Again, this Division attacked, again it stormed the position, and again
it was driven out. General Gouraud then, at 2.55 p.m., issued the
following order:"</p>

<p>'From Colonel Viont's report it is evident that the preparation for the
attack at 2.15 p.m. was not sufficient.</p>

<p>'It is indispensable that the Turkish first line of trenches in front of
you should be taken, otherwise the gains of the 2nd Division may be
rendered useless. You have five hours of daylight, take your time, let
me know your orders and time fixed for preparation, and arrange for
Infantry assault to be simultaneous after preparation.'</p>

<p>"As a result of this order, the bombardment of the Turkish left was
resumed, the British guns and howitzers lending their aid to the French
Artillery as in the previous attacks. At about 6 p.m., a fine attack was
launched, 600 yards of Turkish first line trenches were taken, and
despite heavy counter-attacks during the night, especially at 3.20 a.m.,
all captured positions are still in our hands. Am afraid casualties are
considerable, but details are lacking. The enemy lost very heavily. One
Turkish battalion coming up to reinforce, was spotted by an aeroplane,
and was practically wiped out by the seventy-fives before they could
scatter.</p>

<p>"Type of fighting did not lend itself to taking prisoners, and only some
50, including one officer, are in our hands. The elan and contempt of
danger shown by the young French drafts of the last contingent,
averaging, perhaps, 20 years of age, was much admired by all. During the
fighting, the French battleship _St. Louis_ did excellent service
against the Asiatic batteries. All here especially regret that Colonel
Girodon, one of the best staff officers existing, has been severely
wounded whilst temporarily commanding a brigade. Colonel Nogues, also an
officer of conspicuous courage, already twice wounded, at Kum Kale, has
again been badly hit."</p>

<p>Girodon is one in ten thousand; serious, brave and far sighted. The
bullet went through his lung. We are said to have suffered nearly 3,000
casualties.</p>

<p>They say that the uproar of battle was tremendous, especially between
midnight and 4 a.m. Some of our newly arrived troops stood to their arms
all night thinking the end of the world had come.</p>

<p>At 6 p.m. de Robeck, Keyes, Ormsby Johnson and Godfrey came over from
the flagship to see me.</p>

<p>Have got an answer about the Japanese trench mortars and bombs. In two
months' time a thousand bombs will be ready at the Japanese Arsenal, and
five hundred the following month. The trench mortars--bomb guns they
call them--will be ready in Japan in two and a half months' time. Two
and a half months, plus half a month for delay, plus another month for
sea transit, makes four months! There are some things speak for
themselves. Blood, they say, cries out to Heaven. Well, let it cry now.
Over three months ago I asked--_my first request_--for these primitive
engines and as for the bombs, had Birmingham been put to it, Birmingham
could have turned them out as quick as shelling peas.</p>

<p>Am doing what I can to fend for myself. This Dardanelles war is a war,
if ever there was one, of the ingenuity and improvised efforts of man
against nature plus machinery. We are in the desert and have to begin
very often at the beginning of things. The Navy _now_ assure me that
their Dockyard Superintendent at Malta could make us a fine lot of hand
grenades in his workshops if Lord Methuen will give him the order.</p>

<p>So I have directed a full technical specification of the Turkish hand
grenades being used against us with effects so terrible, to be sent on
to Methuen telling him it is simple, effective, that I hope he can make
them and will be glad to take all he can turn out.</p>

<p>_23rd June, 1915. Imbros._ Another day in camp. De Robeck and Keyes came
over from the _Triad_ to unravel knotty points.</p>

<p>Am enraged to recognize in Reuter one of my own cables which has been
garbled in Egypt. The press censorship is a negative evil in London; in
Cairo there is no doubt it is positive. After following my wording
pretty closely, a phrase has been dovetailed in to say that the Turks
have day and night to submit to the capture of trenches. These cables
are repeated to London and when they get back here what will my own men
think me? If, as most of us profess to believe, it is a mistake to tell
lies, what a specially fatal description of falsehood to issue
short-dated bulletins of victory with only one month to run. I have
fired off a remonstrance as follows:--</p>

<p>"(No M.F. 359). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to War Office. A Reuter
telegram dated London, 16th June, has just been brought to my notice in
which it is stated that the Press Bureau issues despatch in which the
following sentence occurs: 'Day and night they (the Turks) have to
submit to capture of trenches.' This information is incorrect, and as
far as we are aware, has not been sent from here. This false news puts
me in a false position with my troops, who know it to be untrue, and I
should be glad if you would trace whence it emanates.</p>

<p>"Repeated to General Officer Commanding, Egypt."</p>

<p>_24th June, 1915. Imbros._ Three days ago we asked the War Office to let
us know the merits of the three new Divisions. The War Office replied
placing them in the order XIth; XIIth; Xth, and reminding me that the
personality of the Commander would be the chief factor for deciding
which were to be employed in any particular operation. K. now
supplements this by a cable in which he sizes up the Commanders.
Hammersley gets a good _chit_ but the phrase, "he will have to be
watched to see that the strain of trench warfare is not too much for
him" is ominous. I knew him in October, '99, and thought him a fine
soldier. Mahon, "without being methodical," is praised. Shaw gets a
moderate eulogy, but we out here are glad to have him for we know him.
On these two War Office cables Hammersley and the 11th Division should
be for it.</p>

<p>After clearing my table, embarked with Braithwaite and Mitchell aboard
the _Basilisk_ (Lieutenant Fallowfield) and made her stand in as close
as we dared at Suvla Bay and the coast to the North of it. We have kept
a destroyer on patrol along that line, and we were careful to follow the
usual track and time, so as to rouse no suspicions.</p>

<p>To spy out the land with a naval telescope over a mile of sea means
taking a lot on trust as we learned to our cost on April 25th. We can't
even be sure if the Salt Lake _is_ a lake, or whether the glister we see
there is just dry sand. We shall have to pretend to do some gun
practice, and drop a shell on to its surface to find out. No sign of
life anywhere, not even a trickle of smoke. The whole of the Suvla Bay
area looks peaceful and deserted. God grant that it may remain so until
we come along and make it the other thing.</p>

<p>On my return the Admiral came to hear what I thought about it all. Our
plan is bold, but there never was a state of affairs less suited to half
and half, keep-in-the-middle-of-the-road tactics than that with which
the Empire is faced to-day. If we get through here, now, the war will,
must be, over next year. My Manchurian Campaign and two Russian
Manoeuvres have taught me that, from Grand Duke to Moujiks, our Allies
need just that precise spice of initiative which we, only we in the
world, can lend them. Advice, cash, munitions aren't enough; our
palpable presence is the point. The arrival of Birdwood, Hunter-Weston
and Gouraud at Odessa would electrify the whole of the Russian Army.</p>

<p>As to the plan, I have had the G.S. working hard upon it for over a
fortnight (ever since the Cabinet decided to support us). Secrecy is so
ultra-vital that we are bound to keep the thing within a tiny circle. I
am not the originator. Though I have entirely fathered it, the idea was
born at Anzac. We have not yet got down to precise dates, units or
commanders but, in those matters, the two cables already entered this
morning should help. The plan is based upon Birdwood's confidence that,
if only he can be strengthened by another Division, he can seize and
hold the high crest line which dominates his own left, and in my own
concurrence in that confidence. Sari Bair is the "keep" to the Narrows;
Chunuk Bair and Hill 305 are its keys: i.e., from those points the
Turkish trenches opposite Birdwood can be enfiladed: the land _and_ sea
communications of the enemy holding Maidos, Kilid Bahr and Krithia can
be seen and shelled and, in fact, any strong force of Turks guarding the
European side of the Narrows can then be starved out, whilst a weak
force will not long resist Gouraud and Hunter-Weston. As to our tactical
scheme for producing these strategical results, it is simple in outline
though infernally complicated in its amphibious and supply aspects. The
French and British at Helles will attack so as to draw the attention of
the Turks southwards. To add to this effect, we are thinking of asking
the Anzacs to exert a preliminary pressure on the Gaba Tepe alarum to
the southwards. We shall then give Birdwood what he wants, an extra
division, and it will be a problem how to do so without letting the
enemy smell a rat. Birdwood's Intelligence are certain that no trenches
have been dug by the enemy along the high ridge from Chunuk Bair to Hill
305. He is sure that with one more Division under his direct command,
plus the help of a push from Helles to ease his southern flank, he can
make good these dominating heights.</p>

<p>[Illustration: THE NARROWS FROM CHUNUK BAIR]</p>

<p>_But_,--here comes the second half of the plan: the balance of the
reinforcements from home are also to be thrown into the scale so as at
the same time to give further support to Birdwood on his _northern_
flank and to occupy a good harbour (Suvla Bay) whence we can run a light
railway line and more effectively feed the troops holding Sari Bair than
they could be fed from the bad, cramped beaches of Anzac Cove. This will
be the more necessary as the process of starving out the Turks to the
south must take time. Suvla Bay should be an easy base to seize as it is
weakly held and unentrenched whilst, tactically, any troops landed there
will, by a very short advance, be able to make Birdwood's mind easy
about his left. Altogether, the plan seems to me simple in outline, and
sound in principle. The ground between Anzac and the Sari Bair crestline
is worse than the Khyber Pass but both Birdwood and Godley say that
their troops can tackle it. There are one or two in the know who think
me "venturesome" but, after all, is not "nothing venture nothing win" an
unanswerable retort?</p>

<p>De Robeck is excited over some new anti-submarine nets. They are so
strong and he can run them out so swiftly that they open, he seems to
think, new possibilities of making landings,--not on open coasts like
the North of the Aegean but at places like Yukeri Bay, where the nets
could be spread from the North and South ends of Tenedos to shoals
connecting with Asia so as to make a torpedo proof basin for transports.
The Navy, in fact, suddenly seem rather bitten with the idea of landing
opposite Tenedos. But whereas, this very afternoon, our own eyes
confirmed the aeroplane reports that Suvla Bay is unentrenched, weakly
held and quiescent, only yesterday a division of the enemy were reputed
to be busy along the whole of the coastline to the South of Besika Bay.</p>

<p>I have raised a hornet's nest by my objection to faked cables; but I
will not have it done. They may suppress but they shall not invent.</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 366). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to War Office. Your No.
12431. I do not object to General Officer Commanding, Egypt, publishing
any telegram I send him, as I write them for that purpose. But I do
object to the addition of news which is untrue, and which can surely be
seen through by any reading public. If we can take trenches at our will,
why are we still on this side of Achi Baba?</p>

<p>"In compliance with Lord Kitchener's instructions I send a telegram to
the Secretary of State for War and repeat it to Egypt; also to Australia
and New Zealand if it affect these Dominions. Please see your No.
10,475, code, and my No. M.F. 285, instructing me to do this. These
telegrams are practically identical when they leave here, and are
intended to be used as a communique and to be published. Instead of this
I find a mutilated and misleading Cairo telegram reproduced in London
Press in place of the true version I sent to the Secretary of State for
War."</p>

<p>General Paris crossed from Helles to dine and stay the night. After
dinner, Commodore Backhouse came over to make his salaams to his
Divisional Chief.</p>

<p>Gouraud has sent me his reply to Lord K.'s congratulations on his
victory of the 21st. He says,</p>

<p>     "_Vous prie exprimer a Lord Kitchener mes respectueux remerciements
     nous n'avons, eu qu'a prendre exemple sur les heroiques regiments
     anglais qui ont debarque dans les fils de fer sur la plage de
     Seddulbahr_."</p>

<p>_25th June, 1915. Imbros._ At 8 a.m. walked down with Paris to see him
off. Worked till 11 a.m. and then crossed over to "K" Beach where
Backhouse, commanding the 2nd Naval Brigade, met me. Inspected the Hood,
Howe and Anson Battalions into which had been incorporated the
Collingwood and Benbow units--too weak now to carry on as independent
units. The Hood, Howe and Anson are suffering from an acute attack of
indigestion, and Collingwoods and Benbows are sick at having been
swallowed. But I had to do it seeing there is no word of the cruel
losses of the battle of the 4th being made good by the Admiralty. The
Howe, Hood and Anson attacked on our extreme right, next the French.
They did most gloriously--most gloriously! As to the Collingwoods, they
were simply cut to pieces, losing 25 officers out of 28 in a few
minutes. Down at the roots of this unhappiness lie the neglect to give
us our fair share of howitzers and trench mortars--in fact stupidity!
The rank and file all round looked much better for their short rest, and
seemed to like the few halting words of praise I was able to say to
them. Lunched with Backhouse in a delicious garden under a spreading fig
tree; then rode back.</p>

<p>At 5 p.m. Ashmead-Bartlett had an appointment, K. himself took trouble
to send me several cables about him a little time ago. Referring in one
of them to the dangers of letting Jeremiah loose in London, K. said,
"Ashmead-Bartlett has promised verbally to speak to no one but his
Editor, who can be trusted." Verbally, or in writing, my astonishment at
K.'s confidence can only find expression in verse:--</p>

<p>  "Oft expectation fails, and most oft there
  Where most it promises;"</p>

<p>He, Ashmead-Bartlett, came to-day to beg me to deliver him out of the
hands of the Censor. He wants certain changes made and I have agreed.</p>

<p>Next, he fully explained to me the importance of the Bulair Lines and
urged me to throw the new Divisions against them. He seems to think he
is mooting to me a spick and span new idea--that he has invented
something. Finally, he suggests ten shillings and a free pardon be
offered to every Turk who deserts to our lines with his rifle and kit:
he believes we should thus get rid of the whole of the enemy army very
quickly.</p>

<p>This makes one wonder what would Ashmead-Bartlett himself do if he were
offered ten shillings and a good supper by a Mahommedan when he was
feeling a bit hungry and hard up amongst the Christians. Anyway, there
is no type of soldier man fighting in the war who is more faithful to
his salt than the Osmanli Turk. Were we to offer fifty pounds per head,
instead of ten shillings, the bid would rebound in shame upon ourselves.</p>

<p>Colonel Sir Mark Sykes was my next visitor. He is fulfilling the promise
of his 'teens when he was the shining light of the Militia; was as keen
a Galloper as I have had on a list which includes Winston and F.E., and,
generally, gained much glory, martial, equestrian, histrionic,
terpsichorean at our Militia Training Camp on Salisbury Plain in '99.
Now he has mysteriously made himself (heaven knows how) into our premier
authority on the Middle East and is travelling on some ultra-mysterious
mission, very likely, _en passant_, as a critic of our doings: never
mind, he is thrice welcome as a large-hearted and generous person.</p>

<p>Dined with de Robeck on board the _Triad_. He is _most_ hospitable and
kind. I have not here the wherewithal to give back cutlet for cutlet,
worse luck.</p>

<p>_26th June, 1915._ Worked till past 11 o'clock, then started
for Anzac with Braithwaite per destroyer _Pincher_ (Lieutenant-Commander
Wyld). After going a short way was shifted to the _Mosquito_
(Lieutenant-Commander Clarke). We had biscuits in our pockets, but the
hospitable Navy stood us lunch.</p>

<p>When the Turks saw a destroyer come bustling up at an unusual hour they
said to themselves, "fee faw fum!" and began to raise pillars of water
here and there over the surface of the cove. As we got within a few
yards of the pier a shell hit it, knocking off some splinters. I jumped
on to it--had to--then jumped off it nippier still and, turning to the
right, began to walk towards Birdie's dugout. As I did so a big fellow
pitched plunk into the soft shingle between land and water about five or
six yards behind me and five or six yards in front of Freddie. The slush
fairly smothered or blanketed the shell but I was wetted through and was
stung up properly with small gravel. The hardened devils of Anzacs, who
had taken cover betwixt the shell-proofs built of piles of stores,
roared with laughter. Very funny--to look at!</p>

<p>As the old Turks kept plugging it in fairly hot, I sat quiet in
Birdwood's dugout for a quarter of an hour. Then they calmed down and we
went the rounds of the right trenches. In those held by the Light Horse
Brigade under Colonel G. de L. Ryrie, encountered Lieutenant Elliot,
last seen a year ago at Duntroon.</p>

<p>Next, met Colonel Sinclair Maclagan commanding 3rd (Australian) Infantry
Brigade. After that saw the lines of Colonel Smith's Brigade, where
Major Browne, R.A., showed me a fearful sort of bomb he had just
patented.</p>

<p>At last, rather tired by my long day, made my way back, stopping at
Birdie's dugout en route. Boarded the _Mosquito_; sailed for and reached
camp without further adventure. General Douglas of the East Lancs
Division is here. He has dined and is staying the night. A melancholy
man before whose eyes stands constantly the tragic melting away without
replacement of the most beautiful of the Divisions of Northern England.</p>

<p>_27th June, 1915. Imbros._ Blazing hot; wound up my mail letters; fought
files, flies and irritability; tackled a lot of stuff from Q.M.G. and
A.G.; won a clear table by tea time. In the evening hung about waiting
for de Robeck who had signalled over to say he wanted to talk business.
At the last he couldn't come.</p>

<p>The sequel to the letter telling me I'd have to cut the names of
battalions out of my Despatch has come in the shape of a War Office
cable telling me that, if I agree, it is proposed "to have the despatch
reviewed and a slightly different version prepared for publication." I
hope my reply to Fitz may arrive in time to prevent too much titivation.</p>

<p>An imaginative War Office (were such a thing imaginable) would try first
of all to rouse public enthusiasm by letting them follow quite closely
the brave doings of their own boys' units whatever these might be. Next,
they would try and use the Press to teach the public that there are
three kinds of war, (_a_) military war, (_b_) economic war and (_c_)
social war. Lastly, they would explain to the Cabinet that this war of
ours is a mixture of (_a_) and (_b_) with more of (_b_) than (_a_) in
it.</p>

<p>How can economic victory be won? (1) by enlisting the sympathy of
America; (2) by taking Constantinople.</p>

<p>The idea that we can hustle the Kaiser back over the Rhine and march on
to Berlin at the double emanates from a school of thought who have
devoted much study to the French Army, not so much to that of the
Germans. But we _can_ (no one denies it) hustle the Turks out of
Constantinople if we will make an effort, big, no doubt, in itself but
not very big compared to that entailed by a few miles' advance in the
West. Let us do that and, forthwith, we enlist economics on our side.</p>

<p>None of these things can be carried through without the help of the
Press. Second only to enthusiasm of our own folk comes the sweetening of
the temper of the neutral. Hard to say at present whether our Censorship
has done most harm in the U.K. or the U.S.A. Before leaving for the
Dardanelles I begged hard for Hare and Frederick Palmer, the Americans,
knowing they would help us with the Yanks just as much as aeroplanes
would help us with the Turks, but I was turned down on the plea that the
London Press would be jealous.</p>

<p>These are the feelings which have prompted my pen to-day. Writing one of
the few great men I know I put the matter like this:--</p>

<p>"From my individual point of view a hideous mistake has been made on the
correspondence side of the whole of this Dardanelles business. Had we
had a dozen good newspaper correspondents here, the vital life-giving
interest of these stupendous proceedings would have been brought right
into the hearths and homes of the humblest people in Britain....</p>

<p>"As for information to the enemy, this is too puerile altogether. The
things these fellows produce are all read and checked by competent
General Staff Officers. To think that it matters to the Turks whether a
certain trench was taken by the 7th Royal Scots or the 3rd Warwicks is
just really like children playing at secrets. The Censors who are by way
of keeping everyone in England in darkness allow extremely accurate
outline panoramas of the Australian position from the back; trenches,
communication tracks, etc., all to scale; a true military sketch, to
appear in the _Illustrated London News_ of 5th June. The wildest
indiscretions in words could not equal this."</p>

<p>Again I say the Press must win. On no subject is there more hypocrisy
amongst big men in England. They pretend they do not care for the Press
and _sub rosa_ they try all they are worth to work it. How well I
remember my Chief of the General Staff coming up to me at a big
conference on Salisbury Plain where I had spent five very useful minutes
explaining the inwardness of things to old Bennett Burleigh, the War
Correspondent. He (the C.G.S.) begged me to see Burleigh privately,
afterwards, as it would "create a bad impression" were I seen by
everyone to be on friendly terms with the old man! He meant it very
kindly: from his point of view he was quite right. I lay no claim to be
more candid than the rest of them: quite the contrary. Only, over that
particular line of country, I am more candid. Whenever anyone
ostentatiously washes his hands of the Press in my hearing I chuckle
over the memory of the administrator who was admonishing me as to the
unsuitability of a public servant having a journalistic acquaintance
when, suddenly, the door opened; the parlour-maid entered and said,
"Lord Northcliffe is on the 'phone."</p>

<p>Have told Lord K. in my letter we have just enough shell for one more
attack. After that, we fold our hands and wait the arrival of the new
troops and the new outfit of ammunition:--not "wait and see" but "wait
and suffer." A month is a desperate long halt to have in a battle. A
month, at least, to let weariness and sickness spread whilst new armies
of enemies replace those whose hearts we have broken,--at a cost of how
many broken hearts, I wonder, in Australasia and England?</p>

<p>This enforced pause in our operations is a desperate bad business: for
to-day there is a feeling in the air--thrilling through the ranks--that
_at last_ the upper hand is ours. Now is the moment to fall on with
might and main,--to press unrelentingly and without break or pause until
we wrest victory from Fortune. Morally, we are confident
but,--materially? Alas, to-morrow, for our last "dart" before
reinforcements arrive a month hence, my shell only runs to a forty
minutes' bombardment of some half a mile of the enemy's trenches. We
simply have not shell wherewith to cover more or keep it up any longer.</p>

<p>A General laying down the law to a Field Marshal is as obnoxious to
military "form" as a vacuum was once supposed to be to the sentiments of
nature. The child, who teaches its grandmother to suck eggs, commits a
venial fault in comparison. So I have had to convey my precepts
insensibly to Milord K.--to convey them in homeopathic doses of parable.
The brilliant French success of the 21st-22nd, I explain to him, was due
to the showers of shell wherewith they deluged the Turkish lines until
their defenders were sitting dazed with their dugouts in ruins about
them. Also, in the same epistle, I have tried to explain Anzac.</p>

<p>In the domain of tactics our landing at Helles speaks for itself. Since
gunpowder was invented nothing finer than the 29th Division has been
achieved. But it will be a long time yet before people grasp that the
landing at Anzac is just as remarkable in the imaginative domain of
strategy. The military student of the future will, I hope and believe,
realize the significance of the stroke whereby we are hourly forcing a
great Empire to commit _hari kiri_ upon these barren, worthless
cliffs--whereby we keep pressing a dagger exactly over the black heart
of the Ottoman Raj. Only skin deep--so far; only through the skin. Yet
already how freely bleeds the wound. Daily the effort to escape this
doom; to push away the threat of that painful point will increase. Even
if we were never to make another yard's advance,--here--in the cove of
Anzac--is the cup into which the life blood of the Caliphat shall be
pressed. And on the whole Gallipoli Peninsula this little cove is the
one and only spot whereon a base could have been established, which is
sheltered (to a bearable extent) from the force of the enemy's fire.
Dead ground; defiladed from inland batteries; deep water right close to
the shore!</p>

<p>Enver dares not leave Anzac alone. We are too near his neck; the
Narrows!! So on this most precarious, God-forsaken spot he must maintain
an Army of his best troops, mostly supplied by sea,--by sea whereon our
submarines swallow 25 per cent. of their drafts, munitions and food,
just as a pike takes down the duckling before the eyes of their mother
on a pond. Hold fast's the word. We have only to keep our grip firm and
fast; Turkey will die of exhaustion trying to do what she can't do;
drive us into the sea!</p>

<p>Braithwaite and Amery dined. Great fun seeing Amery again. _What_
memories of his concealment in the Autocrat's "Special" going to the
Vereeniging Conference; of our efforts to create a strategical training
ground for British troops in South Africa; of our battles against one
another over the great Voluntary Service issue.</p>

<p></p>


<chapter>CHAPTER XII</chapter>

<p>A VICTORY AND AFTER</p>

<p>
_28th June, 1915. Imbros._ The fateful day.</p>

<p>Left camp with Braithwaite, Dawnay and Ward. Embarked on the destroyer
_Colne_ (Commander Seymour) and sailed for Helles. The fire fight was
raging. From the bridge we got a fine view as our guns were being
focused on and about the north-west coast. The cliff line and half a
mile inland is shrouded in a pall of yellow dust which, as it twirls,
twists and eddies, blots out Achi Baba himself. Through this curtain
appear, dozens at a time, little balls of white,--the shrapnel searching
out the communication trenches and cutting the wire entanglements. At
other times spouts of green or black vapour rise, mix and lose
themselves in the yellow cloud. The noise is like the rumbling of an
express train--continuous; no break at all. The Turks sitting there in
their trenches--our men 100 yards away sitting in _their_ trenches! What
a wonderful change in the art,--no not the art, in the mechanism--of
war. Fifteen years ago armies would have stood aghast at our display of
explosive energy; to-day we know that our shortage is pitiable and that
we are very short of stuff; perilously short.--(Written in the cabin of
the _Colne_.)</p>

<p>Jimmy Watson met me on the pier. He is Commandant Advance Base. Deedes
also met me and the whole band of us made our way inland to my battle
dugout. This is probably our last onslaught before the new troops and
new supplies of shell come to hand in about a month from now. We have
just enough stuff to deal with one narrow strip by the coast. Had it not
been for some help from the French, we could not have entered upon this
engagement at all, but must have continued to sit still and be shot
at--rather an expensive way of fighting if John Bull could only be told
the truth. Now, although the area is limited the battle is a big one,
fairly entitled to be called a general action. As I said, the French are
helping Simpson-Baikie in his bombardment; the Fleet are helping us with
the fire of the _Scorpion_, _Talbot_ and _Wolverine_, and Birdwood has
been asked to try and help us from Anzac by making a push there to hold
the enemy and prevent him sending reinforcements south. On their side
the Turks are making a very feeble reply. Looks as if we had caught them
with their ammunition parks empty.</p>

<p>I went into the dugout indescribably slack; hardly energy to struggle
against the heat and the myriads of flies. I came out of it radiant. The
Turks are beat. Five lines of their best trenches carried (or, at least,
four regular lines plus a bit extra); the Boomerang Redoubt rushed, and
in two successive attacks we have advanced 1,000 yards. Our losses are
said to be moderate. The dreaded Boomerang collapsed and was stormed
with hardly a casualty. This was owing partly to the two trench mortars
lent us by the French and partly to the extraordinary fine shooting of
our own battery of 4.5 howitzers. The whole show went like
clockwork--like a Field Day. First the 87th Brigade took three lines of
trenches; then our guns lengthened their range and fuses and the 86th
Brigade, with the gallant Royal Fusiliers at their head, scrambled over
the trenches already taken by the 87th, and took the last two lines in
splendid style. We could have gone right on but we had nothing to go on
with. How I wish the whole world and his wife could have been here to
see our lines advancing under fire quite steadily with intervals and
dressing as on parade. A wonderful show!</p>

<p>As the 87th Brigade left the trenches at 11 a.m., the enemy opened a hot
shrapnel fire on them but although some men fell, none faltered as we
could see very well owing to the following device. The 29th attackers
had sewn on to their backs triangles cut out of kerosine tins. The idea
was to let these bright bits of metal flash in the sunlight and act as
helios. Thus our guns would be able to keep an eye on them. The
spectacle was extraordinary. From my post I could follow the movements
of every man. One moment after 11 a.m. the smoke pall lifted and moved
slowly on with a thousand sparkles of light in its wake: as if someone
had quite suddenly flung a big handful of diamonds on to the landscape.</p>

<p>At 11.30 the 86th Brigade likewise advanced; passed through the 87th and
took two more lines of trenches.</p>

<p>At mid-day I signalled, "Well done 29th Division and 156th Brigade. Am
watching your splendid attack with admiration. Stick to it and your
names will become famous in your homes."</p>

<p>At 1.50 I got a reply, "Thanks from all ranks 29th. We are here to
stay."</p>

<p>At 3.15 I ran across and warmly congratulated Hunter-Weston, staying
with him reading the messages until about 4 p.m. when I went on to see
Gouraud. Hunter-Weston, Gouraud and Braithwaite agree that:--_had we
only shell to repeat our bombardment of this morning, now, we could go
on another 1,000 yards before dark,--result, Achi Baba to-morrow, or, at
the latest, the day after; Achi Baba_ and fifty guns perhaps with, say,
10,000 prisoners.</p>

<p>At 5 p.m. Gouraud and I walked back to Hunter-Weston's G.H.Q. A load was
off our minds--we were wonderfully happy. At 5.30 a message from Birdie
to say the Queenslanders had thrust out towards Gaba Tepe and had
"drawn" the Turkish reserves who had been badly hammered by our guns.
With this crowning mercy in my pocket, walked down and boarded the
destroyer _Scourge_ (Lieutenant Tupper) and got back to camp before
seven. What a day! May our glorious Infantry gain everlasting
_Kudos_--and the Gunners, too, may the good use they made of their shell
ration create a legend.</p>

<p>The French official photographer has fixed a moment by snapping Gouraud
and myself overlooking the Hellespont from the old battlements.</p>

<p>[Illustration: GENERAL GOURAUD "Central News" photo.]</p>

<p>_Midnight._--When I lay down in my little tent two hours ago the canvas
seemed to make a sort of sounding board. No sooner did I try to sleep
than I heard the musketry rolling up and dying away; then rolling up
again in volume until I could stick it no longer and simply had to get
up and pick a path, through the brush and over sandhills, across to the
sea on the East coast of our island. There I could hear nothing. Was the
firing then an hallucination--a sort of sequel to the battle in my
brain? Not so; far away I could see faint corruscations of sparks; star
shells; coloured fire balls from pistols; searchlights playing up and
down the coast. Our fellows were being hard beset to hold on to what
they had won; there, where the horizon stood out with spectral
luminosity. What a contrast; the direct fear, joy, and excitement of the
fighting men out there in the searchlights and the dull anguish of
waiting here in the darkness; imagining horrors; praying the Almighty
our men may be vouchsafed valour to stick it through the night;
wondering, waiting until the wire brings its colourless message!</p>

<p>One thought I have which is in the end a sure sleep-getter--the
advancing death. Whether by hours or by years, by inches or by leagues,
by bullets or bacilli, we struggle-for-lifers will very soon struggle no
more. My last salaams are well-nigh due to my audience and to the stage.
That rare and curious being called I is more fragile than any porcelain
jar. How on earth it has preserved itself so long, heaven only knows.
One pellet of lead, it falls in a heap of dust; the Peninsula
disappears; the fighting men fall asleep; the world and its glories
become a blank--not even a dream--nothing!</p>

<p>_29th June, 1915. Imbros._ Sunlight has scattered the spectres of the
night,--they have fled, leaving behind them only the matter-of-fact
residuum of heavy Turkish counter-attacks against our fresh-won ground.
The fighting took place along the coastline, and the stillness of the
night seems to have helped the sounds of musketry across the twelve
miles of sea. The attack was most determined: repulsed by bombs and with
the bayonet: at daylight the enemy came under a cross-fire of machine
guns and rifles and were shot to pieces.</p>

<p>Very early approved the revise of my long cable (for the Cabinet)
outlining my hopes and fears:--</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 381). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to Earl Kitchener. With
reference to your telegram No. 5770, cipher. As the Cabinet are anxious
to consider my situation in all its bearings, it is necessary I should
open to you all my mind. In my No. M.F. 328 of 13th June, I gave you an
outline of my plan, based on the news that I was to be given new
divisions, and I told you what I should do with a possible fourth
division in my No. M.F. 364 of 23rd June. I am now asked whether I
consider a fifth division advisable and necessary.</p>

<p>"I have taken time to answer this question, as the addition of each new
division necessitates, in such a theatre of war as this, a
reconsideration of the whole strategical and tactical situation as well
as of the power of the Fleet to work up to the increased demands that
would be placed upon it. The scheme which might tempt me (Naval
considerations permitting) of landing the 4th and 5th Divisions together
with the three divisions and one or two divisions from Cape Helles and
Anzac on flank of shore of Gulf of Saros to march on Rodosto and
Constantinople I reject because the 4th and 5th Divisions cannot reach
me simultaneously with all their transport.</p>

<p>"But assuming that reinforcements can only reach me in echelon of
divisions I have decided that the best policy would be to adhere to my
original plan of endeavouring to turn the enemy's right at Anzac with
the first three divisions and to gain a position from Gaba Tepe to
Maidos. I should then use the 4th and 5th Divisions, in case of
non-success at first to reinforce this wing, and in case of success
possibly to effect a landing on the southern shore of the Dardanelles;
and since the enemy's forces south of the Straits would probably have
been reduced to a minimum in order to oppose my reinforced strength on
the Peninsula I should in the latter case count upon these two divisions
doing more than hold a bridge-head (see my M.F. 349 of 19th June), and
should expect them, reinforced from the northern wing if necessary, to
press forward to Chanak and thus to cut off this enemy's sole remaining
line of supply.[22] By these means I should hope to compel the
surrender of the whole Gallipoli Army. Meanwhile, with my force on the
Asiatic side I would be enabled to establish in Morto Bay a base safe
from the bad weather which must be expected later on.</p>

<p>"With regard to ammunition, the more we can get the more easy will our
task be, but I hope we may be able to achieve success at the end of July
with the amount available. As we are so far from home, however, we
cannot afford to run things too fine, and we shall always be obliged to
keep up a large reserve until the arrival of further supply. I should,
therefore, like as much as you can spare, particularly high explosive.
So far as this question affects sending a 4th and 5th Division I would
not refuse them on the score of ammunition alone, because with the
Artillery of three new divisions complete I think we shall have as many
guns as the terrain will allow us to use in the operations towards
Maidos, and also sufficient to compete with any Artillery which the
enemy could bring against the detachment operating on the Asiatic shore.</p>

<p>"To summarize--I think I have reasonable prospects of eventual success
with three divisions, with four the risks of miscalculation would be
minimized, and with five, even if the fifth division had little or no
gun ammunition, I think it would be a much simpler matter to clear the
Asiatic shore subsequently of big guns, etc., Kilid Bahr would be
captured at an earlier date and success would be generally assured."</p>

<p>Next, I boiled down yesterday's battle into telegraphic dispatch form:</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 383). From General Sir Ian Hamilton to Secretary of State for
War. In continuation of my Nos. M.F. 379 and 382. Plan of operations
yesterday was to throw forward left of my line south-east of Krithia,
pivoting on point about one mile from the sea, and after advancing
extreme left for about half a mile, to establish new line facing east on
ground thus gained. This plan entailed the capture in succession of two
lines of the Turkish trenches east of the Saghir Dere and five lines of
trenches west of it. Australian Corps was ordered to co-operate by
making vigorous demonstration. The action opened at 9 a.m. with
bombardment by heavy artillery of the trenches to be captured.</p>

<p>"Assistance rendered by French in this bombardment was most valuable. At
10.20 our field artillery opened fire to cut wire in front of Turkish
trenches and this was effectively done. Great effect on enemy's trench
near sea and in keeping down his artillery fire from that quarter was
produced by very accurate fire of H.M.S. _Talbot_, _Scorpion_, and
_Wolverine_. At 10.45 a small Turkish advanced work in the Saghir Dere,
known as the Boomerang Redoubt, was assaulted. This little fort was
very strongly sited, protected by extra strong wire entanglements and
has long been a source of trouble. After special bombardment by trench
mortars and while bombardment of surrounding trenches was at its height
part of Border Regiment, at the exact moment prescribed, leapt from
their trenches like a pack of hounds pouring out of cover, raced across
and took the work most brilliantly.</p>

<p>"Artillery bombardment increased in intensity till 11 a.m. when range
was lengthened and infantry advanced. Infantry attack was carried out
with great dash along whole line. West of Saghir Dere 87th Brigade
captured three lines of trenches with little opposition. Trenches full
of dead Turks, many buried by bombardment, and 100 prisoners were taken
in them. East of Ravine two battalions Royal Scots made fine attack,
capturing the two lines of trenches assigned as their objective, but
remainder of 156th Brigade on their right met severe opposition and were
unable to get forward. At 11.30, 86th Brigade led by 2nd Bn. Royal
Fusiliers started second phase of attack West of Ravine. They advanced
with great steadiness and resolution through trenches already captured
and on across the open, and taking two more lines of trenches reached
objective allotted to them, Lancashire Fusiliers inclining half right
and forming line to connect with our new position East of Ravine.</p>

<p>"The northernmost objective I had set out to reach had now been
attained, but the Gurkhas pressing on under the cliffs captured an
important knoll still further forward, actually due west of Krithia.
This they fortified and held during the night, making our total gain on
the left precisely 1,000 yards. During afternoon 88th Brigade attacked
trenches, small portion of which remained uncaptured on right, but enemy
held on stubbornly, supported by machine guns and artillery, and attacks
did not succeed. During night enemy counter-attacked furthest trenches
gained but was repulsed with heavy loss. Party of Turks who penetrated
from flank between two lines of captured trenches, subjected to
machine-gun fire at daybreak, suffered very heavily and survivors
surrendered.</p>

<p>"Except for small portion of trench already mentioned which is still
held by enemy, all, and more than we hoped for, from operations has been
gained. On extreme left, line has been pushed forward to specially
strong point well beyond limit of advance originally contemplated. Our
casualties about 2,000, the greater proportion of which are slight cases
of which 250 at Anzac, in the useful demonstration made simultaneously
there. All engaged did well, but certainly the chief factor in the
success was the splendid attack carried out by XXIXth Division, whose
conduct in this as on previous occasions was beyond praise."</p>

<p>Lastly, I wrote out a special Force Order thanking the incomparable
29th.</p>

<p>Winter brought me over a letter just received from Wallace. He is
quarrelling with Elliot. For that I don't blame him. At the end of his
letter Wallace says, "I feel that the organization of the Lines of
Communication and making it work is such a task that I sometimes doubt
myself whether I am equal to it." Wallace is a good fellow and a
sensible man placed, by British methods, out of his element and out of
his depth. Have told Winter to tell him I sympathize and will help him
and support him all I know; that if it turns out his strong points lie
in another direction than administering a huge business machine, I will
try and find a handsome way out for him.</p>

<p>Had been writing, writing, writing since cockcrow so when I heard a
trawler was going over with two of the General Staff at mid-day, I could
not resist the chance of another visit to the scene of yesterday's
victorious advance. Went to see Hunter-Weston but he was up at the front
where I had no time to follow him. His Chief of Staff says all goes
well, but they have just had cables from my own Headquarters to tell
them that heavy columns of Turks are massing behind Achi Baba for a
fresh counter-attack. Thought, therefore, the wisest thing was to get
back quickly. Reached camp again about 7 p.m., and found more news in
office than I got on the spot. Last night's firing on the Peninsula
meant close and desperate fighting. Several heavy columns of Turks
attacked with bomb and bayonet, and in places some of their braves broke
through into our new trenches where the defence had not yet been put on
a stable footing. When daylight came we got them enfiladed by machine
guns and every single mother's son of them was either killed or
captured. So we still hold every yard we had gained.</p>

<p>The attack by a part of the Lowland Division seems to have been
mishandled. A Brigade made the assault East of the Ravine; the men
advanced gallantly but there was lack of effective preparation. Two
battalions of the Royal Scots carried a couple of the enemy's trenches
in fine style and stuck to them, but the rest of the Brigade lost a
number of good men to no useful purpose in their push against H.12. One
thing is clear. If the bombardment was ineffective, from whatever cause,
then the men should not have been allowed to break cover.[23]</p>

<p>_30th June, 1915. Imbros._ Writing in camp.</p>

<p>More good news. It never rains but it pours. The French have made a fine
push and got the Quadrilateral by 8 a.m. with but little loss. The Turks
seemed discouraged, they say, and did not offer their usual firm
resistance.</p>

<p>At 10.30 a.m. wired Gouraud:--"Warm congratulations on this morning's
work which will compensate for the loss of your 2,000 quarts of wine.
Your Government should now replace it with vintage claret. Please send
me quickly a sketch of the ground you have gained."</p>

<p>Gouraud now replies:--"Best thanks for congratulations. Sketch being
made. If our Government is pleased to send a finer brand of wine to
replace what was wasted by the guns of Asia, we Frenchmen will drink it
to the very good health of our British comrades in arms."</p>

<p>How lucky I signalled de Robeck 8 p.m. yesterday to let us keep the
_Wolverine_ and _Scorpion_ "in case of a night attack!" Sure enough
there was another onslaught made against our northernmost post. Two
Turkish Regiments were discovered in mass creeping along the top of the
cliffs by the searchlights of the _Scorpion_. They were so punished by
her guns that they were completely broken up and the Infantry at
daylight had not much to do except pick up the fragments. 300 Turks lay
dead upon the ground. Also, hiding in furze, have gleaned 180 prisoners
belonging to the 13th, 16th and 33rd Regiments. A Circassian prisoner
carried in a wounded Royal Scot on his back under a heavy fire.</p>

<p>Three wires from Helles; the first early this morning; the last just to
hand (11 p.m.) saying that the lack of hand grenades is endangering all
our gains. The Turks are much better armed in this respect. De Lisle
says that where we have hand grenades we can advance still further;
where we have not, we lose ground. At mid-day, we wired our reply saying
we had no more hand grenades we feared but that we would do our best to
scrape up a few; also that several trench mortars had just arrived from
home and that they would be sent over forthwith.</p>

<p>Have returned some interesting minutes on the Dardanelles, sent me from
home, with this remark:--"Looking back I see now clearly that the one
fallacy which crept into your plans was non-recognition of the pride and
military _moral_ of the Turk. There was never any question of the Turk
being demoralized or even flustered by ships sailing past him or by
troops landing in his rear. _At last, I believe_, this _moral_ is
beginning to crack up a little (not much) but nothing less than
murderous losses would have done it. In their diaries their officers
speak of this Peninsula as the Slaughterhouse."</p>

<p>Brigadier-General de Lothbiniere and Major Ruthven lunched and young
Brodrick and I dined together on board the _Triad_ with the hospitable
Vice-Admiral. We were all very cheery at the happy turn of our fortunes;
outwardly, that is to say, for there was a skeleton at the feast who
kept tap, tap, tapping on the mahogany with his bony knuckles; tap, tap,
tap; the gunfire at Helles was insistent, warning us that the Turks had
not yet "taken their licking." But when I get back, although there is
nothing in from Hunter-Weston there is an officer from Anzac who has
just given me the complete story of Birdwood's demonstration on the
28th. The tide of war is indeed racing full flood in our favour.</p>

<p>When we were working out our scheme for the attack of the 29th Division
and 156th Brigade the day before yesterday, as well as Gouraud's attack
of yesterday, we had reckoned that the Turkish High Command would get to
realize by about 11 a.m. on the 28th that an uncommon stiff fight had
been set afoot to the sou'-west of Krithia. L. von S. would then, it
might be surmised, draw upon his reserves at Maidos and upon his forces
opposite Anzac: they would get their orders about mid-day: they would be
starting about 1 p.m.: they would reach Krithia about dusk: they would
use their "pull" in the matter of hand grenades to counter-attack by
moonlight. So we asked Birdie to make one of his most engaging gestures
just to delay these reinforcements a little bit; and now it turns out
that the Australians and New Zealanders in their handsome, antipodean
style went some 50 per cent. better than their bargain:--</p>

<p>(1) At 1 p.m. on the 28th the Queensland giants darted out of their
caves and went for the low ridge covering Gaba Tepe, that tenderest spot
of the Turks. They got on to the foot of it and, by their dashing
onslaught, drew the fire of all the enemy guns; but, what was still
better, heavy Turkish columns, on the march, evidently, from Maidos to
the help of Krithia, turned back northwards and closed in for the
defence of Gaba Tepe. As they drew near they came under fire of our
destroyers and of the Anzac guns and were badly knocked about and broken
up. So both Krithia and the French Quadrilateral have had to do without
the help of these reinforcements from the reserves of Liman von Sanders.
One of the neatest of strokes and the credit of it lies with the
Queenslanders who were not content to flourish their fists in the
enemy's face but ran out and attacked him at close quarters.</p>

<p>(2) Now comes the sequel! Birdie has just sent in word of the best
business done at Anzac since May 19th!! The success of his demonstration
towards Gaba Tepe had given the Turks a bad attack of the jumps,
followed by a thirst for vengeance. Yesterday, they got _very_ nervy
during a dust storm and for two hours the whole of their Army kept up
high pressure fire from every rifle and machine gun they could bring to
bear. They simply poured out bullets by the million into the blinding
dust. Things then gradually quieted down till 1.30 this morning when a
very serious assault--very serious for the enemy--was suddenly launched
against the Anzac left, the brunt of it falling on Russell's New Zealand
Mounted Rifles and Chauvel's Australian Light Horse; a bad choice too!
Our victory complete; bloodless for us. Their defeat complete; very
bloody. Nine fresh enemy battalions smashed to bits: fighting went on
until dawn: five hundred Turks laid out and counted: no more detail but
that is good enough to go to sleep upon.</p>

<p>_1st July, 1915. Imbros._ Good news from Helles continues. In the early
hours of last night an attack was made on the Gurkhas in J trenches.
When they ran out of bombs the Turks bombed them out. Headed by Bruce
their Colonel, whom they adore, they retook the trench and, for the
first time, got into the enemy with their _kukris_ and sliced off a
number of their heads. At dawn half a battalion of Turks tried to make
the attack along the top of the cliff and were entirely wiped out.</p>

<p>Against this I must set down cruel bad news about Gouraud. An accursed
misadventure. He has been severely wounded by a shell. Directly I heard
I got the Navy to run me over. He was already in the Hospital ship; I
saw him there. A pure toss up whether he pulls round or not; luckily he
has a frame of iron. I was allowed to speak to him for half a minute and
he is full of pluck. The shell, an 8-incher from Asia, landed only some
half a dozen yards away from him as he was visiting his wounded and sick
down by "V" Beach. By some miracle none of the metal fragments touched
him, but the sheer force of the explosion shot him up into the air and
over a wall said to be seven feet high. His thigh, ankle and arm are all
badly smashed, simply by the fall. We could more easily spare a Brigade.
His loss is irreparable. By personal magnetism he has raised the ardour
of his troops to the highest power. Have cabled to Lord K. expressing my
profound sorrow and assuring him that "the grave loss suffered by the
French, and indirectly by my whole force," is really most serious, as I
know, I say, "the French War Minister cannot send us another General
Gouraud."</p>

<p>_2nd July, 1915. Imbros._ Worked all day in camp. Birdie, with Onslow,
his A.D.C--_such_ a nice boy--came over from Anzac in the morning and
stayed with me the day, during which we worked together at our plan. At
night we all went over together to H.M.S. _Triad_ to dine with the
Vice-Admiral.</p>

<p>Birdwood is quite confident that with a fresh Division and a decent
supply of shell he can get hold of the heights of Sari Bair, whereby he
will enfilade the whole network of Turkish trenches, now hedging him
round. The only thing he bargains for is that G.H.Q. so work the whole
affair from orders down to movements, that the enemy get no inkling of
our intentions. The Turks so far suspect nothing, and Koja Chemen Tepe
and Chunuk Bair, with all the intervening ridge, are still unentrenched
and open to capture by a _coup-de-main_. Even if the naval objections to
Bulair could be overcome, Sari Bair remains the better move of the two.
With the high ridges of Sari Bair in our hands we could put a stop to
the Turkish sea transport from Chanak which we could neither see nor
touch from Bulair. The tugs with their strings of lighters could not run
by day, and as soon as we could get searchlights fixed up, they would
find it very awkward to show themselves in the Straits by night. As to
the enemy land communications, as soon as we can haul up our big guns we
should command, and be able to search, all the ground between the Aegean
and the Dardanelles. Now is the moment. Birdwood says that he and his
men have exactly the same feeling that we have down at Helles--the
feeling, namely, that now at last, we have got a right moral pull over
the Turks. All we want is enough material to turn that faith into a mile
or two of mountains.</p>

<p>Making full use of their advantage in hand grenades, the Turks again won
their trench back from the Gurkhas last night; a trench which was the
key to a whole system of earthworks. Bruce had been wounded and they had
no officers left to lead them, so de Lisle had to call once more on the
29th Division and the bold Inniskilling Fusiliers retook that trench at
a cost of all their officers save two.</p>

<p>There are some feats of arms best left to speak for themselves and this
is one of them.</p>

<p>Wrote Lord K. as follows:--</p>

<p>                                                "GENERAL HEADQUARTERS,
                                          "MEDTN. EXPEDITIONARY FORCE.</p>

<p>                                                     "_2nd July, 1915._</p>

<p>    "Dictated.</p>

<p>  "MY DEAR LORD KITCHENER,</p>

<p>"There seems to be a lull in this tooth-and-nail struggle which has kept
me on tenterhooks during the past four days and nights. But we have on
our maps little blue arrows showing the movements of at least a Division
of troops in various little columns from above Kereves Dere, from Soghon
Dere river, from Kilid Bahr and even from within gun-shot of Achi Baba,
all converging on a point a mile or two north-west of Krithia. So it
looks as if they were going to have one more desperate go at the Gurkha
knoll due west of Krithia, and at the line of trench we call J.13
immediately behind it which was also held by the Gurkhas.</p>

<p>"Last night they bombed the Gurkhas out of the eastern half of J.13 and
the Inniskilling Fusiliers had to take it again at the point of the
bayonet just as day broke.</p>

<p>"You can have small idea of what the troops are going through. The same
old battalions being called on again and again to do the forlorn hope
sort of business. However, each day that passes, these captured
positions get better dug in, and make the Turks' counter-attack more
costly.</p>

<p>"The cause of the attack made the night before last on Anzac has been
made quite clear to us by a highly intelligent Armenian prisoner we have
taken. The strictest orders had been issued by His Excellency
Commanding-in-Chief on the Peninsula that no further attacks against our
works were to be made unless, of course, we took any ground from them
when we must be vigorously countered. But it was explained to the men
that the losses in attack had proved too heavy, whereas, if they had
patience and waited a week or ten days in their trenches, then at last
we would come out and try to attack them when they would kill us in
great quantities. However, Enver Pasha appeared in person amongst the
troops at Anzac, and ordered three regiments to attack whilst the whole
of the rest of the line supported them by demonstrations and by fire. It
was objected this was against the command of their local chief. He
brushed this objection aside, and told them never to look him in the
face again if they failed to drive the Australians into the sea. So off
they went and they certainly did not drive the Australians into the sea
(although they got into their support trenches at one time) and
certainly most of them never looked Enver in the face again, or anyone
else for that matter.</p>

<p>"The old battle tactics have clean vanished. I have only quite lately
realized the new conditions. Whether your entrenchments are on the top
of a hill or at the bottom of a valley matters precious little: whether
you are outflanked matters precious little--you may hold one half of a
straight trench and the enemy may hold the other half, and this
situation may endure for weeks. The only thing is by cunning or
surprise, or skill, or tremendous expenditure of high explosives, or
great expenditure of good troops, to win some small tactical position
which the enemy may be bound, perhaps for military or perhaps for
political reasons, to attack. Then you can begin to kill them pretty
fast."</p>

<p>_3rd July, 1915. Imbros._ Very hot; very limp with the prevalent disease
but greatly cheered up by the news of yesterday evening's battle at
Helles. The Turks must have got hold of a lot of fresh shell for, at
5.30 p.m., they began as heavy a bombardment as any yet seen at Helles,
concentrating on our extreme left. We could only send a feeble reply. At
6 o'clock the enemy advanced in swarms, but before they had covered more
than 100 yards they were driven back again into the Ravine some 800
yards to our front. H.M.S. _Scorpion_ and our machine guns played the
chief hand. At 7 p.m. the Turkish guns began again, blazing away as if
shells were a drug in the market, whilst, under cover of this very
intense fire, another two of their battalions had the nerve to emerge
from the Ravine to the north-east of our forward trenches and to move in
regular lines--shoulder to shoulder--right across the open. Hardly had
they shown themselves when the 10th Battery R.F.A. sprayed them
beautifully with shrapnel. The Gurkha supports were rushed up, and as
there was no room for them in the fire trenches they crept into shell
craters and any sort of hole they could find from which to rake the
Turks as they made their advance. The enemy's officers greatly
distinguished themselves, waving their swords and running well out into
the open to get the men forward. The men also had screwed up their
courage to the sticking point and made a big push for it, but, in the
end, they could not face our fire, and fell back helter-skelter to their
mullah. Along the spot where they had stood wavering awhile before they
broke and ran, there are still two clearly marked lines of corpses.</p>

<p>Wrote a letter to Sclater saying I cannot understand his request for
fuller information about the drafts needed to make my units up to
strength. We have regularly cabled strengths; the figures are correct
and it is the A.G. himself who has ordered us to furnish the optimistic
"ration" strengths instead of the customary "fighting" strengths. The
ration strength are for the Q.M.G., but unless the A.G. wishes to go on
living in a fool's paradise, why should he be afraid of knowing the
numbers we cannot put into the line of battle!</p>

<p>Have also written Cowans protesting once more that we should have
business brains to run the most intricate business proposition at
present on tap in the world--our communications. During the past month
the confusion at Mudros, our advanced base, becomes daily worse
confounded. Things meant for Anzac go to Helles, and _vice versa_: or,
not infrequently, stores, supplies or luxuries arrive and are sent off
on a little tour to Alexandria and Malta before delivery. The system
would be perfect for the mellowing of port or madeira, but when it is
applied to plum and apple jam or, when 18 pr. shell are sent to
howitzers, the system needs overhauling. I know the job is out of the
way difficult. There is work here for Lesseps, Goethals and Morgan
rolled into one:--work that may change the face of the world far, far
more than the Suez or Panama Canals and, to do it, they have put in a
good fighting soldier, quite out of his setting, and merely because they
did not know what to do with him in Egypt! In case Cowans shares K.'s
suspicions about my sneaking desire for Ellison, I say, "I assure you;
most solemnly I assure you, that the personal equation does not, even in
the vaguest fashion, enter into my thoughts. Put the greatest enemy I
possess in the world, and the person I most dislike, into that post, and
I would thank God for his appointment, on my knees, provided he was a
competent business man."</p>

<p>Again:--</p>

<p>"I am in despair myself over it. Perhaps that is putting it rather
strong as I try never to despair, but seriously I worry just as much
over things behind me as I do over the enemy in front of me. What I want
is a really big man there, and I don't care one D. who he is. A man I
mean who, if he saw the real necessity, would wire for a great English
contractor and 300 navvies without bothering or referring the matter to
anyone."</p>

<p>A cable to say that the editing of my despatch is ended, and that the
public will be let into its dreadful secrets in a day or two. But, I am
informed there are passages in it whose "secret nature will be
scrupulously observed." What passages? I cannot remember any secrets in
my despatch.</p>

<p>Have been defending myself desperately against the War Office who want
to send out a Naval Doctor to take full charge and responsibility for
the wounded (including destination) the moment they quit dry land. But
we must have a complete scheme of evacuation _by land and sea_, not two
badly jointed schemes. So I have asked, who is to be "Boss"? Who is to
see to it that the two halves fit together? The answer is that the War
Office are confident "there will be no friction" (bless them!); they
say, "nothing could be simpler than this arrangement and no difficulty
is anticipated. Neither is boss and the boundary between the different
spheres of activity of the two officers might be laid down as the
high-water mark." (Bless them again!). Have replied:--</p>

<p>"I have struggled with your high-water mark silently for weeks and know
something about it. Had I bothered you with all my troubles you would, I
respectfully submit, realize that your proposal is not simple but
extraordinarily complicated, even pre-supposing seraphic dispositions on
either side. If you determine finally that these two officers are to be
independent, I foresee that you will greatly widen the scope of dual
control which is now only applicable to my great friend the Admiral and
myself.</p>

<p>"Either Babtie must order up the ships when and where he wants them, or
Porter must order the wounded down when he is ready for them. This is
my considered opinion."[24]</p>

<p>Have also sent an earnest message to K.--just the old, old story--saying
that what I want _first_ is drafts, and only _second_ fresh divisions.
My old Chief has been his kind self again:--so very considerate has he
been in his recent messages that I feel it almost brutal to press him or
to seem to wish to take advantage of his goodness. But we are dealing
with lives of men and I _must_ try and make myself clear:--</p>

<p>"I am anxious with regard to the question of reinforcements for units.
During the period 28th to 30th June, the Brigades of the XXIXth and
Lowland Divisions dropped in strengths approximately as follows:--86th
from 71 officers, 2,807 others to 36 and 1,994; 87th from 65 and 2,724
to 48 and 2,075; 88th from 63 and 2,139 to 46 and 1,765; 156th from 102
and 2,839 to 30 and 1,399. All Officers who have arrived from England to
date are included in the above figures. Maxwell has agreed to let me
have 80 young Officers from Egypt. Of the other ranks I have no
appreciable reinforcements to put in. This is the situation after an
operation carried out by the XXIXth and two brigades of LIInd Divisions,
which was not only successful but even more successful than we
anticipated; wherein the initial losses on 28th June were comparatively
small, namely 2,000, but as the result of numerous counter-attacks day
and night, have since swelled to some 3,500.</p>

<p>"The drafts promised in your No. 5793, A.G.2a, would, provided there
were no more casualties, bring the units of the XXIXth Division to
approximately 75 per cent. of establishment, but would leave none
available as further reinforcements.</p>

<p>"In view of the operations on a larger scale, with increased forces, I
feel I should draw your attention to the risk introduced by the theatre
of operations being so far from England. I have no reserves in base
depots now, while the operations we are engaged in are such that heavy
casualties are to be expected. The want of drafts ready on the spot to
fill up units which have suffered heavily might prevent me pressing to
full advantage as the result of a local success. At a critical moment I
might find myself compelled to suspend operations until the arrival of
drafts from England. This might involve a month and in the meantime the
enemy would have time to consolidate his position. The difficulty of the
drafts question is fully realized, but I think you should know exactly
how I am placed and that I should reflect and make clear the essential
difference between the Dardanelles and France in so far as the necessity
of mobilizing first reinforcements for each unit is concerned. Our real
need is a system which will enable me to maintain drafts for the
deficiencies in depots on my lines of communications with Egypt."</p>

<p>If K. did not want brief spurts sandwiched between long waits, all he
had to do was to tell his A.G. to see to it that the XXIXth Division was
kept up to strength. A word and a frown would have done it. But he has
not said the word, or scowled, and the troops have by extraordinary
efforts and self-sacrifice carried through the work of strong battalions
with weak ones--but only to some extent. That is the whole story.</p>

<p>_4th July, 1915. Imbros._ Church Parade this morning. Made a close
inspection of the Surrey Yeomanry under Major Bonsor. Even with as free
a hand as the Lord Almighty, it would be hard to invent a better type of
fighting man than the British Yeomanry; only, they have never been
properly appreciated by the martinets who have ruled our roost, and
chances have never been given to them to make the most of themselves as
soldiers.</p>

<p>The Escort was made up of men of the 29th Division under Lieutenant
Burrell of the South Wales Borderers--that famous battalion which
stormed so brilliantly de Tott's battery at the first landing,--also of
a detachment of Australians under Lieutenant Edwards and a squad of New
Zealanders under Lieutenant Sheppard, fine men all of them, but very
different (despite the superficial resemblance imparted by their slouch
hats) when thus seen shoulder to shoulder on parade. The Australians
have the pull in height and width of chest; the New Zealanders are
thicker all through, chests, waists, thighs.</p>

<p>After Church Parade, boarded H.M.S. _Basilisk_ (Lieutenant Fallowfield)
and steamed to Helles. The Turks, inconsiderate as usual, were shelling
Lancashire Landing as we got ashore. Every living soul had gone to
ground. Strolled up the deserted road with an air of careless
indifference, hopped casually over a huge splosh of fresh blood, and
crossed to Hunter-Weston's Headquarters. Had I only been my simple self,
I would have out-stripped the hare for swiftness, as it was, I, as
C.-in-C, had to play up to the dugouts. As Hunter-Weston and I were
starting lunch, an orderly rushed in to say that a ship in harbour had
been torpedoed. So we rushed out with our glasses and watched. She was a
French transport, the _Carthage_, and she took exactly four minutes to
sink. The destroyers and picket boats were round her as smart as flies
settle on a lump of sugar, and there was no loss of life. Sad to see the
old ship go down. I knew her well at Malta and Jean once came across in
her from Tunis. She used to roll like the devil and was always said,
with what justice I do not know, to be the sister ship to the _Waratah_
which foundered so mysteriously somewhere off the Natal coast with a
very good chap, a M.F.H., Percy Brown, on board. At 2.30 General
Bailloud, now commanding the French, came over to see me. When he had
finished his business which he handles in so original a manner as to
make it a recreation, I went off with Hunter-Weston and Staffs to see
General Egerton of the Lowland Division. Egerton introduced me to
Colonel Mudge, A.A.G., Major Maclean, D.A.A.G. (an old friend), Captain
Tollemashe, G.S.O.3, and to his A.D.C., Lieutenant Laverton. We then
went on and saw the 156th Brigade. Passed the time of day to a lot of
the Officers and men. Among those whose names I remember were Colonel
Pallin, acting Brigadier; Captain Girdwood, Brigade Major; Captain Law,
Staff Captain; Colonel Peebles, 7th Royal Scots; Captain Sinclair, 4th
Royal Scots; Lieutenant McClay, 8th Scottish Rifles. The last Officer
was one of the very few--I am not sure they did not say the only one--of
his Battalion who went into the assault and returned untouched.</p>

<p>The whole Brigade had attacked H. 12 on the 28th ult. and lost a number
of good men. The rank and file seemed very nice lads but--there was no
mistaking it--they have been given a bad shake and many of them were
down on their luck. As we came to each Battalion Headquarters we were
told, "These are the remnants of the----," whatever the unit was. Three
times was this remark repeated but the fourth time I had to express my
firm opinion that in no case was the use of the word "remnant," as
applied to a fighting unit "in being," an expression which authority
should employ in the presence of the men.</p>

<p>Re-embarked in H.M.S. _Basilisk_ and got back to Imbros fairly late.</p>

<p>A set of Turkish Divisional orders sent by the Turkish General to the
Commander of their right zone at Helles has been taken from a wounded
Turkish officer. They bear out our views of the blow that the 29th
Division have struck at the enemy's _moral_ by their brilliant attack on
the 28th inst.</p>

<p>"There is nothing that causes us more sorrow, increases the courage of
the enemy and encourages him to attack more freely, causing us great
losses, than the losing of these trenches. Henceforth, commanders who
surrender these trenches from whatever side the attack may come before
the last man is killed will be punished in the same way as if they had
run away. Especially will the commanders of units told off to guard a
certain front be punished if, instead of thinking about their work
supporting their units and giving information to the higher command,
they only take action after a regrettable incident has taken place.</p>

<p>"I hope that this will not occur again. I give notice that if it does, I
shall carry out the punishment. I do not desire to see a blot made on
the courage of our men by those who escape from the trenches to avoid
the rifle and machine gun fire of the enemy. Henceforth, I shall hold
responsible all Officers who do not shoot with their revolvers all the
privates who try to escape from the trenches on any pretext. Commander
of the 11th Division, Colonel Rifaat."</p>

<p>In sending on this order to his battalions, the Colonel of the 127th
Regiment adds:--</p>

<p>"To Commander of the 1st Battalion. The contents will be communicated to
the Officers and I promise to carry out the orders till the last drop of
our blood has been shed."</p>

<p>Then followed the signatures of the company commanders of the Battalion.
There is a savage ring about these orders but they are, I am sure, more
bracing to the recipients than laments and condolences over their
losses.</p>

<p>_5th July, 1915. Imbros._ Spent a long, hot day hanging at the end of
the wire. Heavy firing on the Peninsula last night under cover of which
the Turks at dawn made, or tried to make, a grand, concerted attack. Not
a soul in England, outside the Ordnance, realizes, I believe, that
barring the guns of the 29th Division and the few guns of the Anzacs,
our field artillery consists of the old 15-prs., relics of South Africa,
and of 5-inch hows., some of them Omdurman veterans. Quite a number of
these guns are already unserviceable and, in the 42nd Division, to keep
one and a half batteries fully gunned, we have had to use up every piece
in the Brigade. The surplus personnel are thus wasted. To take on new
Skoda or Krupp guns with these short-range veterans is rough on the
gunners. Still, but for the Territorial Force we should have nothing at
all, and but for those guns to-day some of the enemy might have got
home.</p>

<p>A sort of professional gossip turned up to-day from G.H.Q. France. We do
not seem to be so popular as we deserve to be in _la belle France!_ But
what I would plead were I only able to get at Joffre and French is that
we are "such a little one." Were we all to be set down in the West
to-morrow with our shattered, torn formations, they'd put us back into
reserve for a month's rest and training. As for the guns, they'd scrap
the lot. _They_ don't want ancient 15-prs. and 5-inch hows. out there.
They picture us feasting upon their munitions, but half of what we use
they would not touch with a barge pole and, of the good stuff, one
Division in France will fire away in one day what would serve to take
the Peninsula.</p>

<p>Braithwaite has a letter from the D.M.I. telling him that 5,000 Russians
sailed from Vladivostock on the 1st inst. to join us here. One Regiment
of four Battalions plus one Sotnia of Cossacks. A reinforcement of 5,000
stout soldiers tumbling out of the skies! Russians placed here are worth
twice their number elsewhere, not only because we need rifles so badly,
but because of the moral effect their presence should have in the
Balkans.</p>

<p>This little vodka pick-me-up has come in the nick of time to hearten me
against the tenor of the news of to-day which is splendid indeed in one
sense; ominous in another. The Turks are being heavily reinforced. All
the enemy troops who made the big attack last night were fresh arrivals
from Adrianople. I do not grumble at the attack (on the contrary we like
it), but at the reason they had for making it, which is that two fresh
Divisions, newly arrived, asked leave to show their muscle by driving us
into the sea. Full details are only just in. The biggest bombardment
took place at Anzac. A Turkish battleship joined in from the Hellespont,
dropping about twenty 11.2-inch shells into our lines. At Helles, all
night, the Turks blazed away from their trenches. At 4 a.m. they opened
fire on our trenches and beaches with every gun they could bring to
bear from Asia or Achi Baba. Their Asiatic Batteries alone fired 1,900
rounds, of which 700 fell on Lancashire Landing. At least 5,000 shell
were loosed off on to Helles. A lot of the stuff was 6-inch and over.
The bombardment was very wild and seemed almost unaimed. Soon after 4
a.m. very heavy columns of Turks tried to emerge from the Ravine against
the left of the 29th Division. "It wanted to be the hell of a great
attack," as one of the witnesses, a moderate spoken young gentleman,
states. When the Commanders saw what was impending they sent messages to
Simpson-Baikie begging him to send some 4.5 H.E. shell into the Ravine
which was beginning to overflow. He was adamant. He had only a few
rounds of H.E. and he would not spend them, feeling sure his 18 prs.
with their shrapnel were masters of the field. At 6 a.m. out came the
Turks, not in lines, but just like a swarm of bees. Our fellows never
saw the like and began to wonder whenever they were going to stop, and
what on earth _could_ stop them! Thousands of Turks in a bunch, so the
boys say, swarmed out of their trenches and the Gully Ravine. Well, they
were stopped _dead_. There they lie, _still_. The guns ate the life out
of them.</p>

<p>It was our central group of artillery who did it. As that big oblong
crowd of Turks showed their left flank to Baikie's nine batteries they
were swept in enfilade by shrapnel. The fall of the shell was corrected
by the two young R.A. subalterns at the front, neither of whom would
observe in the usual way through his periscope. They looked over the
parapet because that method was more sure and quick, and the stress of
the battle was great. There is a rumour that both were shot through the
head: I pray it may be but a rumour. Out of all these Turks some thirty
only reached our parapets. The sudden destruction which befell them was
due in the main to the devotion of these two young heroes. At 7.30 a.m.
the Turks tried to storm again. Some of them got in amongst the Royal
Naval Division, who brought up their own supports and killed 300,
driving out the rest. Ninety dead Turks are laid out on their parapet.
Another, later, enemy effort against the right of the 29th Division was
clean wiped out. 150 Turks are dead there. But it is on the far
crestline they lie thick.</p>

<p>Every one of these attacking Turks were _fresh_--from Adrianople! Full
of fight as compared with their thrice beaten brethren. If the Turks are
given time to swap troops in the middle of fighting, we can't really
tell how we stand. Still; they are not now as fresh as they were. They
have lost a terrible lot of men since the 28th. The big Ravine and all
the small nullahs are chock-a-block with corpses. Their casualties in
these past few days are put at very high figures by both Birdie and H.W.
and it is probable that 5,000 are actually lying dead on the ground. I
have on my table a statement made by de Lisle; endorsed by Hunter-Weston
and dated 4th instant, saying that 1,200 Turkish dead can be counted
corpse by corpse from the left front. The actual numbers de Lisle
estimates as between 2,000 and 3,000. Now we have to-day's losses to
throw in. The Turks are burning their candle fast at the Anzac as well
as the Helles end. Ten days of this and they are finished.[25]</p>

<p>Naturally, my mind dwells happily just now upon our incoming New Army
formations. Yet every now and then I feel compelled to look back to
regret the lack of systematic flow of drafts and munitions which have
turned our fine victory of the 28th into a pyrrhic instead of a fruitful
affair. When Pyrrhus gained his battle over the Romans and exclaimed,
"One more such victory and I am done in," or words to that effect, he
had no organized system of depots behind him from which the bloody gaps
in his ranks could be filled. A couple of thousand years have now passed
and we are still as unscientific as Pyrrhus. A splendid expeditionary
force sails away; invades an Empire, storms the outworks and in doing so
knocks itself to bits. Then a second expeditionary force is sent, but
that would have been unnecessary had any sort of arrangement been
thought out for promptly replacing first wastages in men and in shell.</p>

<p>_6th July, 1915._ From early morning till 5 p.m. stuck as persistently
to my desk as the flies stuck persistently to me. After tea went riding
with Maitland. Then with Pollen to dine on board H.M.S. _Triad_. The two
Territorial Divisions are coming. What with them and the Rooskies we
ought to get a move on this time. Discoursed small craft with the
Admiral. The French hate the overseas fire--small blame to them--and
Bailloud agrees with his predecessor Gouraud in thinking that one man
hit in the back from Asia affects the _moral_ of his comrades as badly
as half a dozen bowled over by the enemy facing them. The Admiral's idea
of landing from Tenedos would help us here, but it is admitted on all
hands now that the Turks have pushed on with their Asiatic defences, and
it is too much to ask of either the New Army or of the Territorials that
they should start off with a terrible landing.</p>

<p>_7th July, 1915._ No escape from the steadily rising flood of letters
and files,--none from the swarms of filthy flies. General Bailloud and
Colonel Piepape (Chief of Staff) came across with Major Bertier in a
French torpedo boat to see me. They stayed about an hour. Bailloud's
main object was to get me to put off the attack planned by General
Gouraud for to-morrow. Gouraud has worked out everything, and I greatly
hoped in the then state of the Turks the French would have done a very
good advance on our right. The arrival of these fresh Turkish Divisions
from Adrianople does make a difference. Still, I am sorry the attack is
not to come off. Girodon is a heavy loss to Bailloud. Piepape has never
been a General Staff Officer before; by training, bent of mind and
experience he is an administrator. He is very much depressed by the loss
of the 2,000 quarts of wine by the Asiatic shell. Since Gouraud and
Girodon have left them the French seem to be less confident. When
Bailloud entered our Mess he said, in the presence of four or five young
Officers, "If the Asiatic side of the Straits is not held by us within
fifteen days our whole force is _voue a la destruction_." He meant it as
a jest, but when those who prophesy destruction are _gros bonnets_; big
wigs; it needs no miracle to make them come off--I don't mean the wigs
but the prophecies. Fortunately, Bailloud soon made a cheerier class of
joke and wound up by inviting me to dine with him in an extra chic
restaurant at Constantinople.</p>

<p>Have told K. plainly that the employment of an ordinary executive
soldier as Boss of so gigantic a business as Mudros is suicidal--no
less. Heaven knows K. himself had his work cut out when he ran the
communications during his advance upon Khartoum. Heaven knows I myself
had a hard enough job when I became responsible for feeding our troops
at Chitral, two hundred miles into the heart of the Himalayas from the
base at Nowshera. Breaking bulk at every stage--it was heart-breaking.
First the railway, then the bullock cart, the camel, the mules--till, at
the Larram Pass we got down to the donkey. But here we have to break
bulk from big ships to small craft; to send our stuff not to one but to
several landings, to run the show with a mixed staff of Naval and
Military Officers. No, give me deserts or precipices,--anything fixed
and solid is better than this capricious, ever-changing sea. The problem
is a real puzzler, demanding experience, energy, good temper as well as
the power of entering into the point of view of sailors as well as
soldiers, and of being (mentally) in at least three places at once:--</p>

<p>"_From General Sir Ian Hamilton to Earl Kitchener. (No. M.F. 424)._</p>

<p>"Private. I am becoming seriously apprehensive about my Lines of
Communication and am forced to let you know the state of affairs.</p>

<p>"Much of the time of General Headquarters has been taken up during the
last few days considering matters relating to Mudros and Lines of
Communication generally. The Inspector-General of Communications must be
a man of energy and ideas. The new Divisions will find the Mudros
littoral on arrival better prepared for their reception than it was a
month ago. The present man is probably excellent in his own line, but he
himself in writing doubts his own ability to cope with one of the most
complicated situations imaginable. Please do not think for a moment that
I am still hankering after Ellison, I only want a man of that type,
someone, for instance, like Maxwell or Sir Edward Ward. Unless I can
feel confident in the Commandant of my Lines of Communication I shall
always be looking behind me. Wallace could remain as Deputy
Inspector-General of Communications. Something, however, must be done
meanwhile, and I am sending Brigadier-General Hon. H.A. Lawrence, a man
of tried business capacity and great character, to Mudros to-day as
dry-nurse."</p>

<p>I have followed up this cable in my letter to Lord K. of date, where I
say, "I have just seen Bertie Lawrence who I am sending to reinforce
Wallace. He is bitterly disappointed at losing his Brigade, but there is
no help for it. He is a business man of great competence, and I think he
ought to be able to do much to get things on to a ship-shape footing.
General Douglas is very sorry too and says that Lawrence was one of the
best Brigadiers imaginable."</p>

<p>The last sentence has been written, I confess, with a spice of malice.
When, about a month ago, I had hurriedly to lay my hands on a Commander
for the 127th Brigade, I bethought me of Bertie Lawrence, then G.S.O. to
the Yeomanry in Egypt. The thrust of a Lancer and the circumspection of
a Banker do not usually harbour in the same skull, but I believed I knew
of one exception. So I put Lawrence in. By return King's Messenger came
a rap over the knuckles. To promote a dugout to be a Brigadier of
Infantry was risky, but to put in a Cavalry dugout as a Brigadier of
Infantry was outrageous! Still, I stuck to Lorenzo, and lo and behold!
Douglas, the Commander of the East Lancs. Division, is fighting tooth
and nail for his paragon Brigadier![26]</p>

<p>Since 19th March we have been asking for bombs--any kind of bombs--and
we have not even got answers. Now they offer us some speciality bombs
for which France, they say, has no use.</p>

<p>I have replied:--</p>

<p>"I shall be most grateful for as many bombs of this and any other kind
as you can spare. Anything made of iron and containing high explosive
and detonator will be welcome. I should be greatly relieved if a large
supply could be sent overland via Marseilles, as the bomb question is
growing increasingly urgent. The Turks have an unlimited supply of
bombs, and our deficiencies place our troops at a disadvantage both
physically and morally and increase our difficulties in holding captured
trenches.</p>

<p>"Could you arrange for a weekly consignment of 10,000 to be sent to us
regularly?"</p>

<p>De Lisle came over to dine and stay the night.</p>

<p>_8th July, 1915. H.M.S. "Triad." Tenedos._ Started off in H.M.S. _Triad_
with Freddie Maitland, Aspinall and our host, the Admiral.</p>

<p>Had a lovely sail to Tenedos where Colonel Nuillion (acting Governor)
and Commander Samson, now Commandant of the Flying Camp, came on board.
After lunch, rowed ashore. There was some surf on and I jumped short,
landing (if such an expression may pass) in the sea. Wet feet rather
refreshing than otherwise on so hot a day. Tenedos is lovely. Each of
these islands has its own type of coasts, vegetation and colouring: like
rubies and diamonds they are connected yet hardly akin. Climbed Tenedos
Hill, our ascent ending in a desperate race for the crest. My long legs
and light body enabled me to win despite the weight of age. Very hot,
though, and the weight of age has got even less now.</p>

<p>From the top we had an hour's close prospecting of the opposite coasts,
where the Turks have done too much digging to make landing anything but
a very bloody business. Half a mile to the South looks healthier, but
they are sure to have a lot of machine guns there now. The landing would
be worse than on the 25th April. Anyway, _I am not going to do it_.</p>

<p>On the ground we now have a fair showing of aeroplanes, but mostly of
the wingless sort. At this precise moment only two are really fit. K.
has stuck to his word and is not going to help us here, and I can't
grumble as certainly I was forewarned. Had he only followed Neville
Usborne's L10,000,000 suggestion, we might now be bombing the Turks'
landing places and store depots, as well as spotting every day for our
gunners. But these naval airmen, bold fellows, always on for an
adventurous attack, are hardly in their element when carrying out the
technical gunnery part of our work.</p>

<p>Re-embarked, and during our sail back saw a trawler firing at a
submarine, whilst other trawlers and picket boats were skurrying up from
all points of the compass. Nets were run out in a jiffy, but I fear the
big fish had already given them the slip. Cast anchor about 7 o'clock.</p>

<p>Colonel Dick and Mr. Graives dined.</p>

<p>_9th July, 1915._ Spent the morning writing for the King's Messenger. My
letter to K. (an answer to that of Fitz to me) tells him:--</p>

<p>(1) That we have passed through the most promising week since the first
landing. The thousand yards' advance on the left and the rows of dead
Turks left by the receding tide of their counter-attack are solid
evidences to the results of the 28th ult., and of the six very heavy
Turkish assaults which have since broken themselves to pieces against
us.</p>

<p>(2) That Gouraud's loss almost wipes out our gains. Bailloud does not
attack till next week when he hopes to have more men and more
ammunition, but will this help us so much if the Turks also have more
men and more ammunition?</p>

<p>(3) That the Asiatic guns are giving us worry, but that I hope to knock
them out with our own heavy guns (the French 9.4s and our own 9.2s) just
being mounted. When the new Monitors come they ought to help us here.</p>

<p>(4) That "_power of digestion, sleeping and nerve power are what are
essential above all things to anyone who would command successfully at
the Dardanelles. Compared with these qualifications most others are
secondary._"</p>

<p>(5) That the British and Australians are marvels of endurance, but that
I am having to pull the Indian Brigade right out and send them to
Imbros. Their Commander, fine soldier though he be, is too old for the
post of Brigadier; he ought to be commanding a Division; and the men are
morally and physically tired and have lost three-fourths of their
officers: with rest they will all of them come round.</p>

<p>(6) That Baldwin's Brigade of the 13th Division have been landed on the
Peninsula and are now mixed up by platoons with the 29th Division where
they are tumbling to their new conditions quite quickly. They have
already created a very good impression at Helles.</p>

<p>Godley and his New Zealander A.D.C. (Lieutenant Rhodes), both old
friends, came over from H.M.S. _Triad_ to lunch. Hunter-Weston crossed
from Helles to dine and stay the night.</p>

<p>_10th July, 1915. Imbros._ These Imbros flies actually drink my fountain
pen dry! Hunter-Weston left for Helles in the evening.</p>

<p>Yesterday a cable saying there were no men left in England to fill
either the 42nd Division or the 52nd. We have already heard that the
Naval Division must fade away. Poor old Territorials! The War Office are
behaving like an architect who tries to mend shaky foundations by
clapping on another storey to the top of the building. Once upon a time
President Lincoln and the Federal States let their matured units starve
and thought to balance the account by the dispatch of untried
formations. Why go on making these assurances to the B.P. that we have
as many men coming in voluntarily as we can use?</p>

<p>Have refused the request made by His Excellency, Weber Pasha, who signs
himself Commandant of the Ottoman Forces, to have a five hours' truce
for burying their piles of dead. The British Officers who have been out
to meet the Turkish parlementaires say that the sight of the Turkish
dead lying in thousands just over the crestline where Baikie's guns
caught them on the 5th inst. is indeed an astonishing sight. Our
Intelligence are clear that the reason the Turks make this request is
that they cannot get their men to charge over the corpses of their
comrades. Dead Turks are better than barbed wire and so, though on
grounds of humanity as well as health, I should like the poor chaps to
be decently buried, I find myself forced to say no.</p>

<p>Patrick Shaw Stewart came to see me. I made Peter take his photo. He was
on a rat of a pony and sported a long red beard. How his lady friends
would laugh!</p>

