<?xml-model href="gallipoliSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
  <chapter n="13">CHAPTER XIII</chapter>

<title>K.'S ADVICE AND THE P.M.'S ENVOY</title>

<entry><p>_11th July, 1915._ Worked in my office from early morning till 12.45.
The whole scheme for to-morrow's attack is cut and dried, according to
our cloth: time tables fixed and every round counted.</p>

  <p><person name="Frederick_Stopford">Freddy Stopford</person> and his Staff turned up from <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location>. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> in very
good form. The first thing he did was to deliver himself of a personal
message from <person name="Lord_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> He (<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>) wrote it down, in the ante-room, the
moment he left the presence and I may take it as being as good as
verbatim. Here it is:--</p>

<p>     "<person name="Lord_Kitchener">Lord Kitchener</person> told me to tell you he had no wish to interfere
     with the man on the spot, but from closely watching our actions
     here, as well as those of <person name="General_French">General French</person> in <location region="Flanders">Flanders</location>, he is certain
     that the only way to make a real success of an attack is by
     surprise. Also, that when the surprise ceases to be operative, in
     so far that the advance is checked and the enemy begin to collect
     from all sides to oppose the attackers, then, perseverance becomes
     merely a useless waste of life. In every attack there seems to be a
     moment when success is in the assailant's grasp. Both the French
     and ourselves at <location town="Arras">Arras</location> and <location town="Neuve_Chapelle">Neuve Chapelle</location> lost the opportunity."</p>

<p>Well said! <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> has made <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> bring me in his pocket the very text for
what I wanted to say to him. Only my grumbling thoughts find expression
by my pen but I have plenty of others and my heart has its warm corner
for <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> whenever he cares to come in.</p>

<p>As I told <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>, <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> has not only anticipated my advice but has dived
right down into this muddle of twentieth century war and finds lying at
the bottom of it only the old original idea of war in the year 1. At our
first landing the way was open to us for just so long as the _surprise_
to the Turks lasted. That period here, at the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>, might be
taken as being perhaps twice as long as it would be on the Western front
which gave us a great pull. The reason was that land communications were
bad and our troops on the sea could move thrice as fast as the Turks on
their one or two bad roads. Yet, even so, there was no margin for
dawdling. <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> and <person name="Albert_d'Amade">d'Amade</person> had tried their best to use their
brief _surprise_ breathing space in seizing the Key to the opening of
the Narrows--<location heights="Achi_Baba">Achi Baba</location>, and had failed through lack of small craft, lack
of water, lack of means of bringing up supplies, lack of our 10 per
cent. reserves to fill casualties. At that crucial moment when we had
beaten the local enemy troops and the enemy reinforcements had not yet
come up, we could not get the men or the stuff quick enough to shore.
Still, we had gained three or four miles and there were spots on the
Peninsula where, to-day, three or four miles would be enough. Also,
supposing he had to run a landing, his (<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>'s) action would take
place under much easier conditions than <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person>'s on April 25th.</p>

<p>First and foremost, in our "beetles" or barges, conveying 500 men under
their own engines, we had an instrument which reduced the physical
effort three quarters. This meant half the battle. When we made our
original landing at Anzac we could only put 1,500 men ashore, per trip,
at a speed of 2-1/2 miles per hour, in open cutters. Were a Commander to
repeat that landing now, he would be able to run 5,000 men ashore, per
trip, at a speed of five miles per hour with no trouble about oars,
tows, etc., and with protection against shrapnel and rifle bullets. As
to the actual landing on the beach, that could be done--we had proved
it--in less than one quarter of the time. Each beetle had a "brow" fixed
on to her bows; a thing to be let down like a drawbridge over which the
men could pour ashore by fours; the same with mules, guns, supplies,
they could all be rushed on land as fast as they could be handled on the
beaches. Secondly, we had already been for some time at work to fix up
the wherewithal to meet our chronic nightmare, the water trouble.
Thirdly, the system of bringing up food and ammunition from the beaches
to the firing line had now been practically worked out into a science at
<location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> and Anzac where <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> would be given a chance of studying it
at first hand.</p>

<p>As to place, date, command, and distribution of forces, these were still
being considered; still undetermined; and I could say no more at
present. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> was away at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> but, if he would go over to the
General Staff, he would find <person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person>, my G.S. (1), and the Q. Staff who
would give him the hang of our methods and post him in matters which
would be applicable to any date or place.</p>

<p>There was more in this message as taken down by <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>. After going
into some details of trench warfare, <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s message went on:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"It is not the wish of the Cabinet that <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian Hamilton</person> should make
partial attacks. They (the Cabinet) consider it preferable that he
should await the arrival of his reinforcements to make one great effort,
which, if successful, will give them the ridge commanding the Narrows.
It is not intended, however, that Sir Ian should do nothing in the
meantime and if he gets a really good opportunity he is to seize it."</p>

<p>There is something in this reminds me of Kuropatkin's orders to
Stakelberg, yet I am glad to find that our spontaneously generated
scheme jumps with the views of the Cabinet, for, there is only one
"ridge commanding the Narrows" (Kilid Bahr is a plateau), and it is that
ridge we mean to try for by "one great effort."</p>

<p>In my reply I shall merely acknowledge. Sari Bair is my secret; my Open
Sesame to the cave where the forty thieves of the Committee of Union
and Progress have their Headquarters. It makes me uneasy to think the
Cabinet are talking about Sari Bair.</p>

<p>A battle is a swirl of "ifs" and "ands." The Commander who enters upon
it possessed by some just and clear principle is like a sailing ship
entering a typhoon on the right tack. After that he lives from hand to
mouth. How far will wise saws cut ice? How much nearer do you get to
shooting a snipe by being _told_ how not to take your aim? Well thought
out plans and preparations deserve to win; order and punctuality on the
part of subordinates tend to make the reality correspond to the General
Staff conception; surprise, if the Commander can bring it off, is worth
all <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> can say of it; the energy and rapidity of the chosen troops will
exploit that surprise for its full value--bar, always, Luck--the Joker;
and Wish to Fight and Will to Win are the surest victory getters in the
pack. The more these factors are examined, the more sure it is that
everything must in the last resort depend upon the _executive_
Commander; and here, of course, I am referring to an _enterprise_, not
to a huge, mechanically organized dead-lock like the western front.</p>

<p><person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> was away in G.H.Q. Staff tents all afternoon; afterwards both
he and Adderley, his A.D.C., dined. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> likes Reed who is, indeed,
a very pleasant fellow to work with. Still, I stick to what I wrote
Wolfe <person name="Wolfe_Murray">Murray</person>:--the _combination_ of <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and Reed is not good; not
for this sort of job.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_12th July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Had meant to start for <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> an hour before
daylight to witness the opening of the attack by the French Corps and
the Lowland Division. But am too bad with the universal complaint to
venture many yards from camp.</p>

<p><person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and Staff breakfasted. He has fallen in love with our ideas.
After lunch he and his party left for <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location>. Am forcing myself to write
so as to ease the strain of waiting: the battle is going on: backwards
and forwards--backwards and forwards--I travel between my tent; the
signal station, and the G.S. map tent.</p>

<p>A delightful message from <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>, thanking me for my letters: patting me on
the back; telling me that <person name="General_Altham">Altham</person> is coming out to run the
communications, and <person name="General_Ellison">Ellison</person> to serve on my Staff.</p>

<p>Thank heavens we are at last to have a business man at the head of our
business! As to <person name="General_Ellison">Ellison</person>, <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s conscience has for long been smiting him
for not having let me take my own C.G.S. with me in the first instance.
But <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> has won his spurs now in many a hair-raising crisis, so
<person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> may let his mind rest at ease.</p>

<p>Freddie <person name="Freddie_Maitland">Maitland</person> and I dined with the Vice-Admiral who kept a signaller
on special watch for my messages from the shore--but nothing came in.
He, the Admiral, wants to take all the 600 stokers serving in the Royal
Naval Division back to the ships. This will be the last straw to the
Division. We had the treat of being taken off the _Triad_ in the
Admiral's racing motor boat and when we got ashore found good news which
I have just cabled home:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"In the southern section we attacked at daylight to-day with our right
and right centre. After heavy fighting lasting all day the troops
engaged, namely, the French Corps and the LIInd Lowland Division, have
succeeded in carrying the two strongly held and fortified lines of
Turkish trenches opposite to them. The ground covered by the advance
varies in depth from 200 to 400 yards, and if we can maintain our gains
against to-night's counter-attacks the effect of the action will be not
only to advance but greatly to strengthen our line. Full details
to-morrow."</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_13th July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Still feeling very slack. Nothing clear from
<location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>. My cable best explains:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"Troops have been continuously engaged since my last cable, but
situation is still too confused to admit of definition, especially as
telephone wires all cut by shell or rifle fire.</p>

<p>"So far as can be gathered the sum total of the engagements taking place
in a labyrinth of trenches is satisfactory up to the hour of cabling and
we have taken some 200 prisoners. I hope I shall be able to send
definite news to-morrow morning."</p>

<p>Oh, energy, to what distant clime have you flown? I used to be
energetic; not perhaps according to Evelyn Wood's standards--but
still--energetic! Yet, see me to-day, when a poor cousin to the
cholera--this cursed enteritis--lays me by the heels; fills me with
desperate longing to lie down and do nothing but rest. More than half my
Staff and troops are in the same state of indescribable slackness and
this, I think, must be the reason the Greeks were ten long years taking
Troy.</p>

<p>Some newspaper correspondents have arrived. I have told them they may do
whatever they d--d well please. <person name="Ellis_Ashmead-Bartlett">Ashmead-Bartlett</person> is vexed at his
monopoly being spoiled. Charlie Burn, who came with the King's bag,
lunched. The Vice-Admiral, Roger <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>, and Flag-Lieutenant Bowlby
dined; very good of them to leave their own perfectly appointed table
for our rough and ready fare. The A.D.C.s between them managed to get
some partridges, opulent birds which lent quite a Ritzian tone to our
banquet.</p>

<p>As was expected, the Turks counter-attacked heavily last night but were
unable to drive us out except in one small section on our right. To-day,
fighting is still going on and the Naval Division are in it now. We have
made a good gain and taken over 400 prisoners and a machine gun. We are
still on the rack, though, as there are a lot of Turks not yet cleared
out from holes and corners of our new holding, and ammunition is running
very short. If our ammunition does not run out altogether and we can
hold what we have, our total gain will be 500 yards depth.</p>

<p>Since June 4th, when we had to whang off the whole of our priceless 600
rounds of H.E., we have had _none_ for 18-prs. on the Peninsula--not one
solitary demnition round; nor do we seem in the least likely to get one
solitary demnition round. <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> and his C.R.A. explain forcibly,
not to say explosively, that on the 28th June the right attack would
have scored a success equally brilliant to that achieved by the <unit type="division">29th</unit>
Division on our left, had we been able to allot as many shell to the
Turkish trenches assaulted by the <unit type="brigade">156th Brigade</unit>--Lowland Division--as we
did to the sector by the sea. But we could not, because, once we had
given a fair quota to the left, there was not enough stuff in our
lockers for the right. Such is war! No use splitting the difference and
trying to win everywhere like high brows halting between <location region="Flanders">Flanders</location> and
<location peninsula="Gallipoli">Gallipoli</location>. But I _am_ sick at heart, I must say, to think my brother
Scots should have had to catch hold of the hot end of the poker. Also to
think that, with another couple of hundred rounds, we should have got
and held H. 12. H. 12 which dominates--so prisoners say--the wells
whence the enemy draws water for the whole of his right wing.</p>

<p>To-day the old trouble is a-foot once again. <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> tells us the
Turkish counter-attacks are being pressed with utmost fury and are
beginning to look ugly, as we can give our infantry no support from our
guns although the enemy offer excellent artillery targets. When <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> is
extra accommodating it is doubly hard to be importunate, but it's got to
be done:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>_General <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian Hamilton</person> to Earl Kitchener._</p>

<p>"With reference to my telegrams No. M.F. 328 of 13th June and No. M.F.
381 of 28th June. Each successive fight shows more clearly than the last
how much may hang on an ample supply of ammunition, more especially high
explosive howitzer ammunition. In my telegram No. M.F. 381 I said that I
hoped we might be able to achieve success with the ammunition already
promised, and I adhere to that opinion; but every additional 100 rounds
means some reduction of risks and greater assurance of success. I raise
this question again because I gather from what I hear that matters in
the other theatre of operations may possibly be at a standstill without
much prospect of any vital alteration before the autumn fairly sets in.
If this should be the case it is for you to consider whether a larger
and more regular supply of ammunition should be sent to me in order to
give this force the utmost chance of gaining an early success. Judging
from the increased effect of the bombardments before the last two
attacks on facilitating the Infantry advance I am led to hope that this
success would not be long delayed under the cumulative effect of
unremitting bombardment. If, therefore, any change in the general
situation should make it possible to allow me temporary preferential
claim to all the ammunition I should like, I would ask for the following
amounts to be here by 1st August, in addition to those accompanying the
troops and already promised, namely, 4.5-inch howitzer, 3,000 rounds;
5-inch howitzer, 7,000 rounds; 6-inch howitzer, 5,000, and 9.3-inch
howitzer, 500 rounds, all high explosive. I should also ask for a
monthly supply on the following scale, first consignment to arrive
before 15th August:--</p>

<p>  "18-pr.               300,000
  "4.5-inch howitzer     30,000
  "5-inch howitzer       30,000
  "6-inch howitzer       24,000
  "60-pr.                15,000
  "9.2-inch howitzer      6,000</p>

<p>"The howitzer ammunition to be all high explosive, the 60-pr. to be
one-third shrapnel and two-thirds high explosive, and the 18-pr. to be
half of each.</p>

<p>"The above monthly scale includes ammunition for the following
additional ordnance which I should like to get, namely, two batteries of
4.5-inch howitzers for each of the Xth and XIth Divisions (since 5-inch
howitzers are found to be too inaccurate to bombard the enemy trenches
even in close proximity to our own), one battery of 6-inch howitzers and
four 9.2-inch howitzers.</p>

<p>"On the assumption already made it might be possible for you to arrange
to forward to Ordnance Stores, Marseilles, the ammunition asked for to
be here by 1st August. Time would thus be gained to accumulate the
supply required, and I could arrange with the Vice-Admiral to send a
fast steamer of 1,000 tons hold capacity to bring the consignment of
high explosives from Marseilles. To get the steamer coaled, to arrive at
Marseilles, coal again and be ready to receive the ammunition, would
take seven days.</p>

<p>"Please understand that this suggestion is only prompted for the
following reasons: (1) My growing belief that ample artillery might,
within a limited period, lead to quite a considerable success in this
theatre, and (2) because the reports which reach me seem to indicate
that an offensive is not likely to be undertaken elsewhere at present
(and I have mainly asked for offensive ammunition).</p>

<p>"The monthly supply above detailed I should not expect would be required
for more than two months."</p>

<p>If our Government really--whole-heartedly--_will_ that there should be a
complete success in the East, they must, equally, with whole hearts and
braced-up _will_, resist (for a while) the idea of any offensive in the
West. In saying this I speak of the A.B.C. of war. The main theatre is
where the amphibious power wishes to make it so. This cable of mine sent
to a man like <person name="Lord_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> is a very strong order. But now is the time to
speak up and let him realize that he must let the fields of France lie
fallow for the summer if he wishes to plough the Black Sea waves in
autumn.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_14th July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Wrote letters in the morning, and in the
evening went for a ride to the Salt Lake and there inspected the new
aeroplane camp on the far side of the water.</p>

<p>Last night more counter-attacks, all driven off. The French right is now
actually on the mouth of the Kereves Dere where it runs into the sea. We
have made about 500 prisoners and have captured a machine gun.
<person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> had to transfer the command of the <unit type="division">52nd Division</unit>,
temporarily, to Shaw, the new Commander of the <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit>.</p>

<p>Baikie is crying out to us for shells as if _we_ were bottling them up!
There are none.</p>

<p>
_15th July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> The answer has come in from the War
Office:--the answer, I mean, to mine of the day before yesterday in
which it is suggested that _if_ our rich brethren were off their feed
for the moment, some crumbs of high explosive might be spared:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"We have great difficulty in sending you the amounts of ammunition
mentioned in our No. 5770, cipher, and even now the proportion of 18-pr.
high explosive will be less than stated therein. In response, however,
to your No. M.F. 444, we are adding 1,000 rounds 4.5-inch, 500--5-inch,
500--6-inch and 75--9.2-inch. It will be quite impossible to continue to
send you ammunition at this rate, as we have reduced the supply to
France in order to send what we have to you, and the amounts asked for
in the second part of your telegram could not be spared without stopping
all operations in France. This, of course, is out of the question."</p>

<p>"This, of course, is out of the question." "Stopping all operations in
France" is the very kernel of the question. If half the things we hear
about the Bosche forces and our own are half true, we have no prospect
of dealing any decisive blow in the West till next spring. And an
indecisive blow is worse than no blow. But we can _hold on_ there till
all's blue. Now H.E. is offensive and shrapnel is defensive. I ought to
attack at once; French mustn't. Therefore, we should be given, _now_,
dollops of H.E.</p>

<p>This talk does not come through my hat. Some of the best brains on the
Western field are in touch with those of some of my following here. The
winning post stares us in the face; my old Chief gallops off the course;
how can I resist calling out? And then I get this "of course" cable (not
written by <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> I feel sure) which shows, if it shows anything, that "of
course" we ought never to have come here at all! Simple, is it not? In
war all is simple--that's why it's so complex. Never mind; my cable has
not been wasted. We reckon the 1,100 extra rounds it has produced may
save us 100 British casualties.</p>

<p>Rode over to "K" Beach and inspected the 25th Casualty Clearing Station,
Commandant Lieutenant-Colonel Mackenzie. Walked through the different
hospital wards talking to some twenty officers and two hundred men;
mostly medical cases. Did not think things at all up to the mark. Made
special note of the lack of mosquito nets, beds, pyjamas and other
comforts. For weeks past Jean has been toiling to get mosquito nets
bought and made up, which was simple, and to get them out to us, which
seems impossible. Too bad when so much money is being spent to see men
lying on the ground in their thick cord breeches in this sweltering
heat, a prey to flies and mosquitoes.</p>

<p>Discussing the landing of the New Divisions in <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay and the
diversion to be made by Legge on the right by storming Lone Pine,
<person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> makes it clear in a letter just to hand, that he has told his
two Divisional Generals everything. I had not yet gone into some of
these details with <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person>, <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> or Bailloud, all Corps
Commanders, for I am afraid of the news filtering down to the juniors
and from them, in the mysterious way news does pass, to the rank and
file of both services. Thence to the Turks is but a step. Were the Turks
to get wind of our plan, there would be nothing for it but to change the
whole thing, even now, at the eleventh hour.</p>

<p>Lieutenant-Colonel F. G. Fuller, my late G.S.O. (1) in the Central
Force, came over to lunch. He is now G.S.O. (2) of the <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit>.</p>

<p>At 5.30 p.m. rode over to "K" Beach for the second time and inspected
the Indian Brigade under Brigadier-General <person name="Charles_Cox">Cox</person>. They had to be pulled
out some time ago and given a rest. On parade were the 5th, 6th and 10th
Gurkha Battalions with the 14th Sikhs. Walked down both lines and
chatted with the British and Indian Officers. The men looked cheerful
and much recovered. In the evening Charlie Burn, King's Messenger, and
Captain Glyn came to dinner. Glyn has been sent out as a sort of
emissary, but whether by <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> or by the Intelligence or by the Admiralty
neither <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> nor I are quite able to understand.</p>

<p>Cabled the War Office _insisting_ that the lack of ammunition is
"disturbing." Also, that "half my anxieties would vanish" if only the
Master-General of Ordnance would see to it himself that the fortnightly
allowance could be despatched regularly. I could hardly put it stronger.</p>

<p>_Midnight._--Just back from G.S. tent with the latest. So far, so good.
Bailloud and <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> have carried two lines of Turkish trenches,
an advance of two to four hundred yards. But the ammunition question has
reached a crisis, and has become dangerous--very dangerous. On the whole
Southern theatre of operations, counting shell in limbers and shell
loaded in guns, we have 5,000 rounds of shrapnel. No high explosive--and
fighting is still going on!</p>

<p>  _Hi jaculis illi certant defendere saxis._</p>

<p>To whomsoever of my ancestors bequeathed me my power of detachment deep
salaams! How many much better men than myself would not close their eyes
to-night with a battle on the balance and 5,000 rounds wherewith to
fight it? But I shall sleep--D.V.; I can't create shell by taking
thought any more than Gouraud could retake the _Haricot_ by not drinking
his coffee.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_16th July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Forcing myself to work though I feel
unspeakably slack; wrangling with the War Office about doctors, nurses,
orderlies and ships for our August battles. A few days ago I sent the
following cable and they want to cut us down:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"It seems likely that during the first week of August we may have 80,000
rifles in the firing line striving for a decisive result, and therefore
certain that we shall then need more medical assistance. Quite
impossible to foresee casualties, but suppose, for example, we suffered
a loss of 20,000 men; though the figure seems alarming when put down in
cold blood, it is not an extravagant proportion when calculated on basis
of <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> fighting up to date. If this figure is translated into
terms of requirements such a battle would involve conversion of, say, 30
transports into temporary hospital ships, and necessitate something like
200 extra medical officers, with Royal Army Medical Corps rank and file
and nurses in proportion. If my prognosis is concurred in, these should
reach <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location> on or about 1st August. Some would D.V., prove superfluous,
and could be sent back at once, and in any case they could return as
soon as possible after operations, say, 1st September. Medical and
surgical equipment, drugs, mattresses in due proportion. In a separate
message I will deal with the deficiencies in ordinary establishment, but
I think it best to keep this cable as to specified and exceptional
demands distinct."</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_17th July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> After lunch felt so sick of scribble,
scribble, scribble whilst adventure sat seductive upon my doorstep that
I fluttered forth. At 2 o'clock boarded <location ship="H.M.S._Savage">H.M.S. _Savage_</location>
(Lieutenant-Commander Homer) and, with <person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person> and Freddie, steered for
Gully Beach. We didn't cast anchor but got into a cockleshell of a small
dinghy and rowed ashore under the cliffs, where we were met by <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person>.
Along the beach men were either bathing or basking mother-naked on the
hot sand--enjoying themselves thoroughly. I walked on the edge of the
sea, as far as the point which hides the gully's mouth from the Turkish
gunners, and was specially struck by the physique and class of the 6th
East Lancashires under Colonel Cole Hamilton. Then mounted and rode to
the Headquarters of General Shaw, commanding the 13th (new) Division.
Shaw was feeling his wounds; he had already been once round his lines;
so I would not let him come again. But Colonel Gillivan, G.S.O.1, Major
Hillyard, G.S.O.2, Captain Jackson, G.S.O.3, Colonel Burton, A.A. and
Q.M.G., joined us. First we went to the Headquarters of the 39th Brigade
commanded by Brigadier-General Cayley (the Brigade Major is Captain
Simpson). Then I went and looked at the trenches J.11-12-13, where I met
Colonel Palmer of the 9th Warwicks, Colonel Jordan, D.S.O., of the 7th
Gloucesters, Colonel Nunn of the 9th Worcesters, Colonel Andrews of the
7th North Staffordshires. We tramped through miles of trenches. The men
were very fit and cheery. It was the day when they were relieving one
another by companies from the reserve and there was a big crowd in the
Ravine. <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">De Lisle</person> told me that one week had made the most astonishing
difference to the savvy of these first arrivals of the New Army. At
first there was confusion, loss of energy and time; by the end of the
week they had picked up the wrinkles of the veterans. There was a good
lot of shelling from the Turks but, humanly speaking, we were all quite
snug and safe in the big gully or moving down the deep communication
trenches. No one, not even the new <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit>, paid the smallest
deference to the projectiles.</p>

<p>Now began one of these semi-comic, semi-serious adventures which seem to
dog my footsteps. Just as I got into the little dinghy, two bluejackets
pulling and a Petty Officer steering, the Turks began to shell <location ship="H.M.S._Savage">H.M.S.
_Savage_</location> as she lay about a hundred yards out. She did not like it, and,
instead of waiting to let us get aboard, Commander Homer thought it
wiser to sheer off about half a mile. When she quitted the Turks turned
their guns on to our cockleshell, and although none of the shot came
near us they still came quite near enough to interest the whole gallery
of some thousands of bathing Tommies who, themselves safe in the dead
ground under the cliff, were hugely amused to see their C.-in-C. having
a hot time of it. After ten minutes hard rowing we got close to the
destroyer and she, making a big circle at fairly high speed, came along
fast as if she was going to run us down, with the idea of baffling the
aim of the enemy. Not a bad notion as far as the destroyer was concerned
but one demanding acrobatic qualities of a very high order on the part
of the Commander-in-Chief. Anyway just as she was drawing abreast and I
was standing up to make my spring a shell hit her plump and burst in one
of her coal bunkers, sending up a big cloud of mixed smoke and black
coal dust. The Commander was beside himself. He waved us off furiously;
cracked on full steam and again left us in the lurch. We laughed till
the tears ran down our cheeks. Soon, we had reason to be more serious,
not to say pensive. The <location ship="H.M.S._Savage">_Savage_</location> showed a pair of clean heels this time
and ran right away to <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>. So there we were, marooned, half a mile
out to sea, in a tiny dinghy on which the Turks again switched their
blarsted guns. The two bluejackets pulled themselves purple. They were
both of them fat reservists and the mingling of anxiety and exertion,
emotion and motion, made the sweat pour in torrents down their cheeks.
Each time a shell plunked into the water we brightened up; then,
gradually, until the next one splashed, our faces grew longer and
longer. At last we got so far away that the Turks gave us up in disgust.
How much I should like to see that battery commander's diary.
Altogether, by the time we had boarded the <location ship="H.M.S._Savage">_Savage_</location>, we had been in that
cursed little dinghy for just exactly one hour, of which I should think
we were being gently shelled for three quarters of an hour. On board the
destroyer no harm to speak of: only one man wounded.</p>

<p>Cast anchor at <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> at 9 p.m. General Legge and Captain H. Lloyd came
over to stay the night. Mail from England.</p>

<p>Have cabled again to stir them up about the hospital ships.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_18th July, 1915._ Church Parade. Inspected troops. Wrote in camp all
the afternoon. Walked out to the lighthouse in the evening and watched
the shells bursting over Gully Beach where we were yesterday. How often
have I felt anxious seeing these shrapnel through the telescope. On the
spot, as I know from yesterday's experience, their bark is worse than
their bite. Colonel Ward of the Intelligence came to dinner and Captain
Doughtie, commanding <location ship="H.M.S._Abercrombie">H.M.S. _Abercrombie_</location>, paid me a visit.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_19th July, 1915._ Too much office work. Mr. Schuler, an Australian
journalist and war correspondent, turned up. Seems a highly intelligent
young fellow. He had met me on tour in Australia. Gave him leave to go
anywhere and see everything. The Staff shake their heads, but the future
is locked away in our heads, and the more the past is known the better
for us.</p>

<p><person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> has heard from the War Office that the Brigade of Russians
which had started from Vladivostock to join us here has been
counter-ordered. The War Office seem rather pleased than otherwise that
this reinforcement has fallen through. Why, I can't imagine. As they are
sending us a big fresh force of Britishers, they probably persuade
themselves that 5,000 Russians would be more trouble than they are
worth, but they forget the many thousands of shortage in my present
formations. Since they fixed up to send me the new Divisions I must have
lost ten thousand rifles, but as all my old Divisions remain at the
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> _in name_, they are being regarded at home, we strongly
suspect, as a sort of widow's cruse, kept full by miracles instead of
men and still, therefore,--Divisions!</p>

<p>In the evening the Vice-Admiral came over and we rode together down to
the Naval Seaplane Camp. The King's Messenger left at 5 p.m.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_20th July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Wrote double quick, then galloped over to
Kephalos to see the New Army, _sub rosa_. The men we struck were A.1.
They belong to the <unit type="brigade">32nd</unit> and <unit type="brigade">34th</unit> Brigades of the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit>. The <unit type="brigade">33rd</unit>
has gone to <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> to get salted.</p>

<p><person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> is still staying with the Admiral. He has had a hard time
and a heavy responsibility and is quite worn out. I devoutly trust he
may be on his legs again ere long. Have put in <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> to act for him
at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>. This should teach the young idea how to shoot. With every
aspect of the command and administration of the Southern theatre of
operations thus under his immediate orders he has a rare chance of
learning how to do it and how not to do it.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_21st July, 1915._--Just signed a letter to the Chief of the Imperial
General Staff and as it gives the run of my thoughts at the moment I
spatchcock the opening and final paras:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"My dear Wolfe <person name="Wolfe_Murray">Murray</person>,</p>

<p>"How do you manage to find time to write these charming letters of yours
with your own hand? They come like a gift from some oriental potentate
and carry with them the same moral obligations; i.e., that they ought to
be returned in kind. But to-day the time limit interposes, and I know
you will pardon me for once if I dictate.</p>

<p>"I am immensely interested in what you say with reference to the <unit type="division">29th</unit>
Division being below strength, namely, that we are getting short of men.
Well,--though one of the keenest voluntary service people existing, I
have always envisaged the fact that during a war we might be driven
to compulsion. Also in writing out fully my views on this subject (views
which I was not permitted by late Chiefs of the General Staff to
publish) I have always, for that reason, pressed for National
Registration. It does no one any harm, and rubs into the mind of the
young man that, under certain conditions, the State has first pull on
his pocket, labour, life and everything else. But, of course, if your
own wish that the <unit type="division">29th</unit> Division should take out 10 per cent. extra for
drafts (like the regiments do in France), had been carried into effect,
they would never have fallen as low as they actually did.</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

  <p>"<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Freddy Stopford</person> and Reed have been staying with me for 24 hours, and
the former is now in command of the <unit type="corps">8th Corps</unit> on the Peninsula,
<person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> having gone sick. He asked to stay with the Admiral for a
couple of days' rest, and the very moment he got safe on board ship the
overstrain of the past month told on him and he went down with a sharp
go of fever. I earnestly pray he will get right again quickly for there
are not many Commanders of his calibre. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Freddy Stopford</person> will now have a
good chance of getting the hang of this sort of fighting generally,
surrounded as he will be by <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person>'s experienced Staff. After
sending my last letter I rather repented of one or two harsh things I
said about Reed. There is some truth in them, but I need not have said
them. I hope he will do very well out here."</p>

<p>Now since that letter was written (yesterday) in comes a cable from <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>
saying Winston can't leave England but that Hankey starts in his place.</p>

<p><person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> says he is sure I will give him every facility.</p>

<p>A pretty stuffy cable in from the War Office on the Hospital ships and
medical personnel and material wrangle which is still going on. I,
personally, have checked every item of my estimate with closest personal
attention, although it took me hours in the midst of other very pressing
duties. This is not <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>'s pidgin but Woodward's and there was no
help for it. Our first landing found out a number of chinks in our
arrangements, and now, my Director of Medical Services is (quite
naturally) inclined to open his mouth as wide as if ships were drugs in
the market. So I have tried very hard, without too much help, to hit the
mean between extravagance and sufficiency. Now the War Office, who would
be the first to round on me if anything went wrong with my wounded,
query my demands as if we had just splashed off a cable asking for the
first things that came into our heads!</p>

<p>I am all for thrift in ships, but thrift in the lives of my wounded
comes first; my conscience is clear and I have answered sticking to my
point,--firmly! They say the thing is impossible; I have retaliated by
saying it is imperative.</p>

</entry>


<chapter n="14">CHAPTER XIV</chapter>

<title>THE FORCE--REAL AND IMAGINARY</title>

<entry><p>_22nd July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Had a jolly outing to-day. Left for Cape
<location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> by trawler just before 10 o'clock. <person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person>, Bertier and young
Brodrick came with me. Lunched at 8th Army Corps Headquarters with
<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and handed him a first outline scheme of the impending
operations. We read it through together and he seems to take all the
points and to be in general agreement. Left <person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person> behind to explain
any questions of detail which might not seem clear, whilst I went a tour
of inspection through the Eski Lines of trenches held by the 6th and 7th
Manchesters of the 42nd Division. These Eski Lines were first held about
the 7th or 8th May and have since been worked up, mainly by the energy
of <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person>, into fortifications, humanly speaking, impregnable. General
Douglas, Commander of the Division, came round with me. He reminds me
greatly of his brother, the late Chief of the Imperial General Staff;
excellent at detail; a conscientious, very hard worker. When I had seen
my Manchester friends I passed on into the Royal Naval Division Lines.
There General <person name="Archibald_Paris">Paris</person> convoyed me through his section as far as
Zimmerman's Farm, where I was joined by Bailloud with his Chief of Staff
and Chief of Operations. Together we made our way round the whole of
the French trenches winding up at de Tott's Battery.</p>

<p>After this whopping walk, we left by pinnace from below de Tott's
wondering whether the Asiatic Batteries would think us game worth their
powder and shot. They did not and so we safely boarded our trawler at
Cape <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>. Didn't get back to <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Harbour till 9 p.m. Being so
late, boarded the ever hospitable _Triad_ on chance and struck, as
usual--hospitality. <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> is really quite ill with fever. He did
not want to see anyone. As we were sitting at dinner I saw him through
the half open door staggering along on his way to get into a launch to
go aboard a Hospital ship. He is suffering very much from his head. The
doctors prophesy that he will pull round in about a week. I hope so
indeed, but I have my doubts. <person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person> reports that <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> is entirely
in accord with our project and keen.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_23rd July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Spent day in camp trying to straighten things
out: (1) the personal, (2) the strategical and (3) the administrative
arrangements.</p>

<p>(1) <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> has to go home and I have begged for Bruce Hamilton in
his place, and have told them I would have a great champion in him. He
and Smith-Dorrien were my best Brigadiers in South Africa. They stood on
my right hand and on my left all the way between Bloemfontein and
Pretoria, and I never quite made up my mind as to which was the better.
Bruce is a fighting man with an iron frame, and, in <location peninsula="Gallipoli">Gallipoli</location>, his
chief crab, his deafness, will be rather a gain to him.</p>

<p>(2) Bailloud, with his own War Minister in the background, is doing all
he knows to get 20,000 of my new troops allotted to a side show, not for
strategy's sake, but for the tactical relief of his troops from the
shelling. I quite sympathize with his reason as, after all, he is
responsible for his own troops and not for the larger issue. But, to
take one objection only, the Navy could not land a force at Besika Bay
and at the same time carry out landings at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> and Anzac. Again, since
Bailloud urged these views, the guns fixed up at de Tott's Battery have
already begun to gain mastery over the fire from the site of Troy. When
we have one of the new 14-inch gunned monitors moored off Rabbit Island
we shall get cross fire observations and give the Turkish Asiatic guns
the clean knock out. Amphibious operations are ticklish things: allied
operations are ticklish things: but the two together are like skating on
thin ice arm in arm with two friends who each want to cut a figure of
his own.</p>

<p>(3) Slovenly bills of lading. Bertie Lawrence, who was sent to <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location> in
June when things were growing desperate, was here yesterday and has made
a report on the present business situation which, though less chaotic,
is still serious. There are not launches enough to enable people to get
about. There are not lighters enough to work the daily transhipment of
300 tons. But the worst trouble lies in the bills of lading. Sometimes
they arrive a week after their ships. Usually cargo shipped at Malta or
Alexandria is omitted. Half the time we can't lay hands on vital plant,
tackle, supplies, munitions, because we have no means of knowing what
is, or is not, on board some ship in the harbour. The trouble is of old
date but has reached its climax owing to our shortage of rounds for our
18-pounders.</p>

<p>We were notified a new fuse key would be required for the new shells on
the 12th June. The shells arrived but the keys were not despatched till
the 15th July! The vouchers are all wrong, and there, in idleness, lies
the stuff that spells success. A soldier is not a conjurer that he
should be handed over a fully laden ship and told to ferret out a fuse
key.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_24th July, 1915._ Last night the Turkish Commander drove his troops
into their tenth attack upon our extreme left where they were beaten off
as usual with a loss of several hundreds--this time we only suffered
about a dozen casualties. Together with <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, I rode over to "K"
Beach at 11 a.m. to inspect part of the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit> there encamped.
General Hammersley, Divisional Commander, met me. Also Colonel Malcolm,
his General Staff Officer and Major Duncan. The first Brigade I looked
at was Sitwell's--the <unit type="brigade">34th</unit>. A fine looking lot of men:--</p>

<p>  8th Northumberland Fusiliers,
  5th Dorsets,
  9th <unit type="brigade">Lancashire Fusiliers</unit>,
  1 Coy. 11th Manchester Fusilers.</p>

<p>Next I passed on to Haggard's Brigade--the <unit type="brigade">32nd</unit>. On parade were--</p>

<p>  9th West Yorkshires,
  6th Yorkshires,
  8th West Riding Regiment,
  6th York and Lancashires.</p>

<p>Lastly I inspected the 67th and 68th Companies R.E. of the 1<unit type="brigade">34th</unit>
Fortress Company, as well as the Field Ambulance. Officers and men
looked splendid. I was glad indeed to be able to congratulate Hammersley
on his command. The doctors tell me, that, short as has been their stay,
a large number of the men are already infected by the prevalent disease.
Well, they don't look like that,--and it won't kill them that's certain,
for I have had it on me strong for the best part of two months. But it
knocks out the starch from its victims, and if fair play existed in
moonlit lands, every white man here should be credited with 25 per cent.
extra kudos for everything that he does with his brains or his body
under the shadow of this pestilence.</p>

<p>Have got a reply from the War Office (Q.M.G.2) making light of my
shipping troubles and saying the War Office has always cabled full
advices. What can I say to that? As the lamb thought to himself when the
wolf began to growl.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_25th July, 1915._ Spent most of the day in camp. Church Parade at 9
a.m. Charles Lister came over from "K" Beach to lunch. He is a
fascinating creature and has made a name for himself with the Naval
Division, where standards are high, as being the keenest of the keen
and the bravest of the brave. Hammersley, Malcolm and Aitkin called in
the evening, but I had gone for a stroll and missed them.</p>

<p>The great Turkish attack timed by all our spies for the 23rd has never
come off but, as showing the fine spirit which animates the Anzacs, it
is worth noting that on that day not one soul reported sick. They would
not go near the doctors for fear they might be made to miss a battle.</p>

<p>Last night the French took a small trench, and though the Turks had a
dash at it in the morning, they were easily beaten off. Twice out of
three times we gain something when we fight and the third time we lose
no ground.</p>

<p>Given, therefore, the factors of the problem, men, munitions and the
distance to be covered (two to three miles), the result pans out like a
proposition by Euclid. No question of breaking through is involved as in
any other theatre, but merely a question of pushing back a very clearly
limited number of yards. The men have in their hearts a reservoir of
patience which will never run dry so long as they are sure of the Will
to Win at their backs. They need have no qualms about G.H.Q. here, but
politicians are more--shall we say, mercurial? And the experts from
France are throwing cold water on our cause by day and night. Therefore,
as the Fleet is not going to have a dash, it is just as well we are
about to try the one great effort and get it done quickly. We will gain
a lot of ground; so much is certain, and it's as sure as anything can
be in war that somewhere we shall make good a key to the position.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_26th July, 1915._ Stifling. Am sticking out about the lack of proper
advices of shipments. Ammunition _makes_ itself scarce enough without
being _made_ scarce. Rare and curious articles are worth careful
booking; that's the text of my cable.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_27th July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Hard at it. <person name="General_Altham">Altham</person> came in to see me and
spent an hour and a half. A man of business! Mahon arrived at mid-day.
Very cheery but he feels that he is the only Lieutenant-General
executively employed with troops who has so small a command as a
Division. He says that either he should be given a Corps, or that
his Lieutenant-General's rank should be reverted to that of
Major-General. I quite agreed. I feel as strongly as he does that, as a
Lieutenant-General, he is clean out of his setting in a Major-General's
appointment and has blocked the way to a go-ahead young Corps Commander,
because that Corps Commander must, by <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s decision, be his senior.
Still, there didn't seem to be anything to be done, so after my telling
him how things stood here, and hearing with great pleasure the fine
account he gave me of his Irish Division, we adjourned to lunch. Colonel
King, his G.S.O. (1), also lunched and seemed to be a very nice fellow.
After lunch they both went off to the G.S. to be posted.</p>

<p>Admiral Wemyss came over from <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location> and saw me. He is senior to de
Robeck but has waived that accident of rank seeing we are at war. An
interesting man and a <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>ite; i.e., he'd go right through the Straits
to-morrow,--or go under. He is one of those men, none too common in the
Services, whose mind has gained breadth in the great world without
losing its keenness. These rival tenets are straining the fabric of the
Fleet, but, as I constantly tell our General Staff, my course is as
clear to me as a pikestaff. I back the policy of the _de facto_ Naval
Commander-in-Chief--my own coadjutor. There is a temptation to do wrong,
but I resist it. What would it not be to me were the whole Fleet to
attack as we land at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>! But obviously I cannot go out of my own
element to urge the Fleet to actions, the perils of which I am
professionally incompetent to gauge.</p>

<p>At 5.30 p.m. I went off riding with <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>, Ormsby Johnson and
Freddie <person name="Freddie_Maitland">Maitland</person>. We cantered over to Seaplane Camp; passed the time of
day to the men there and over-hauled some of the machines. Coming back,
we passed through part of the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit> Camp; all very ship-shape
and clean. Freddie <person name="Freddie_Maitland">Maitland</person> and I dined on board the _Beryl_ with Sir
Douglas Gamble. He seems highly pleased with everyone and everything; I
wouldn't go quite so far! There we met <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>, <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>, <person name="General_Altham">Altham</person>, <person name="General_Ellison">Ellison</person>
and Captain Stephens. Got back at 11.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_28th July, 1915._ A cable from <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> about <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person>'s breakdown,
telling me the Prime Minister thinks that Bruce Hamilton is too old for
active work and heavy strain. Instead I am to have <person name="Francis_Davies">Davies</person>. I know Joey
<person name="Francis_Davies">Davies</person>--everyone does. But I also know Bruce Hamilton. There is no
tougher man or more resolute fighter in the Army. In my letter to <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> I
said, "The only man I can think of who would really inspire me with full
confidence in these emergencies, excursions and alarms, would be Bruce
Hamilton. Bruce Hamilton is a real fighting man, and his deafness here
would be a great asset as he would be able to sleep through the shell
and rifle fire at night."</p>

<p>The older Officers will be sorry indeed to hear Bruce Hamilton is
barred. Shaw, the new Commander of the <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit>, will be especially
disappointed.</p>

<p>Admiral Gamble came off to see me and afterwards dined. I was very
careful as I don't want to be quoted about the Sister Service. Gamble
sings praise of our outfit, but I can't help wondering how, when and
where he has got it into his head that we have small craft in abundance!</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_29th July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Stuck to camp, and lucky I did so, for the
cipher of a queer cable from S. of S. for War came in and called for as
much thought as is compatible with prompt handling. The message begins
with a ripe sugar plum:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"At this stage of the operations which you have conducted with so much
ability and in which your troops have so greatly distinguished
themselves, we" (this "we" is a new expression; the S. of S. always says
"I") "consider it advisable to summarize what we are placing at your
disposal for the effort which we hope will bring your operations to a
successful termination.</p>

<p>"We have sent you out" and then the cable launches out into an inventory
of the forces entrusted to me which, though very detailed, is yet
largely based on what we call the widow's cruse principle. As to the
demnition total, "we" tells "me," categorically, (as the Lawyers say
when they describe the whiteness of soot) that I have "a total of about
205,000 men for the forthcoming operations." The A.G. who brought me the
cable could make nothing of it. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> then came over and he could
make nothing of it. We can none of us see the point of pretending to
_us_ that my force has been kept up to the strength all the time, or of
adding bayonets to the French or of assuming to _us_ that _we_ possess
troops which Maxwell has told me time and again he requires for Egyptian
defence. Were these figures going to the enemy Chief they might
intimidate him--coming here they alarm me. There is a "We" at the other
end of the cable which knows so little that it tells me, who know every
gun, rifle and round of ammunition I have at my disposal, that I have
double that number to handle. We won't defeat the enemy by paper
strengths. As far as sentiments go, the cable is by chalks the heartiest
handshake we poor relations to the West have had since we started. From
the outset we've been kicked by phrases such as, if you don't hurry up
we will have to "reconsider the position," etc., etc. Now, the "Wees"
wind up with a really wonderful paragraph:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"We should like to hear from you after considering your plans whether
there is anything further in the way of personnel, guns or ammunition we
can send you, as we are most anxious to give you everything you can
possibly require and use. You will realize that as regards ammunition we
have had to stop supplying France to give you the full output, which
will be continued as long as possible; in the short time available
before the bad weather intervenes the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> operations are now of
the highest importance."</p>

<p>The position seems now, to me, extraordinarily delicate. Are we to let
the mistakes in this flattering cable slide, and build upon its
promises, or, are we to pull whoever believes these figures out of their
fool's paradise? Well, I feel we must have it out and although deeply
grateful for the nice words and for the splendid effort actually being
made, we _cannot_ let it be assumed by _anyone_ that our vanishing Naval
and Territorial Divisions are complete and up to strength. As to
ammunition, I asked plainly over a fortnight ago, for what I thought was
necessary to rapid success. I was told in so many words that France
would not spare it; though it would have been a small affair to them.
Now; as if these cables had no existence, they ask if there is "anything
in the way of _personnel, guns or ammunition you can possibly require
and use_." The truth is, I don't like this cable; in spite of its
flowery opening I don't like it at all. As to personnel, I ask for young
and energetic commanders, Byng and Rawlinson, and am turned down. Next I
ask for an old and experienced Commander, Bruce Hamilton, and am turned
down. Next I say that Reed, who would be a good staff officer to some
Generals, is not well suited to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>; I am turned down. I try to get
a business man to run <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location> and have been turned down till just the
other day. In all these points the War Office are supreme and are acting
well within their rights. But they show some want of consistency in
talking to me all of a sudden, as if it was a matter of course I should
be met half way in my wishes.</p>

<p>So there and then we roughed out this reply:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"Your Nos. 6583 and 6588. Your appreciation of our efforts will afford
intense gratification and encouragement to everyone.</p>

<p>"In regard to what we should like if it is available in the shape of
guns and ammunition, please see my No. M.F. 444, of 13th July, which
still holds good. As to the final paragraph of your No. 6583, I did not
realize that you were stopping supplies to France in order to give us
full output, since a fortnight ago your No. 6234 stated that it was then
impossible for you to send the ammunition I asked for, and that it would
be impossible to continue supplies even on a much lower scale, since it
would involve the reduction of supplies to France. Naturally, I have
always realized that you, and not I, must judge of the comparative
importance of the demands from the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> and from France.</p>

<p>"With regard to numbers, the grand total you mention does not take into
account non-effectives or casualties; it includes reinforcements such as
<unit type="division">LIVth</unit> and part of the <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit> Divisions, etc., which cannot be here in
time for my operation, and it also includes Yeomanry and Indian troops
which, until this morning, I was unaware were at my unreserved disposal.
For the coming operation, the number of rifles available is about half
the figure you quote, viz., 120,000. I am only anxious, in emphasizing
this point, to place the statement regarding my strength on the correct
basis, and one which gives a true view of the position.</p>

<p>"What I want in a hurry is as much additional high explosive shell as
you can send me up to amounts asked for in my No. M.F. 444, and as many
of the 4.5-inch and 6-inch howitzers asked for in that telegram as there
is ammunition for. I am despatching a ship immediately, and its time of
arrival at Marseilles will be telegraphed later.</p>

<p>"With regard to sending the IInd Mounted Division unmounted, I am at
once telegraphing Maxwell to obtain his views."</p>

<p>The Mail bag went out this morning.</p>

<p>Hankey is now busy going over the Peninsula. I have not seen much of
him. A G.S. Officer has been told off to help him along and to see that
he does not get into trouble. I am not going to dry nurse him. He showed
me of his own free will a copy of a personal cable he had sent to Lord
Kitchener in which he says, speaking of his first visit to Anzac,
"Australians are superbly confident and spoiling for a fight." This is
exactly true and I feel it is good that one who has the ear of the
insiders should say it. I wrote Wolfe <person name="Wolfe_Murray">Murray</person> a week ago that he was a
successor to those Commissioners who were sent out by the French
Republic in its early days. Actually, I am very glad to have him. Lies
are on the wing, and he, armed with the truth, will be able to knock
some of them out hereafter when he meets them in high places.</p>

<p>I have been bothered as to how to answer a letter from a statesman for
whom I cherish great respect, who has always been very kind to me and
whom I like very much. He writes:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"It may interest you to know the Cabinet has entrusted the
superintendence of the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> business to a comparatively small and
really strong committee drawn equally from the two parties. We most
thoroughly understand the extreme difficulty of your task and the
special conditions of the problem in front of you and the Admiral. All
we ask from you is complete confidence and the exact truth. We are not
babes and we can digest strong meat. Do not think that we ever want
anything unpleasant concealed from us, nor do we want you ever to swerve
one hair's breadth from your own exact judgment in putting the case
before us, certainly never on the pleasant side; if you ever swerve pray
do so on the unpleasant side.... If you want more ammunition say so...."</p>

<p>"Could you eat a bun, my boy?" said the old gentleman to the little boy
looking in at the shop window. "Could I eat ten thousand b ... buns and
the baker who baked them?" So the dear little fellow answered. If I want
more ammunition indeed? If ...? I fear the "comparatively small and
really strong committee." They fairly frighten me. There they sit, all
wishing us well, all evidently completely bamboozled. "If you want more
ammunition, say so!" Anyway, my friend means me well but my path is
perfectly clear; I have only one Chief--<person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>--and I correspond with no one
but him, or his Staff, whether on the subject of ammunition or anything
else....</p>

<p>As to the letter, I know it is entirely kind, genuine and inspired by
the one idea of helping me. But I've got to say no thank you in some
unmistakable manner. So I have replied:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"I am grateful for your reassuring remarks about your Committee having
confidence in my humble self. For my part I have confidence in the
_moral_ of my troops and in the devotion of the Navy which are the two
great and splendid assets amidst this shifting kaleidoscope of the
factors and possibilities of war.</p>

<p>"I am not quite sure that I clearly understand your meaning about
cabling home the exact truth. Is there any occasion on which I have
failed to do so? I should be very sorry indeed to think I had
consciously or unconsciously misled anyone by my cables. There is
always, of course, the broad spirit of a cable which depends on the
temperament of the sender. It is either tinged with hope or it has been
dictated by one who fears the worst. If you mean that you would prefer a
pessimistic tone given to my appreciations, then I am afraid you will
have to get another General."</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_30th July, 1915._ Gascoigne of "Q" branch lunched. On getting news of
the decisive victory on the Euphrates I caused a _feu de joie_ to be
fired precisely at 5 p.m. by all the troops on the Peninsula. At the
appointed hour I walked up the cliff's edge whence I clearly heard the
roll of fire. The question of whether musketry sounds will carry so far
is settled. Evidently the Turks have taken up the challenge for it was
quite a long time before the distant rumbling died away. In the cool of
the evening took a walk. Commandant Bertier and la Borde dined.</p>

<p><person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>, now commanding at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>, has endorsed a report from the
Commander of the 42nd <unit type="brigade">East Lancs</unit> Division saying that out of a draft of
45 recruits just come from home three have been cast as totally unfit
and nine as permanently unfit through blindness. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> says that he
can't understand this, as the second line Battalion, from which these
poor fellows were selected, contained good soldiers and tall fellows
quite lately when they were under his command in England. Have cabled
the facts home; also the following, showing the result of the
Admiralty's attitude towards their own Naval Division now Winston has
departed:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 505). From General <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian Hamilton</person> to War Office. The
effective strength of the Marine Brigade is now reduced to 50 officers
and 1,890 rank and file. In addition, only five battalions, Royal Naval
Volunteer Reserve Battalions, are now remaining in the Division, as the
Anson Battalion has been withdrawn for special work in connection with
the forthcoming operations. Moreover, 300 men, stokers, from this
division have been handed over to the Navy for work in auxiliary
vessels, see my telegram No. M.F.A. 1377, of 11th July. I have
consequently decided to reduce the division to eight battalions and to
reorganize it into two brigades as a temporary measure. Can you give me
any idea when the reinforcements for this division are likely to be
despatched and when they may be expected here? I should like to see the
division again at its strength of 12 battalions, and do not want to lose
it, as it contains a very valuable war-trained nucleus, but unless it is
brought under army administration, it does not appear likely that it can
be maintained."</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_31st July, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Quiet day spent in trying to clear my table
before sailing for Mitylene to see the new Irish Division. The grand
army with which some War Office genius credited us appear to have served
their purpose. At our challenge they have now taken to their heels like
Falstaff's eleven rogues in buckram suits. The S. of S. (cabling this
time as "I" and not as "We,") says, "it is not worth while trying to
reconcile numbers by cable and it is difficult to make up accurate
states."</p>

<p>Do not let me forget, though, that a slice of solid stuff is sandwiched
into this cable--we are to get some 4.5 shell _via_ Marseilles; H.E. we
hope: also, two batteries of 4.5 howitzers: also that the A.G. has been
trying hard to feed the <unit type="division">29th</unit> Division. The Territorials are the people
who are being allowed to go to pot--not a word of hope even, and before
the eyes of everyone.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_1st August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> The usual rush before leaving. No time to
write. Sent two cables, copies attached. The first to the War Office, in
answer to one from the A.G. wherein he plumes himself upon the
completeness of the <unit type="division">29th</unit> Division. That completeness, alas, is only so
relatively; i.e., in comparison with the sinking condition of the
Territorial Divisions:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"We are deeply grateful to you for the drafts you have despatched for
the XXIXth Division as the fighting existence of that fine formation has
been prolonged by their timely arrival, but I fear that you are very
wide of the mark in your assumption that these drafts have completed the
Division.</p>

<p>"As I have ventured to point out incessantly since my arrival here,
constant large numbers of casualties must occur between the demands for
and the arrival of drafts owing to the length of the sea voyage. It was
for this very plain reason that it was doubly necessary to have here the
10 per cent. margin granted in the case of battalions going to France.
We must always be considerably under establishment in the absence of
some such margin.</p>

<p>"I fully realize, in saying this, that it may be quite impossible to
meet such demands as I suggest, but I feel bound to let you know the
only possible terms on which any unit in this force can ever be up to
establishment.</p>

<p>"At the present moment, excluding 1,700 drafts coming on _Simla_ and
_Themistocles_, the actual infantry strength of the XXIXth Division is
219 officers and 8,424 other ranks."</p>

<p>The second cable is to <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> The War Office Army has melted into thin air
and it only remains to express my heartfelt thanks for the real Army:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"With reference to your No. 6645. Very many thanks. You have done
everything for us that man can do. The ship will probably not reach me
in time but since I know that the ammunition is actually _en route_ for
me, and that it will (D.V.) arrive, I need not husband what we have, but
can fire freely if I see great results thus obtainable. The Turk, at any
rate, where he knows that he is fighting for Constantinople, is a
stubborn fighter, and the difficulty is not so much in the taking of
positions as in the maintaining of them.</p>

<p>"Hence the extra ammunition you are sending me will come in the nick of
time. The ship will arrive at Marseilles 7 p.m. 4th August, as I
telegraphed to the Quartermaster-General yesterday. Many thanks for the
two batteries of 4.5-inch howitzers, they are worth their weight in gold
to us."</p>

<p>At 5 p.m. embarked on H.M.S. _<location ship="H.M.S._Chatham">Chatham</location>_ (Captain Drury Lowe) with George
Lloyd of the General Staff and young Brodrick. At 6 p.m. sailed for
Mitylene.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_2nd August, 1915. H.M.S. "<location ship="H.M.S._Chatham">Chatham</location>," Mitylene._ We opened Mitylene
Harbour at 5.30 a.m. So narrow was the entrance, and so hidden, that at
first it looked as if the _<location ship="H.M.S._Chatham">Chatham</location>_ was charging the cliffs; next as if
her long guns must entangle themselves in the flowering bushes on either
side of the channel; then, as we sailed out over a bay like a big
turquoise, I felt as though we were at peace with all men, making a
pilgrimage to the home of Sappho, and that we had left far behind us
these giant wars. But only for a moment!</p>

<p>After early breakfast, where I met Captain Grant of H.M.S. _Canopus_,
left in a steam pinnace to inspect the 30th Brigade under
Brigadier-General Hill.</p>

<p>Inspected:--</p>

<p>  H.M.T. _Alaudia_, 9.30 a.m.
      6th Royal Dublin Fusiliers,
      7th Royal Dublin Fusiliers,
          Col G. Downing, 7th R.D.F., in command.</p>

<p>  H.M.T. _Andania_, 10.30 a.m.
      6th R. Inniskilling Fusiliers,
      5th Royal Irish Fusiliers,
          Lt.-Col. M. Pike, 5th R.I.F., in command.</p>

<p>  H.M.T. _Canada_, 11.30 a.m.
      6th Royal Irish Fusiliers,
          Lt.-Col. F. A. Greer in command.</p>

<p>  H.M.T. _Novian_, 12 p.m.
      5th Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers,
          Lt.-Col. H. Vanrennan in command.</p>

<p>The Royal Irish Fusiliers and Royal Inniskilling Fusiliers had not got
back on board ship by the time I was ready for them, so I hurried off
by motor launch to a landing in another part of the Bay and, walking
through a village, caught them resting by their piled arms after a route
march. All of these men looked very well and cheery. The villagers were
most friendly and had turned out in numbers, bringing presents of
flowers and fruit. Not more than 60 per cent. of the men are Irish, the
rest being either North of England miners or from Somerset.</p>

<p>In the evening, crossed the glassy bay and motored to pay a
double-barrelled visit to the Military and Civil Governors. Topping the
watershed, yet another pleasure shock. Through the sea haze Mitylene
shines out like an iridescent bubble of light. Never had I seen anything
so vivid in its colour and setting as this very ancient, very small,
very brilliant city of Mitylene. Rio de Janeiro, Sydney, the Golden Horn
are sprawling daubs to flawless Mitylene.</p>

<p>Hesketh Smith and Compton Mackenzie were with us. The Governors very
polite. The soldier man is a Cretan and seemed a good sort. We took tea
at the Hotel and then made our way back to the _<location ship="H.M.S._Chatham">Chatham</location>_. Found messages
from G.H.Q. to say all's well and stuff being smuggled in without hitch
at Anzac. At 7 p.m. we sailed for <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location>; a breeze from the West
whipping up little waves into cover for enemy periscopes. So the moment
we left the harbour we took on a corkscrew course, dodging and twisting
like snipe in an Irish bog, to avoid winding up our trip in the dark
belly of a German submarine. Soon emerged from the sea a huge piled up
white cloud, white and clear cut at first as the breast of a swan upon
a blue lake, slowly turning to deep rose colour flecked here and there
with gold. As it swallowed up the last lingering colours of the sunset,
the world grew grey, then black, and we were, humanly speaking, safe.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_3rd August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Anchored at <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> roadstead 5.30 a.m.
<person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> not up yet so <person name="General_Altham">Altham</person> got first innings about transport and
supply.</p>

<p>Next the G.S. All our preliminaries are working on quite smoothly
towards the climax and, so far, it seems likely the Turks have no notion
of the scheme.</p>

<p>Girodon steamed over from <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> to see me and went back again in the
evening. He is the mirror of French chivalry, modesty and good form,
besides being an extraordinary fine soldier.</p>

<p>The <unit type="brigade">33rd</unit> Brigade, sent by me to gain wisdom at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>, have now been
brought here so that the whole <unit type="division">11th Division</unit> can start off together.</p>

<p>Just as the peculiar foggy air of Lancashire is essential to the weaving
of the finer sorts of tissues, so an atmosphere of misunderstandings
would really seem to suit the War Office.</p>

<p>In the cable telling me I would have 205,000 troops for my push, the S.
of S. had informed me categorically that the 8,500 Yeomanry and mounted
troops in Egypt, as well as 11,500 Indian troops and the Artillery
stationed there _were mine_.</p>

<p>As the present garrison of Egypt numbers over 70,000 and as the old
peace garrison of Egypt was 5,000 and as, further, there is no question
of serious attack on Egypt from outside, it seemed to us there might be
men in this part of the message. Leaving the Indian troops out of the
account, for the moment, I therefore wired to Maxwell and asked him if
he thought he would be able to organize a _portion_ of the 8,500 mounted
men, in order that, at a pinch, they might be able to come and reinforce
us here. So the matter stood when I got another cable from the S. of S.
telling me 5,000 drafts are "_en route_ or under orders" to join the
<unit type="division">29th</unit> Division and that the War Office are "unable to carry out your
views about additional marginal drafts." S. of S. then goes on:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"Maxwell wires that you are taking 300 officers and 5,000 men of his
mounted troops. I do not quite understand why you require Egyptian
Garrison troops while you have the <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit> Division at Alexandria, and
the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit>, the last six battalions of which are arriving in five or six
days, on the _Aquitania_.</p>

<p>"When I placed the Egyptian Garrison at your disposal to reinforce at
the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> in case of necessity, Maxwell pointed out that Egypt
would be left very short, and I replied that you would only require them
in case of emergency for a short time, and that the risk must be run. I
did not contemplate, however, that you would take troops from the
Egyptian Garrison until those sent specially for you were exhausted. How
long will you require Maxwell's troops, and where do you intend to send
them? They should only be removed from Egypt for actual operations and
for the shortest possible time."</p>

<p>We may read this cable wrong but it seems to us to embody a topsy-turvy
tactic! To wait till one part of your forces are killed off (for that is
the plain English of "exhausted") before you bring up the other part of
your forces.</p>

<p>It is not easy to know what to do. The very best we can do, it sometimes
seems to me, is to keep quiet rather than add one iota to the anxieties
of people staggering under a load of responsibilities and cares. In the
good old days the Gordons fought in two decisive battles in two
Continents within a few months and no one worried the War Office about
drafts! The 92nd carried on--had to carry on; they fell to quarter
strength--still they were the Gordons and they carried on, just as if
they counted a thousand rifles in their ranks. Now, I am quite prepared
to do that to-day--_if that is the policy_. If that _were_ the policy;
not one grouse or grumble should ever cross my lips. But that is _not_
the policy. Press and People believe a Division is a unit made up in
scientific proportions of different branches and numbering a certain
number of rifles. They are told so; the War Office keep telling them so;
they believe it, and, in fact, it is an absolute necessity of this
modern trench war that it should be so. Although the Gordons got no
_drafts_ between the battle of Kandahar and the battle of Majuba Hill,
they got six months' _rest_; which was even better. In those days, apart
from sieges, a battle was an event, here it is the rest or respite that
is an event. Even British soldiers can't stick day and night fighting
for ever. The attack spirit begins to ebb _unless_ it is fed with fresh
blood. Whether <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s mind, big with broad views, grasps this new factor
with which he has never himself come into personal contact, God knows.
But for his sake, every bit as much as for my own, it is up to me to
keep hammering, hammering, hammering at drafts, drafts, drafts.</p>

<p>Dined with the ever hospitable and kind hearted <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> on _Triad_.
The Navy are still divided. Some there are who would wish me to urge the
Admiral to play first fiddle in the coming attack. This _I will not do_.
I have neither the data nor the technical knowledge which would justify
me to my conscience in doing so.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_4th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Have been out seeing the New Army at work.
Some of the XIth Division were practising boat work in the evening and
afterwards a Brigade started upon a night march into the mountains. The
men are fit, although just beginning to be infected with the Eastern
Mediterranean stomach trouble; i.e., the so-called cholera, which saved
Constantinople from the Bulgarians in the last war.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_5th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> The day so longed for is very near now. O
that it had come at the period of our victories! But there is time
enough still, and the first moves of the plan are working smooth as
oiled machinery. For the past few nights there has been steady flow
into Anzac of troops, including a Division of the New Army. This has
taken place, without any kind of hitch, under the very noses of the
Turkish Army who have no inkling of the manoeuvre--as yet! The Navy
are helping us admirably here with their organization and good sea
discipline. Also, from what they tell me, Shaw and the <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit> of
the New Army are playing up with the clockwork regularity of veterans.
All this marks us up many points to the good, before even the flag
drops. For, given the fine troops we have, the prime factors of the
whole conception; the factors by which it stands or falls; are:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>(1) Our success in hoodwinking the Turks; i.e., surprise.</p>

<p>(2) Our success in getting the <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit> and the Indian Brigade
unnoticed into Anzac.</p>

<p>(3) Our success in landing the Divisions from <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location>, Lemnos and
Mitylene, at moments fixed beforehand, upon an unknown, unsurveyed,
uncharted shore of <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>. Of these three factors (1) and (2) may already
be entered to our credit; (3) is on the knees of the Navy.</p>

<p>The day before the start is the worst day for a Commander. The operation
overhangs him as the thought of another sort of operation troubles the
minds of sick men in hospitals. There is nothing to distract him; he has
made his last will and testament; his affairs are quite in order; he has
said _au revoir_ to his friends with what cheeriness he can muster.
Looking back, it seems to me that during two months every conceivable
contingency has been anticipated and weighed and that the means of
dealing with it as it may arise is now either:--embodied in our
instructions to Corps Commanders, or else, set aside as pertaining to my
own jurisdiction and responsibility. To my thinking, in fact, these
instructions of ours illustrate the domain of G.H.Q. on the one hand and
the province of the Corps Commander on the other very typically. The
General Staff are proud of their work. Nothing; not a nosebag nor a
bicycle has been left to chance.[1]</p>

<p><person name="Francis_Davies">Davies</person> and Diggle, his A.D.C., lunched and the Admiral came to haul me
out for a walk about 6 p.m.</p>

<p>Have written <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> by this evening's Mail bag about the sickness of the
Australians, and indeed of all the troops here, excepting only the
native Indian troops, and also about our Medical _band-o-bast_ for the
battle. No question about it, the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> was the theatre of all
others for our Indian troops.</p>

<p>Have now seen all the New Army units except six Battalions of the 10th
Division.</p>

<p>French has written me a very delightful letter.</p>

<p>FOOTNOTES:</p>

<p>[Footnote 1: See Appendix III containing actual instructions, together
with a brief explanatory heading.--IAN H., 1920.]</p>

</entry>


<chapter n="15">CHAPTER XV</chapter>

<title>SARI BAIR AND SUVLA</title>

<entry><p>_6th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> O! God of Bethel, by whose hand thy people
still are fed,--I am wishing the very rare wish,--that it was the day
after to-morrow. Men or mice we will be by then, but I'd like to know
which. <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s New Army, too! How will they do? What do they think? They
speak--and with justice--of the spirit of the Commander colouring the
_moral_ of his men, but I have hardly seen them, much less taken their
measure. One more week and we would have known something at first hand.
Now, except that the <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit> and the <unit type="brigade">33rd</unit> Brigade gained good
opinions at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>, all is guess work.</p>

<p>Went down to "K" Beach to see the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit> go off. Young Brodrick,
who was with us, proved himself much all there on the crowded pier and
foreshore; very observant; telling me who or what I had not noticed,
etc. First the destroyers were filling up and then the lighters. The
young Naval Officers in charge of the lighters were very keen to show me
how they had fixed up their reserves of ammunition and water. Spent
quite a time at this and talking to Hammersley and Malcolm, his G.S.O.
(1); also to Coleridge, G.S.O. (2), and to no end of Regimental
Officers and men. Hammersley has been working too hard; at least he
looked it; also, for the occasion, rather glum. Quite natural; but I
always remember Wolseley's remark about the moral stimulus exerted by
the gay staff officer and his large cigar. The occasion! Yes, each man
to his own temperament. Some pray before battle; others dance and drink.
The memory of Cromwell prevails over that of Prince Rupert with most
Englishmen but Prince Rupert, _per se_, usually prevailed over Cromwell.
To your adventurous soldier; to our heroes, <person name="Lord_Bobs">Bobs</person>, Sir Evelyn, Garnet
Wolseley, Charles Gordon (great psalm-singer though he was) an occasion
like to-night's holds the same intoxicating mixture of danger and desire
as fills the glass of the boy bridegroom when he raises it to the health
of his enigma in a veil. But I don't know how it is; I used to feel like
that; now I too am terribly anxious. Disappointed not to see <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>
nor Reed. They were to have been there. Besides the men on the beetles
there are men packed like herrings upon the decks of the destroyers. I
had half a mind to cruise round in the motor launch and say a few words
to them Elandslaagte fashion, but was held back by feeling that the rank
and file don't know me and that there was too long an interval before
the entry into the danger zone.</p>

<p>The sea was like glass--melted; blue green with a dull red glow in it:
the air seemed to have been boiled. Officers and men gave me the "feel"
of being "for it" though over serious for British soldiers who always,
in my previous experience, have been extraordinarily animated and gay
when they are advancing "on a Koppje day." These new men seem subdued
when I recall the blaze of enthusiasm in which the old lot started out
of <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location> harbour on that April afternoon.</p>

<p>The _moral_ of troops about to enter into battle supplies a splendid
field of research for students of the human soul, for then the blind
wall set in everyday intercourse between Commander and commanded seems
to become brittle as crystal and as transparent. Only for a few
moments--last moments for so many? But, during those moments, the
gesture of the General means so much--it strikes the attitude of his
troops. It is up to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and Hammersley to make those gestures.
<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> was not there, and is not the type; Hammersley is not that type
either. How true it is that age, experience, wisdom count for less than
youth, magnetism and love of danger when inexperience has to be
heartened for the struggle.</p>

<p>Strolled back slowly along the beach, and, at 8.30, in the gathering
dusk, saw the whole flotilla glide away and disappear ghostlike to the
Northwards. The empty harbour frightens me. Nothing in legend stranger
or more terrible than the silent departure of this silent Army, <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s new
Corps, every mother's son of them, face to face with their fate.</p>

<p>But it will never do to begin the night's vigil in this low key. Capital
news from the aeroplanes. Samson has sent in photographs taken
yesterday, showing the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay area. Not more than 100 to 150 yards
of trenches in all; half a dozen gun emplacements and, the attached
report adds, no Turks anywhere on the move.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_7th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Sitting in my hut after a night in the G.S.
tent. One A.D.C. remains over there. As the cables come in he runs
across with them. Freddie <person name="Freddie_Maitland">Maitland</person> runs fast. I am watching to see his
helmet top the ridge of sand that lies between. The <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit> has got
ashore; some scrapping along the beaches but no wire or hold-up like
there was at Sedd-el-Bahr: that in itself is worth fifty million golden
sovereigns. The surprise has come off!</p>

<p>I'd sooner storm a hundred bloody trenches than dangle at the end of
this wire. But now, thank God, the deadliest of the perils is past. The
New Army are fairly ashore. That worst horror of searchlights and of the
new troops being machine gunned in their boats has lifted its dark
shadow.</p>

<p>At Anzac, the most formidable entrenchment of the Turks, "Lone Pine,"
was stormed yesterday evening by the Australian 1st Brigade; a desperate
fine feat. At midnight Birdie cabled, "All going on well on right where
men confident of repelling counter-attack now evidently being prepared:
on left have taken Old No. 3 Post and first ridge of Walden Point,
capturing machine gun: progress satisfactory, though appallingly
difficult: casualties uncertain but on right about 100 killed; 400
wounded."</p>

<p>At <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> a temporary success was scored, but, during the early part of
the night, counter-attacks have brought us back to "as you were."
Fighting is going on and we ought to be pinning the enemy to the South
which is the main thing.</p>

<p>From <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> we have no direct news since the "All landings successful"
cable but we have the repetition of a wireless from G.H.Q. IXth Corps to
the Vice-Admiral at 7.58 a.m. saying, "Prisoners captured state no fresh
troops have arrived recently and forces opposed to us appear to be as
estimated by G.H.Q. Apparently one Regiment only was opposed to our
advance on left."</p>

<p>I have caused this cable to be sent to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"4.20 p.m. G.H.Q. to <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit>. Have only received one telegram from
you. Chief glad to hear enemy opposition weakening and knows you will
take advantage of this to push on rapidly. Prisoners state landing a
surprise so take every advantage before you are forestalled."</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_8th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Another night on tenter hooks: great news: a
wireless from a warship to tell us the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> troops are up on the
foothills: two cables from <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>: many messages from Anzac and
<location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>.</p>

<p>"2.12 a.m. IXth Corps to G.H.Q. As far as can be ascertained <unit type="brigade">33rd</unit>
Brigade hold line the sea about 91.I.9 to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> East corner[2] of Salt
Lake to <location hill="Lala_Baba">Lala Baba</location> inclusive. North of Salt Lake 31st and <unit type="brigade">32nd</unit> Brigade
extended East of Asmak 117.U. preparatory. <unit type="brigade">34th</unit> Brigade advancing having
followed retreating enemy towards line diagonally across 117.X. and
117.D. One battalion latter Brigade occupy high ground about square
135.X."</p>

<p>"5.10 a.m. IXth Corps to G.H.Q. <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location> is in our hands. No
further information."</p>

<p>Awful work at Lone Pine. Desperate counter-attacks by enemy, but now
Birdie thinks we are there to stay. Bulk of Turkish reserves engaged
there whilst <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person>'s New Zealanders and the new <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit> under
Shaw are well up the heights and have carried <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location>. Koja Chemen
Tepe not yet; but <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location> will do: with that, we win!</p>

<p>At <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> we have pushed out again and the <unit type="brigade">East Lancs</unit> Division have
gallantly stormed the Vineyard which they hold. The Turks are making
mighty counter-attacks but their columns have been cut to pieces by the
thin lines of the <unit type="brigade">Lancashire Fusiliers</unit>. Neither from <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> nor from the
Southern area of Anzac are the enemy likely to spare men to reinforce
Sari Bair or <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>.</p>

<p>At 11.30 I ordered the _Arno_ for mid-day sharp. Then happened one of
those aquatic incidents which lend an atmosphere all their own to
amphibious war. Rear-Admiral Nicholson, in local naval command here, had
ordered the _Arno_ to fill up her boilers. Some hitch arose, some d--d
amphibious hitch. Thereupon, without telling me, he ordered the
Commander of the _Arno_ to draw fires, so that, when my signal was sent,
a reply came from the Rear-Admiral saying he was sorry I should be
inconvenienced, but he thought it best to order the fires to be drawn;
otherwise the boilers might have suffered. When, at a crisis, a boiler
walks into the middle of his calculations, a soldier is simply--boiled!
I could not altogether master my irritation, and I wrote out a reply
saying this was not a question of convenience or inconvenience but one
of preventing a Commander-in-Chief from exercising his functions during
battle. I sent the signal down to the signal tent and about an hour
later <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> came over and said he had taken it upon himself to
tone it down.[3] Just as well, perhaps, but here I was, marooned upon an
island!</p>

<p>No other ship could be signalled. As a rule there was a destroyer on
patrol about <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> which could be called up by wireless, but to-day
there was no getting hold of it. I began to be afraid we should not get
away till dark when, at about 3.30 p.m. Nicholson signalled that the
_Triad_ was sailing for <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> at 4.15 p.m., and would I care to go in
her, the _Arno_ following after she had watered. We were off like a
shot, young Brodrick, Captain Anstey and myself for <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>
remained to carry on with Anzac and <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>. The moment I quit my post I
drop out and he takes up the reins. His hands are capable--fortunately!
To-day's cables before I left were right from <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>; splendid from
Anzac and nothing further from <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>.[4]</p>

<p>As we sailed in, that bay, always till now so preternaturally deserted
and silent, was alive and bustling with ships and small craft. A launch
came along from the _<location ship="H.M.S._Chatham">Chatham</location>_ and I jumped in whilst we were still going
pretty fast and shot off to see <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>. He seemed to think things
naval were going pretty well and that Rear-Admiral Christian had been
coping quite well with his share, but suggested that, as he was under a
severe strain, I had better leave him alone. As to the soldiers' show,
he said what Turks were on the ground, and there weren't many, had been
well beaten--but--but--_but_; and all I could get him to say was that
although he was well aware the fighting at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> and Anzac demanded my
closest attention; still, that was in practised hands and he had felt
bound to wireless to beg me to come up to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> and see things for
myself.</p>

<p>Roger <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person> said then that the landings had come off, on the whole, A.1.
Our G.H.Q. idea, which the Navy had shared, that the whole of the troops
should be landed South of <location hill="Lala_Baba">Lala Baba</location> had been sound. The <unit type="brigade">33rd</unit> Brigade had
landed there without shot fired; the <unit type="brigade">32nd</unit> had been sharply, but not
very seriously opposed; the Brigade (the <unit type="brigade">34th</unit>) which we, to meet the
wish of the Corps, had tried to land for them opposite Hill 10 inside
the Bay, instead of with the others as we had originally arranged, had
only been able to find depth at the mouth of the Salt Lake; had suffered
loss from rifle fire and had been thrown into disorder by the grounding
of some lighters. The long wade through the water and mud had upset the
cohesion of the Brigade.</p>

<p><person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person> now turned up. He was in a fever; said our chances were being
thrown away with both hands and that he had already cabled me strongly
to that effect. Neither the Admiral's message nor <person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person>'s had reached
me.[5]</p>

<p>Not another moment was to be lost, so <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person> took us both in his motor
boat to H.M.S. _Jonquil_ to see <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>. He (<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>) seemed happy and
said that everything was quite all right and going well. Mahon with some
of his troops was pressing back the Turks along Kiretch Tepe Sirt. There
had been a very stiff fight in the darkness at <location hill="Lala_Baba">Lala Baba</location> and next
morning the Turks had fought so hard on a little mound called Hill 10
that he (<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>) had been afraid we were not going to be able to take
it at all. However, it had been taken, but there was great confusion and
hours of delay in deploying for the attack of the foothills. They were
easily carried in the end but by that time the men were so thirsty and
tired that they did not follow up the beaten enemy.</p>

<p>"And where are they now?" I asked.</p>

<p>"There," he replied, "along the foot of the hills," and he pointed out
the line, north to south.</p>

<p>"But they held that line, more or less, yesterday," I said.</p>

<p>"Yes," said <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>, and he went on to explain that the Brigadiers had
been called upon to gain what ground they could without serious fighting
but that, actually, they had not yet occupied any dominating tactical
point. The men had been very tired; he had not been able to get water up
to them or land his guns as quickly as he had hoped. Therefore, he had
decided to postpone the occupation of the ridge (which might lead to a
regular battle) until next morning.</p>

<p>"A regular battle is just exactly what we are here for" was what I was
inclined to say, but what I did say was that most of this was news to
me; that he should have instantly informed me of his decision that he
could not obey my cabled order of yesterday afternoon to "push on
rapidly." <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> replied that he had only made up his mind within the
past hour or so; that he had just got back from the shore and was going
to send me a full message when I arrived.</p>

<p>Now, what was to be done? The Turks were so quiet it seemed to me
certain they must have taken the knock-out. All along the beaches, and
inland too, no end of our men were on the move, offering fine targets.
The artillery which had so long annoyed Anzac used to fire from behind
<location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location>; i.e., within point blank range of where our men were
now strolling about in crowds. Yet not a single shell was being fired.
Either, the enemy's guns had been run back over the main ridge to save
them; or, the garrison of <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> was so weak and shaken that
they were avoiding any move which might precipitate a conflict.</p>

<p>I said to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>, "We must occupy the heights at once. It is
imperative we get <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> and <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location> _now_!" To this he
raised objections. He doubted whether the troops had got their water
yet; he and Reed were agreed we ought to get more guns ashore; the
combination of naval and military artillery was being worked out for the
morning; orders would all have to be re-written. He added that, whilst
agreeing with me on principle as to the necessity for pushing on, there
were many tactical reasons against it, especially the attitude of his
Generals who had told him their men were too tired. I thought to myself
of the many, many times Lord <person name="Lord_Bobs">Bobs</person>, French, every leader of note has had
to fight that same _non possumus_; of the old days when half the victory
lay in the moral effort which could impel men half dead with hunger,
thirst and sleeplessness to push along. A cruel, pitiless business, but
so is war itself. Was it not the greatest of soldiers who said his
Marshals could always find ten good reasons for putting off an attack
till next day!</p>

<p>So I said I would like to see the G.O.C. Division and the Brigadiers
personally so as to get a better grip of things than we could on board
ship in harbour. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> agreed; nothing, he said, would please him
more than if I could succeed where he had failed, but would I excuse him
from accompanying me; he had not been very fit; he had just returned
from a visit to the shore and he wanted to give his leg a chance. He
pointed out Hammersley's Headquarters about 400 yards off and said he,
Hammersley, would be able to direct me to the Brigades.</p>

<p>So I nipped down the _Jonquil's_ ladder; tumbled into Roger <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>'
racing motor boat and with him and <person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person> we simply shot across the
water to <location hill="Lala_Baba">Lala Baba</location>. Every moment was priceless. I had not been five
minutes on the _Jonquil_ and in another two I was with Hammersley.</p>

<p>Under the low cliffs by the sea was a small half-moon of beach about 100
by 40 yards. At the North end of the half-moon was Hammersley. Asked to
give me an idea of the situation he gave me much the same story as
<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>. The 9th West Yorks and 6th Yorks had done A.1 storming Lala
Baba in the dark. There had been marching and counter-marching in the
move on Hill 10. The Brigadier had not been able to get a grip of his
Battalions to throw them at it in proper unison and form. A delay of
precious hours had been caused in the attack on <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location> by a
Brigadier who wanted to go forward finding himself at cross purposes
with a Brigadier who thought it better to hold back. At present all was
peaceful and he expected a Staff Officer at any moment with a sketch
showing the exact disposition of his troops. He could not, he feared,
point me out the Brigade Headquarters on the ground. The general line
held followed the under features of the hills.</p>

<p>Malcolm, G.S.O.1, was then called and came up from the far end of the
little beach. He was in the act of fixing up orders for next morning's
attack. I told both Officers that there had never been a greater crisis
in any battle than the one taking place as we spoke. They were naturally
pleased at having got ashore and to have defeated the Turks on the
shore, but they must not fly away with the idea that with time and
patience everything would pan out very nicely. On the contrary, it was
imperative, absolutely imperative, we should occupy the heights before
the enemy brought back the guns they had carried off and before they
received the reinforcements which were marching at that very moment to
their aid. This was no guess: it _was_ so: our aeroplanes had spotted
Turks marching upon us from the North. We might be too late now; anyway
our margin was of the narrowest.</p>

<p>Hammersley assured me that sheer thirst, and the exhaustion of the
troops owing to thirst, had been the only reason why he had not walked
on to <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> last night. After <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location> had been
carried, there was nothing to prevent the occupation of the heights as
the Turks had been beat, but no one could fight against thirst.</p>

<p>I asked him how the water question stood. He said it had been solved by
the landing of more mules; there was no longer any serious supply
trouble. All the troops were now watered, fed and rested. They had been
told they should gain as much ground as they could without committing
themselves to a general action, but they had not, in fact, made much
progress. Thereupon, I pressed again my view that the Division should
get on to the ridge forthwith. Let the Brigade-Majors, I said, pick out
a few of their freshest companies and get on to the crest right now.
Hammersley still clung to the view that he could not get any of his
troops under weigh before daylight next morning. The units were
scattered; no reconnaissance had been made of the ground to their front;
that ground was jungly and blind; it would be impossible to get orders
round the whole Division in time to let the junior ranks study them.
Hammersley's points were made in a proper and soldierly manner. Every
General of experience would be with him in each of them, but there was
one huge danger rapidly approaching us; already casting its shadow upon
us, which, to me as Commander-in-Chief, outweighed every secondary
objection. We might have the hills at the cost of walking up them
to-day; the Lord only knew what would be the price of them to-morrow.
<location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> and Anzac were both holding the Turks to their own front, but
from Asia and Bulair the enemy were on the march. Once our troops dug
themselves in on the crest no number of Turks would be able to shift
them. But; if the Turks got there first? If, as Colonel Malcolm said, it
was impossible to get orders round the Division in time,--a surprising
statement--was there no body of troops--no Divisional reserve--no
nothing--which could be used for the purpose of marching a couple of
miles? Seemingly, there was no reserve! Never, in all my long soldiering
had I been faced with ideas like these. I have seen attack orders
dictated to a Division from the saddle in less than five minutes. Here
was a victorious Division, rested and watered, said to be unable to
bestir itself, even feebly, with less than twelve hours' notice! This
was what I felt and although I did not say it probably I looked it, for
Malcolm now qualified the original _non possumus_ by saying that
although the Irish and the <unit type="brigade">33rd</unit> and <unit type="brigade">34th</unit> Brigades could not be set in
motion before daylight, the <unit type="brigade">32nd</unit> Brigade, which was concentrated round
about Sulajik, would be ready to move at short notice.</p>

<p>The moment had now come for making up my mind. I did so, and told
Hammersley in the most distinct terms that I wished this Brigade to
advance _at once and dig themselves in on the crestline_.[6] If the
Brigade could fix themselves upon the heights overlooking <location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location>
they would make the morning advance easy for their comrades and would be
able to interfere with and delay the Turkish reinforcements which might
try and debouch between the two Anafartas during the night or march down
upon <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> from the North. Viewed from the sea or studied in a map there
might be some question of this hill, or that hill, but, on the ground it
was clear to half an eye that <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location> was the key to the whole <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>
Bay area. If by dawn, I said, even one Company of ours was well
entrenched on the <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location> height we should have the whip hand of the
enemy in the opening moves next morning.</p>

<p>Hammersley said he understood my order and that the advance should be
put in hand at once. Malcolm hurried off; I left a little before 6.30
and went, _via_ the _<location ship="H.M.S._Chatham">Chatham</location>_, back to the _Triad_. The _Arno_ had by
now come in, but <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> has kindly asked me not to shift quarters if
Anzac and <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> troubles will permit me to stay the night at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>.</p>

<p>All was dead quiet ashore till 11 p.m. I was on the bridge until then
and, seeing and hearing nothing, felt sure the Brigade had made good
<location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location> and were now digging themselves in.</p>

<p>Captain Brody dined. The scraps of news picked up from the sailormen,
mainly by young Brodrick, confirm what the soldiers had told us about
the landing inside <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay along the narrow strip of land West of the
Salt Lake. The attacks on Hill 10 went to pieces, not against the Turks,
but by mishap. The first assault made by one or two Companies succeeded,
but the assailants were taken for Turks and were attacked in turn and
driven off by others of our men. A most distressing affair.</p>

<p>If there was hesitation and mix-up in the general handling, the
Regimental folk atoned and there were many incidents of initiative and
daring on the part of battalions and companies.</p>

<p>Mahon with some of his Irish and a Manchester Battalion are fighting
well and clearing Kiretch Tepe Sirt. Until this morning bullets from
that ridge were falling on "A" Beach; now the working parties are not in
any way disturbed.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_9th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> With the first streak of dawn I was up on
the bridge with my glasses. The hills are so covered with scrub that it
was hard to see what was going on in that uncertain light, but the
heavyish shrapnel fire was a bad sign and the fact that the enemy's guns
were firing from a knoll a few hundred yards East of <location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location> was
proof that our troops were not holding <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location>. But the Officer of
the Watch said that the small hours passed quietly; no firing ashore
during the hours of darkness. Could not make head or tail of it!</p>

<p>As the light grew stronger some of ours could be seen pushing up the
western slopes of the long spur running out South-west from Anafarta.
The scrub was so thick that they had to climb together and
follow-my-leader along what appeared to be cattle tracks up the hill. On
our right all seemed going very well. Looking through naval telescopes
we thought--we all thought--<location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> height was won. Very soon
the shrapnel got on to those bunches of men on our left and there was
something like a stampede from North to South. Looking closer we could
see the enemy advancing behind their own bursting shrapnel and rolling
up our line from the left on to the centre. Oh for the good "Queen
Bess," her high command, and her 15-inch shrapnel! One broadside and
these Turks would go scampering down to Gehenna. The enemy
counter-attack was coming from the direction of <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location> and moving
over the foothills and plain on Sulajik. Our centre made a convulsive
effort (so it seemed) to throw back the steadily advancing Turks; three
or four companies (they looked like) moved out from the brush about
Sulajik and tried to deploy. But the shrapnel got on to these fellows
also and I lost sight of them. Then about 6 a.m., the whole lot seemed
suddenly to collapse:--including the right! Not only did they give
ground but they came back--some of them--half-way to the sea. But others
made a stand. The musketry fire got very heavy. The enemy were making a
supreme effort. The Turkish shell fire grew hotter and hotter. The
enemy's guns seemed now to be firing not only from round about Anafarta
Sagir, but also from somewhere between 113 and 101, 2,500 yards or so
South-west of Anafarta. Still these fellows of ours; not more than a
quarter of those on the ground at the outset--stuck it out. My heart
has grown tough amidst the struggles of the Peninsula but the misery of
this scene well nigh broke it. What kept me going was the sight of Sari
Bair--I could not keep my eyes off the Sari Bair ridge. Guns from all
sides, sea and land, Turks and British, were turned on to it and
enormous explosions were sending slices off the top of the high mountain
to mix with the clouds in the sky. Under that canopy our men were
fighting for dear life far above us!</p>

<p>Between 7.30 and 8.0 the Turkish reinforcements at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> seemed to have
got enough. They did not appear to be in any great strength: here and
there they fell back: no more came up in support: evidently, they were
being held: failure, not disaster, was the upshot: few things so bad
they might not be worse. By 8.0 the musketry and the shelling began to
slacken down although there was a good deal of desultory shooting. We
were holding our own; the <unit type="division">Welsh</unit> Division are coming in this morning; but
we have not sweated blood only to hold our own; our occupation of the
open key positions has been just too late! The element of
surprise--wasted! The prime factor set aside for the sake of other
factors! Words are no use.</p>

<p>Looked at from the bridge of the _Triad_--not a bad observation
station--the tendency of our men to get into little groups was very
noticeable: as if they had not been trained in working under fire in the
open. As to the general form of our attack against the hills on our
right, it seemed to be what our French Allies call _dcousu_. After a
whole day's rest and preparing, there might have been more form and
shape about the movement. Yet it was for the sake of this form and shape
that the Turkish reinforcements have been given time to get on to the
heights. Our stratagems worked well, but there is a time limit set to
all make-believes; the hour glass of fate was set at forty-eight hours,
and now the sands have run out.</p>

<p>Before going over to Anzac I had to get hold of <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> so as to hear
what news had come in from Hammersley and from Mahon. If only Mahon is
pushing forward to <location bay="Ejelmer_Bay">Ejelmer</location> Bay and can occupy the high range to the East
of it that would make amends for much. After breakfast, therefore, at
8.30 got into a launch and landed at Ghazi Baba with young Brodrick as
my only companion. Our boat took us into a deep, narrow creek cut by
nature into the sheer rock just by Ghazi Baba--a name only; there is
nothing to distinguish that spot from any other. Along the beach
feverish activity; stores, water, ammunition, all the wants of an army
being landed. Walking up the lower slope of Kiretch Tepe Sirt, we found
<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>, about four or five hundred yards East of Ghazi Baba, busy with
part of a Field Company of Engineers supervising the building of some
splinter-proof Headquarters huts for himself and Staff. He was absorbed
in the work, and he said that it would be well to make a thorough good
job of the dug-outs as we should probably be here for a very long time.
I retorted, "Devil a bit; within a day or two you will be picking the
best of the Anafarta houses for your billet."</p>

<p>From the spot he had selected the whole of <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay and the Salt Lake
lay open; also the Anafartas and <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location>. But, being on a lower
spur of Kiretch Tepe Sirt, his post was "dead" to the fighting taking
place along the crest of Kiretch Tepe Sirt itself. I remarked on this
and asked what news of the Irish, saying that now we were certainly
forestalled at <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location> and, apparently, on <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location> also, it was
doubly essential Mahon should make a clean sweep of the ridge. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>
said he was confident he would be able to do so, aided as he would be by
the fire from the ships in the harbour--a fire which enfiladed the whole
length of this feature.</p>

<p>As to this morning's hold up, <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> took it philosophically, which
was well so far as it went, but he seemed hardly to realize that the
Turks have rushed their guns and reinforcements here from a very long
way off whilst he has been creeping along at the rate of a mile a day.
<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> expected Hammersley would be in to report progress in person;
he will keep me well posted in his news and he understands that the
<unit type="division">Welsh</unit> Division will be at his disposal to help the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit>.</p>

<p>As <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> could give me no recent news from Mahon I suggested I should
go and find out from him personally how matters then stood. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>
said it was a good idea but that he himself thought it better not to
leave his Headquarters where messages kept coming in. I agreed and
started with George Brodrick to scale the hill.</p>

<p>About half a mile up we struck a crowd of the Irish Pioneer Regiment
(Granard's) filling their water bottles at a well marked on the map as
Charak Cheshme. In their company we now made our way Northwards along a
path through fairly thick scrub as high as a man's waist. We were moving
parallel to, and about 300 yards below, the crestline of the ridge. When
we had gone another mile a spattering of "overs" began to fall around
like the first heavy drops of a thunderstorm. So wrapped in cotton wool
is a now-a-days Commander-in-Chief that this was the first musketry fire
I could claim to have come under since the beginning of the war. To sit
in a trench and hear flights of bullets flop into the sandbag parapet,
or pass harmlessly overhead, is hardly to be under fire. An irregular
stream of Irishmen were walking up the path along with us; one of them
was hit just ahead of me. He caught it in the thigh and stretcher men
whipped him off in a jiffy. At last we got to a spot some 2-1/2 miles
from <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> and had not yet been able to find Mahon. So I sat down behind
a stone, somewhere about the letter "K" of Kiretch Tepe Sirt, and sent
young Brodrick to espy the land. He found that we had pulled up within a
couple of hundred yards of the Brigade Headquarters, where portions of
the 30th, 31st and <unit type="brigade">34th</unit> Brigades (sounds very formidable but only five
Battalions) were holding a spur and preparing to make an attack. General
Mahon was actually in the Brigade Headquarters (a tiny ditch which only
held four or five people) and came back to where I was sitting. He is
angry, and small wonder, at the chaos introduced somehow into the Corps.
He is commanding some of Hammersley's men and Hammersley has the bulk of
his at the far extremity of the line of battle. He besought me to do my
utmost to get Hill and his troops back to their own command.</p>

<p>I told him G.H.Q. had always understood <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> would land his,
Mahon's, two Brigades intact at A Beach. When the naval people could not
find a beach at A, they, presumably with <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>'s concurrence, had
most unluckily dumped them ashore several miles South at C Beach. This
was the cause of the mix-up of his Division which <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>, no doubt,
would take in hand as soon as he could. Mahon seemed in fighting form.
He said he could clear the whole of Kiretch Tepe Sirt, but that he did
not want to lose men in making frontal attacks, so he was trying to work
round South through the thick scrub so as to shift the enemy that way.
He had reckoned five or six hundred men were against him--gendarmes. But
there were more than there had been at daylight. My talk with Mahon made
me happier. Here, at least, was someone who had an idea of what he was
doing. The main thing was to attack before more Turks came down the
coast. My own idea would certainly have been to knock the Turks out by a
bayonet charge--right there. So far they had not had time to dig a
regular trench, only a few shallow scrapings along a natural fold of the
ground. If Mahon wished to make a turning movement, then, I think, he
would have been well advised to take it by the North where the ground
over which he must advance was not only unentrenched and clear of brush,
but also laid quite open to the supporting fire of the Fleet. But I kept
these views to myself until I could see <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>; said good-bye to Mahon
and wished him luck; found Brodrick had wandered off on his own to see
the fun at close quarters; legged it, all alone, down the open southern
slope of the Kiretch Tepe Sirt and got down into ground less open to
snipers' fire from the scrub-covered plain.[7] Then, still quite alone,
I made my way back South-west towards Ghazi Baba on <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay. After a
little I was joined by two young Irish soldiers. I don't know who or
what they took me for; certainly not for the Generalissimo. They came
along with me and discussed identical adventures from diametrically
different standpoints. One, in fact, was an optimist; the other a
pessimist. One found fault with the war for not giving him enough
hardship and adventure; the other was entirely fed up with adventures
and hardships. This seems a trivial incident to jot down amidst issues
so tremendous, but life is life, and my chat with these youngsters put
some new life into me. Nearing the shore, I again struck <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>'s
Headquarters, now beginning to look habitable. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, and one or
two others of my Staff turned up from <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> at that moment. He shoved
some cables into my hand and hastened off to interview Reed. <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> and
Anzac have been duly warned we are both here for a few hours; all the
component parts of my machine, its cranks, levers, pulleys, are
assembled at <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location>, and G.H.Q. simply cannot be left under a junior
much longer. Meanwhile I told <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> about Mahon and the gendarmes.
When I said that the sooner the Kiretch Tepe nettle was grasped the less
it would sting, he informed me he had issued an order that Commanders
were not to lose men by making frontal attacks on trenches but were to
turn them.</p>

<p>So here is a theory which South African practice proved to be more often
wrong than right being treated as an axiom at <location peninsula="Gallipoli">Gallipoli</location>!</p>

<p>We next went into the question of digging a defensive line of trenches
half-way between Corps Headquarters and Mahon's force. Here we were in
accord. No man knows his luck and the tide may turn any moment. Both at
Liao-Yang and the Shaho the Japanese began to dig deep trenches directly
they captured a position.</p>

<p>Young Brodrick rejoined me here; rather anxious at having lost me. He
had found Mahon with the Brigade Staff. He had been shown the exact
positions on a rough sketch map made by one of the Officers. We had
three Battalions in the firing line and two in reserve. The gendarmerie
had been reinforced and were now estimated at 700 without machine guns
or artillery. We had a mountain battery shelling the gendarmes and a
monitor occasionally gave them a big fellow. The Brigade Staff had said
nothing to him about a battalion working round to the South. I repeated
this to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and begged him to make a push for it here.</p>

<p>By now <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> had finished with Reed, so we hurriedly discussed his
budget of news. Hammersley is expected but he has not turned up yet.
Indeed the situation is still by no means free from anxiety although the
arrival of the <unit type="division">Welsh</unit> Division gives confidence. A battalion of the <unit type="brigade">32nd</unit>
Brigade did get up on to <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location> last night, it seems, but were
knocked off this morning before they had time to entrench.[8] Seeing
they should have had several hours time to dig in, that seems strange.
<person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> handed me a bunch of signals and wires; also the news of
what I had known at the back of my mind since morning,--the fact that we
had not got Sari Bair! Then we started back to see <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> and <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>.
For the first time in this expedition Roger <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person> seemed down on his
luck: we had often before seen him raging, never dejected. These awful
delays:--delay in landing the Irish; delay in attacking on the 7th;
delay all night of the 7th; delay during the day of the 8th and night of
the 8th, have simply deprived him of the power of speech,--to soldiers,
that is to say, though, to shipmates, no doubt...!</p>

<p>Now for Anzac. Since dawn a fever about Anzac had held me. Shades of
Staff College Professors, from you no forgiveness to a Chief who runs
about the mountain quitting his central post. But the luminous shade of
Napoleon would better understand my desperation. Some Generals are just
accumulators of the will of the C.-in-C. When that is the case, and when
they run down, there is only one man who can hope to pump in energy.</p>

<p>Exact at noon Roger <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person> and I pushed off in the racing motor boat. On
our way we stopped at "C" beach and picked up Commander Worsley. Next to
Anzac, but at the Cove, found that <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> had left word he would meet
me at the ex-Turkish Post No. 2,--so, as the water was shoal in spots,
we rowed down there in a dinghy, along the shore where our lives would
not have been worth half a minute's purchase just three days ago.</p>

<p>After scrambling awhile over the new trenches, <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person>, <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> and I
sat down on a high spur above <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person>'s Headquarters which gave us a
grand outlook over the whole <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> area, and across to <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location>. Here
we ate our rations and held an impromptu council of war; Shaw,
commanding the new <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit>, joining in with us. All three Generals
were in high spirits and refused to allow themselves to be damped down
by the repulse of the morning's attack on the high ridge. They put down
that check to the lethargy of <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>. Had <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> taken up any point on
the watershed yesterday when it was unoccupied except by some fugitives,
the whole Turkish position on the Peninsula would have become so
critical that they could not have spared the numbers they have now
brought up to defend "Q" and Koja Chemen Tepe. The Anzac Generals
allowed that they themselves had got into arrears in their time tables,
but they had been swift compared to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>.</p>

<p>Even as <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> was holding forth, messages came to hand to say that the
Turks were passing from the defensive to the offensive and urging fresh
attacks on the New Zealanders holding <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location>. <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> is certain the
Turks will never make us quit hold. Shaw, who also has some of his men
up there, is equally confident. <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> thinks <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location> should be
safe, though not so safe as it would have been had we held on to that
ridge at "Q" where Baldwin's delay from causes not yet known, lost us
the crestline this morning. Birdie said he could have cried, and is not
quite sure he didn't cry, when the bombardment stopped dead and minute
after minute passed away, from one minute to twenty, without a sign
of Baldwin and his column who had been booked to spurt for the top on
the heels of the last shell. Unaided, the 6th Gurkhas got well astride
the ridge, but had to fall back owing to the lack of his support. None
the less, these Anzac Generals are in great form. They are sure they
will have the whip hand of the Narrows by to-morrow.</p>

<p>Birdie was offered my last reserves, the <unit type="division">54th</unit> Essex Territorials under
Inglefield. But he can't water them. The effort to carry food, water and
cartridges to the firing lines is already overtaxing the Corps. If
Inglefield's men were also pushed in they simply could not be kept
going. When communication trenches have been dug and brushwood and rocks
flattened out, it will be easier. Till then, the Generals agreed they
would rather the extra pressure was applied from <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>. <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> and
<person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> were keen, in fact, that the Essex Division should go to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>
so that he might at once occupy <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> and, if he could, <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location>.
All that the Anzacs have seen for themselves, or heard from their own
extreme left or from aeroplanes, leads them to believe that the Turkish
reinforcements to the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> theatre came over the high shoulder of Tekke
Tepe or through <location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location> about dawn this morning and that the
enemy are in some strength now along the ridge between <location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location>
and <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> with a few hundred on Kiretch Tepe Sirt: the
Turkish centre was a gift to us yesterday; certainly yesterday forenoon;
now it can only be won by hard fighting. But the Turks have not yet had
time to work round on to the high ridges east of <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay and although
a few Turks did pass over <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location>, it seems to be now clear of any
enemy. There is no sign of life on the bare Eastern slope of that
mountain. Probably one half of the great crescent of hills which
encircles the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> plain and, in places, should overlook the Narrows,
still lies open to an advance.</p>

<p>So together we composed a message to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> sent it off by
telephone--now rigged up between the two Corps Headquarters: the form
was filled in by <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person>; hence his counter signature:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>  TO:--G.O.C., IXth Corps.</p>

<p>  Sender's number. Day of month.  In reply to
  N.Z.G. 103            9         number AAA</p>

<p>  After speaking to <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> and <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person>
  think most important use fresh troops could
  be put to if not urgently required to reinforce
  would be the occupation as early as possible
  of the commanding position running through
  square 137-119 AAA <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> are
  less vital to security of base.
                          SIR IAN HAMILTON.</p>

<p>  _From_
  _Place_ Fisherman's Hut.
  _Date_ 2 p.m. 9th August, 1915.</p>

<p>                              A. J. GODLEY,
                                  Maj. Gen.</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>Took leave of the Anzacs and the Anzac Generals about 4.30 p.m. The
whole crowd were in tip-top spirits and immensely pleased with the
freedom and largeness of their newly conquered kingdom. We of the G.H.Q.
were bitten by this same spirit; <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> took second place in our minds
and when we got on board the _Arno_ the ugly events of the early morning
had been shaken, for the moment, out of our minds. But, on the sail
home, we were able to look at the Peninsula as a whole. Because the
Anzacs, plus the <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit> of the New Army, had carried through a
brilliant stroke of arms was a reason, not for shutting our eyes to the
slowness of the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Generals, but for spurring them on to do likewise.
There is nothing open to them now--not without efforts for which they
are, for the time being, unfit--but <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> and the Aja Liman
Anafarta ridge. So, on arrival at 6 p.m., wrote out the following
message from myself to General <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"I am in complete sympathy with you in the matter of all your Officers
and men being new to this style of warfare and without any leaven of
experienced troops on which to form themselves. Still I should be wrong
if I did not express my concern at the want of energy and push displayed
by the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit>. It cannot all be want of experience as 13th have
shown dash and self-confidence. Turks were almost negligible yesterday
once you got ashore. To-day there was nothing to stop determined
commanders leading such fine men as yours. Tell me what is wrong with
the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit>. Is it the Divisional Generals or Brigadiers or both?
I have a first-rate Major General I can send at once and can also supply
two competent Brigadiers. You must get a move on or the whole plan of
operations is in danger of failing, for if you don't secure the AJA
LIMAN ANAFARTA ridge without delay the enemy will. You must use your
personal influence to insist on vigorous and sustained action against
the weak forces of the Turks in your front, and while agreeing to the
capture of W Hills and spur mentioned in C.G.S. letter to you of to-day,
it is of vital importance to the whole operation that you thereafter
promptly take steps to secure the ridge without possession of which
SUVLA BAY is not safe. You must face casualties and strike while the
opportunity offers and remember the AJA LIMAN ANAFARTA ridge is your
principal and dominant objective and it must be captured. Every day's
delay in its capture will enormously multiply your casualties. I want
the name of the Brigadier who sent the message to say his left was
retiring owing to a strong attack and then subsequently reported that
the attack in question has never developed. Keep <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> informed as he
may be able to help you on your right flank."</p>

<p>This message seemed so important that it was sent by hand of
Hore-Ruthven and another Officer by special destroyer. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> tells
me that, when he was at <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit> Headquarters to-day he showed General
<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> the last two paragraphs of this memo which I had written when
toning down the wording of a General Staff draft:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"C.G.S.</p>

<p>"(1) I do not think much good rubbing it into these fellows, there are
very few Turks opposed to them. We have done it, and that was right, but
we must not overdo it.</p>

<p>"(2) But the men ought to be made to understand that really the whole
result of this campaign may depend on their quickly getting a footing on
the hills right and left of Anafarta. Officers and rank and file must be
made to grasp this.</p>

<p>"(3) If <person name="John_Lindley">Lindley</person> and his new men were kept intact and thrown in on the
Anzac flank, surely they ought to be able to make a lodgment.</p>

<p>                                         (_Initialled_), "IAN H."</p>

<p>FOOTNOTES:</p>

<p>[Footnote 2: Must have meant south-east?--IAN H., 1920.]</p>

<p>[Footnote 3: Long afterwards--long after the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> Commission had
finished their Report--I had the curiosity to get permission to look at
the log of the _Exmouth_ (Rear-Admiral Nicholson) to see how my cable
had been translated. Here it is, very much Bowdlerized:--"Sent 11.45,
received 11.59. Sir I. Hamilton to Rear-Admiral 3. Urgent. 'Understand
_Arno_ drawing fires. Can this be stopped and _Arno_ sent (to)
_Mercedes_ to water at once? _Arno_ specially put at my disposal by
Vice-Admiral and I may require her at any moment.'" The _Mercedes_ was
the ship with our military drinking water.]</p>

<p>[Footnote 4: There is a hiatus in my diary here which I must try and
bridge over by a footnote especially as my story seems to run off the
rails when I say that "nothing further" had come in from <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>. At 10.50
a.m. a further cable did come in from <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"Approximate position of troops under General Hammersley this morning.
Two battalions <unit type="brigade">33rd</unit> Brigade sea to S.E. corner of Salt Lake: will be
moved forward shortly to connect if possible with Anzac troops. Two
battalions <unit type="brigade">33rd</unit> holding <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location>. Position on Hill 500 yards East
<location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location> not yet certain. From <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location> 31st Brigade holds
line through Baka Baba crossroads, thence North to about 118 0 2. <unit type="brigade">32nd</unit>
and <unit type="brigade">34th</unit> Brigades ordered forward from Hill 10 (117 R) where they spent
night to line 118 M.R.W. to fill gap with Tenth Division. Detailed
information of Tenth Division not yet definite: will report later.
Consider Major-General Hammersley and troops under him deserve great
credit for result attained against strenuous opposition and great
difficulty."</p>

<p>Manifestly, the data in this cable were not enough to enable me to form
any opinion of my own as to the credit due to anyone; but every soldier
will understand that it was up to me to respond:</p>

<p>  "To G.O.C. <unit type="corps">8th Corps</unit>.</p>

<p>  "From General <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian Hamilton</person>.</p>

<p>"You and your troops have indeed done splendidly. Please tell Hammersley
how much we hope from his able and rapid advance."</p>

<p>I made no written note of this 10.50 a.m. cable (or of my reply to it)
at the time and, eighteen months later, no mental note of it remained,
probably because it had only added some detail to the news received
during the night. But I had reason to regret this afterwards when I came
to read the final Report of the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> Commission, paragraph 89.
There I see it stated that "with regard to this message" (my pat on the
back for Hammersley) "Sir Frederick <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> informed us that the result
of the operations on the night of the 6th and day of the 7th was not as
satisfactory as he would have liked but he gathered from Sir Ian
Hamilton's congratulations that his dispositions and orders had met with
the latter's approval"</p>

<p>As to my actual feelings that forenoon, I do remember them well. At
sunrise victory seemed assured. As morning melted into mid-day my mind
became more and more uneasy at the scant news about the Irish Division
and at the lack of news of a further advance of the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit>. This
growing anxiety drove me to quit my headquarters and to take ship for
<location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>.]</p>

<p>[Footnote 5: The Admiral's wireless had said, so I was told:--"It is
important we should meet--shall I come to Kephalos or are you coming to
<location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>?" As stated in text I did not get this cable at the time nor did I
ever get it. Four years later the signal logs of the only ships through
which the message could have passed; viz., _Triad_, _Exmouth_,
_<location ship="H.M.S._Chatham">Chatham</location>_, were searched and there is no trace of it. So I think it must
have been drafted and overlooked.--IAN H., 1920.</p>

<p><person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person>'s cable:--"Just been ashore where I found all quiet AAA. No
rifle fire, no artillery fire and apparently no Turks AAA. IXth Corps
resting AAA. Feel confident that golden opportunities are being lost and
look upon the situation as serious." I received this next morning from
<person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>.--IAN H., 1920.]</p>

<p>[Footnote 6: Looking to the distance of Sulajik, the Brigade might have
been expected to move in about an hour and a half. But, as I did not
know at the time, or indeed till two years later, this Brigade was _not_
concentrated. Only two battalions were at Sulajik; the other two, the
6th East Yorks and the 9th West Yorks, were in possession of Hill 70,
vide map.--IAN H., 1920.]</p>

<p>[Footnote 7: My Aide-de-Camp, George Brodrick, has permitted me to use
the following extract from a letter of his written to his father, Lord
Midleton, at the time.</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"I went to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> with Sir Ian in the afternoon of August 8th, and we
arrived to find 'Nothing doing.' The beaches and hillsides covered with
our men almost like a Bank Holiday evening at Hampstead Heath. Vague
shelling by one of our monitors was the only thing which broke the peace
of a most perfect evening--a glorious sunset.</p>

<p>"We went over to the Destroyer where General <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> had his
Headquarters, and I fancy words of exhortation were spoken to him. We
slept on the Triad, Admiral <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person>'s Yacht. I had a camp bed on the
Bridge, so as to hear any happenings during the night. About dawn our
Monitors started to shell the heights behind Anafarta and a sort of
assault was made; the Turkish battery opened with shrapnel, and our
fellows did not seem to get very far.</p>

<p>"We went ashore on 'A' beach about 8 a.m. and walked up to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>'s
Headquarters, as he had gone ashore the night before. They all seemed a
very lifeless crew, with but little knowledge of the general situation
and no spirit in them. We made our way on across some rocky scrubby
country towards Brigade Headquarters; fairly heavy rifle fire was going
on, and after about two miles bullets began to ping unpleasantly all
round us. I persuaded Sir Ian to lie down behind a rock, much against
his will, and went on myself another 150 yards to where the Brigade
Staff were sitting in a dip behind a stone wall. They told me that about
800 Turks were in front of them with no machine guns. We had 3
Battalions in the firing line and two in reserve and yet could not get
on."]</p>

<p>[Footnote 8: Only one Company we hear now.--IAN H., 15.8.15.]</p>

</entry>


<chapter n="16">CHAPTER XVI</chapter>

<p>
KAVAK TEPE ATTACK COLLAPSES</p>

<entry><p>_10th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Had to remain at G.H.Q. all day--the worst
of all days. My visit to Anzac yesterday had infected me with the hopes
of <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> and <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> and made me feel that we would recover what we
had missed at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>, and more, if, working from the pivot of Chunuk
Bair, we got hold of the rest of Sari Bair.</p>

<p>They believed they would bring this off and then the victory would have
been definite. Now--<location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location> has gone!</p>

<p>The New Zealand and New Army troops holding the knoll were relieved by
two New Army Battalions and, at daylight this morning, the Turks simply
ran amok among them with a Division in mass formation. Trenches badly
sited, they say, and Turks able to form close by in dead ground. Many
reasons no doubt and lack of swift pressure from <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>. The Turks have
lost their fear of <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and concentrated full force against the
Anzacs. By Birdie's message, it looks as if the heavy fighting was at an
end--an end which leaves us with a fine gain of ground though minus the
vital crests. Next time we will get them. We are close up to the summit
instead of having five or six hundred feet to climb.</p>

<p>News from <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> still rotten. Here is the result of Hammersley's visit
to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> after I left:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>  "August 9.    5.35.    <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay.</p>

<p>  "DEAR BRAITHWAITE,</p>

<p>"I have had a talk with Hammersley and he tells me that his troops are
much exhausted, have had very heavy fighting, severe losses and have
felt the want of water very much. He does not consider that they are fit
to make a fresh attack to-morrow.</p>

<p>"I have decided after consultation with him to make an attempt on the
ridge about Abrikja with three fresh Territorial Battalions and six
which have been used to-day. I am afraid from what I hear that the Naval
guns do not have much effect on account of difficulty of accurate
observation but I will arrange a programme, to be carefully timed, with
Brigadier-General Smith, my Brigadier R.A., and of course all the field
guns will also help. I _must_ see Smith so please ask the V. Admiral to
place a boat at Smith's disposal to bring him here to see me and then to
see Generals Hammersley and <person name="John_Lindley">Lindley</person>. General <person name="John_Lindley">Lindley</person> will be in
immediate command of the operations as all troops engaged in the attack
will be Territorials.</p>

<p>"I trust the attack will succeed though to-day's did not, but in view of
the urgency of the matter I feel the attempt ought to be made.</p>

<p>"It is absolutely necessary that I should see Smith.</p>

<p>                        "Yours sincerely,
                              (_Sd._) "FRED W. STOPFORD."</p>

<p>At mid-day, got a cable from the <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit> saying that <person name="John_Lindley">Lindley</person>'s
Division had duly gone at Hill 70, a key feature on the ridge, about
1,500 yards North-east of <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location>--and had failed!</p>

<p>In giving me this news, <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> proposes to make a second attack this
afternoon with the same Division. Have caused <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> to cable:</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"Hear you propose attacking again. Chief doubts advisability with tired
troops after morning's failure; if you agree consolidate where you are
and rest and reorganize."</p>

<p>In a letter from <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> in answer to my signal of yesterday from
Fisherman's Hut, he says:--</p>

<p>  "No. 1.   _Date_, Aug. 9.   _Time_, 4 p.m.</p>

<p>  _Place_, <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay.</p>

<p>  "To:</p>

<p>  "DEAR SIR IAN,</p>

<p>"I have received your message from Fisherman's Hut. Hammersley has not
been able to advance to-day, but the Turks have been counter-attacking
all day and he has had to put in one of the Territorial Brigades to
prevent being driven back.</p>

<p>"I quite realize the importance of holding the high ground East of <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>
Bay, but as the Turks advance through the gap between the two Anafartas
where all the roads are, it is absolutely necessary to keep sufficient
troops between <location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location> and <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location>, as otherwise if I
were to seize the high ground between <location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location> and <location bay="Ejelmer_Bay">Ejelmer</location> Bay
without securing this gap, I might find myself holding the heights and
the Turks pouring down to the harbour behind me. I will bear what you
say in mind, and if I get an opportunity with fresh troops of taking the
heights whilst holding on tight to my right flank I will do so. I
understand that one reason why it was necessary to go for Ismail Oglu
Tepe was that if I did not hold the Turks there they would fire into the
rear of <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person>'s troops attacking Hill 305.</p>

<p>                              "I am, Sir,
                                  "Yours sincerely,
                               (_Sd._) "FRED W. STOPFORD."</p>

<p>For myself I wish the Turks would try to pour down over that flat, open
country by the Salt Lake to seize the beaches under the guns of the
warships.</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>Well, we had <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location> in our hands the best part of two days and two
nights. So far the Turks have never retaken trenches once we had fairly
taken hold. Have they done so now? I hope not. Birdie and <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> are at
work upon a scheme for its recapture. The Turks are well commanded: that
I admit. Their Generals knew they were done unless they could quickly
knock us off our <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location>. So they have done it. Never mind: never
say die. Meanwhile we have the East Anglian Division available
to-morrow, and I have been over in the G.S. marquee working out ways and
means of taking <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> which may also give us an outlook, more
distant, but yet an outlook, on to the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_11th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Did not dare to break away from the wire
ends. A see-saw of cardinal events between <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> and Anzac.</p>

<p>A workable scheme of attack has now been put into such shape as to let
<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> dovetail his Corps orders into it, and first thing sent him
this cable:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"G.H.Q. to IXth Corps. General Commanding wishes <unit type="division">54th Division</unit> Infantry
to attack line <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> peak 1195.5. at dawn to-morrow after night
march to foothills; G.S.O. proceeding with detailed instructions. See
Inglefield, make arrangements and give all assistance possible by
landing <unit type="division">53rd</unit> Signal Company, water gear and tools. <unit type="division">53rd</unit> Division becomes
general reserve."</p>

<p>At 4.30 p.m., a letter from <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> anent the failure of the <unit type="division">53rd</unit>
Division,--depressing in itself but still more so in its inferences as
to the <unit type="division">54th Division</unit>. He says these troops showed "no attacking spirit
at all. They did not come under heavy shell fire nor was the rifle fire
very severe, but they not only showed no dash in attack but went back at
slight provocation and went back a long way. Lots of the men lay down
behind cover, etc. They went on when called upon to do so by Staff and
other Officers but they seemed lost and under no leadership--in fact,
they showed that they are not fit to put in the field without the help
of Regulars. I really believe that if we had had one Brigade of Regulars
here to set an example both the New Army and Territorials would have
played up well with them but they have no standard to go by."</p>

<p>Worse follows, for <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> takes back his assurance given me after my
cable of the 9th when he said, "given water, guns and ammunition, I have
no doubt about our being able to secure the hills." He tells me straight
and without any beating about the bush, "I am sure they" (the
Territorials) "would not secure the hills with any amount of guns, water
and ammunition assuming ordinary opposition, as the attacking spirit was
absent; chiefly owing to the want of leadership by the Officers."</p>

<p>Ignoring our <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> scheme, he goes on then to ask me in so many
words, not to try any attack with the <unit type="division">54th Division</unit> but to stick them
into trenches.</p>

<p>This letter has driven me very nearly to my wits' ends. Things can't be
so bad! None of us have any complaint at all of the New Army troops;
only of their Old Army Generals. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> says the <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit> were
not reliable when they were at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>, whereas now, under <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> at
Anzac they have fought like lions.</p>

<p>Rushed off in this, the good tub _Imogene_ (Lieutenant-Commander Potts).
There the rushing ceased as she steamed along so slowly that we didn't
get to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> till 7 p.m. Walked up with <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> and Freddie to the
<unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit> Headquarters. Saw <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>. Wrestled with him for over an
hour; <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> doing ditto with Reed.</p>

<p><person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> urged that these last two Territorial formations sent out to us
were sucked oranges, the good in them having been drafted away into
France and replaced by rejections. He says he would have walked on to
the watershed the first day had we only stiffened his force with the
<unit type="division">29th</unit> Division. There happened to be some pretty decisive objections but
there was no use entering into them then. So I merely told him that the
<unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit> and the Territorials being now well ashore we may be able to
bring up the <unit type="division">29th</unit>. No doubt--had we a couple of Regular Divisions
here--British or Indian--at full strength--no doubt we could astonish
the world. Having the <unit type="division">53rd</unit> and the <unit type="division">54th Division</unit>s, half-trained and at
half strength, I tried to make <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> see we must cut our coats with
the stuff issued to us. The <unit type="division">54th</unit> were good last winter, and, even if the
best have been picked out of them, the residue should do well under
sound leadership: Inglefield was a practised old warrior, and would not
let him down.</p>

<p>There was nothing solid to go upon in crying down the credit of the <unit type="division">54th</unit>
beyond hearsay and the self-evident fact that they are half their
nominal strength. To assume they won't put up a fight is a certain way
of making the best troops gun-shy. We are standing up to our necks in a
time problem, and the tide is on the rise. There is not a moment to
spare. The Turks have reinforced and they have brought back their guns;
that is true. Now they will begin to dig trenches--indeed they are
already digging--and more and more enemy troops will be placed in
reserve behind the Anafartas and to the East of the <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location>--<location bay="Ejelmer_Bay">Ejelmer</location>
Bay range. On the 10th the <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> people reported that, in spite of
their efforts to hold the Turks, they had detached reinforcements to the
North. These extra reinforcements may arrive to-morrow at Anzac or on
the Anafartas; but, for at least another twenty four hours, they will
not be able to get round to the high ridge between Anafarta and <location bay="Ejelmer_Bay">Ejelmer</location>
Bay. So far as can be seen by aeroplane scouting, this ridge is still
unoccupied; certainly it is unentrenched.</p>

<p><person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> who, at first, was dead set on digging agreed to have a dart at
<location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location>. He will throw the <unit type="division">54th</unit> at it. He will turn out the <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit>
and, if chance offers, they will attack along their own front. His chief
remaining ghost inhabits the jungly bit of country between <location town="Anafarta_Ova">Anafarta Ova</location>
and the foothills. In that belt he fears the Turkish snipers may harass
our line of supply so that, when the heights are held, we may find it
hard to feed and water our garrison. The New Armies and Territorials
have no trained counter-snipers and are much at the mercy of the skilled
Anatolian shikarris who haunt the close country.</p>

<p>So I suggested blockhouses on the South African system to protect our
line where it passed through the three quarters of a mile or so of close
country. The enemy artillery would not spot them amongst the trees. I
promised him also one hundred picked Australian bushmen, New Zealand
Maoris and Gurkhas to act as scouts and counter-snipers.</p>

<p><person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> took to this idea very kindly; has fixed up a Conference of 9th
Corps and Territorial Generals early to-morrow morning to discuss the
whole plan, and will make every effort to occupy <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> to-morrow
night. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> seemed in much better form to-night; I think he is more
fit: there has been 24 hours' delay but by waiting that time Inglefield
and the Essex will have the help of a body of first-class scouts--quite
a luminous notion. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>, himself, presides at to-morrow's
Conference. Inglefield is a good, straight fellow, not so young as we
were in South Africa, but quite all right.</p>

<p>Boarded the _Imogene_. Dropped anchor at 11 p.m. at <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location>.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_12th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Last thing last night <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> promised to
let me know the result of the conference to be held at his Headquarters,
and upon the plans for the lines of supply. Sent him a reminder:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"G.H.Q. to IXth Corps. Have you arranged practical system for supplying
troops in the event of <location hill="Tekke_Tepe">Tekke Tepe</location> ridge being secured?"</p>

<p>A cable from <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"I am sorry about the Xth and XIth Divisions in which I had great
confidence. Could you not ginger them up? The utmost energy and dash
are required for these operations or they will again revert to trench
warfare."</p>

<p><person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s disappointment makes me feel _sick_! I know the great hopes he has
built on these magnificent Divisions and I know equally well that he is
not capable of understanding how he has cut his own throat, the men's
throats and mine, by not sending young and up-to-date Generals to run
them. <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> in this, and this alone, is with Tolstoi. The men are
everything; the man nothing. Have cabled back saying, "I am acting
absolutely as you indicate by 'ginger'; I only got back at 11 last night
from a further application of that commodity. As a result a fresh attack
will be made to-morrow morning by the IXth Corps and the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit>
Division."</p>

<p>As to the New Army I point out to <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> that "they are fighting under
conditions quite foreign to their training and moreover they have no
regulars to set them a standard": also, (and pray Heaven it is truth)
"Everyone is fully alive to the necessity for dash, so I trust the
attack of to-morrow will be much better done than were the two previous
attempts."</p>

<p>Hardly had my cable to <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> been despatched when <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> gives us a
sample specimen of "dash" by his answer to my reminder. He wires:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"IXth Corps to G.H.Q. I foresee very great difficulty. The only system
possible at first probably will be convoy under escort."</p>

<p>Twelve hours ago, more or less, <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> had agreed that there was a
difficulty which it was up to him to solve and that, at first, (i.e.,
till blockhouses had been built) the system would be convoy under
escort. We ask him what he had done, expecting to get the particulars
worked out by his Staff after the conference of Generals, and this is
the reply!</p>

<p>Five minutes later, in came another wire giving the general situation at
<location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>; saying the <unit type="division">53rd</unit> Division had failed to clear ground from which
the right of the advance of the <unit type="division">54th Division</unit> might be threatened, and
that <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> wished to postpone his night march another four and twenty
hours.</p>

<p>So this is the result of our "ginger," and <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> or I must rush
over to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> at once. Meanwhile, tactics and <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> must wait.</p>

<p>Wired back:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"In the circumstances the operation for to-morrow is postponed. Chief
sending C.G.S. over now to see you."</p>

<p><person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> went: is back now: has seen both <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and Reed: has
agreed (with a sad heart) on my behalf to the night march being put off
another twenty four hours.</p>

<p>Have had, therefore, to cable <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> again, shouldering the heavy blame of
this further delay:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 545). From General <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian Hamilton</person> to Earl Kitchener. After
anxiously weighing the pros and cons, I have decided that it is wiser to
wait another 24 hours before carrying out the general attack mentioned
in my No. M.F. 543. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> has just returned from the IXth Corps,
and he found that the spirit and general organization were improving
rapidly. A small attack by a Brigade, which promised well, was in
progress. This morning the Xth Division captured a trench."</p>

<p>The story of the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Council of War:--At first the Generals were for
fighting. Inglefield, of the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit>, who is told off for the attack, was
keen. All he asked was, a clean start from <location town="Anafarta_Ova">Anafarta Ova</location>. If his Division
could jump off, intact and fresh, from that well-watered half-way house,
<location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> was his. The <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit> Division for their part agreed to make
good <location town="Anafarta_Ova">Anafarta Ova</location>; to clear out the snipers and to hold the place as a
base for the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit>.</p>

<p>So at 10 a.m. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> issued orders saying the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit> must march off at
4 p.m. moving East of <location town="Anafarta_Ova">Anafarta Ova</location>. Then,--when at last all seemed
settled, in came a message from the G.O.C. <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit> Division, saying he
could not undertake to clear <location town="Anafarta_Ova">Anafarta Ova</location> of snipers and to hold it as a
cover to the advance of the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit>.</p>

<p><person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> thereupon cancelled his first order, and, at 1.15 p.m., issued
fresh orders directing the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit> Division _to send in one of their own
Brigades_ as an advance guard to clear the ground up to a point East of
<location town="Anafarta_Ova">Anafarta Ova</location>. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> stayed at Corps Headquarters at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> until
this Brigade, the 163rd, was moving on <location town="Anafarta_Ova">Anafarta Ova</location> driving the snipers
before them. Mahon, too, after sitting for three days where I left him
on the morning of the 9th, has got tired of looking at the gendarmes
and has carried their trenches by the forbidden frontal bayonet charge
without much trouble or loss although, naturally, these trenches have
been strengthened during the interval.</p>

<p>Amidst these tactical miss-fires entered Hankey. He has had a cable from
his brother Secretary, Bonham Carter, saying the Prime Minister wishes
him to stay on longer and that <person name="Lord_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> would like to know if he can do
anything to give an impetus to the operations. Hankey showed me this
cable; also his answer:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"Reference your 6910. I am glad to stay as desired. The chief thing you
could send to help the present operations would be more ammunition. For
supplies already sent everyone is most grateful. It is also important
that units should be kept up to strength.</p>

<p>"As General Officer Commanding has already apprised you fully of the
situation I have nothing to add."</p>

<p>In the Gordons' Mess "a Marine" used to stand as synonym for emptiness.
Asquith's "Marine"[9] is the reverse. Into two sentences totalling 27
words he boils down the drift of hundreds of cables and letters.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_13th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Well, I must put it down. Worked till
lunch. In the afternoon, left in H.M.S. _Arno_ and sailed over to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>
to have a last look over the _band-o-bast_ for to-morrow's twice
to-morrowed effort. First, saw the Admiral and Commodore who are simply
dancing with impatience. No wonder. Whether or no <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> summit
gives a useful outlook on to the back of Sari Bair and the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>,
at least it will give us the whip hand of the guns on the Anafarta ridge
and save our ships from the annoying attentions they are beginning to
receive. The sailors think too they have worked out an extra good scheme
for ship and shore guns.</p>

<p><person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> then came aboard; in the mood he was in aboard the _Jonquil_ on
the 8th,--only more so! The Divisional Generals are without hope, that
is the text of his sermon. Hopeless about to-night, or to-morrow, that
is to say; for there are rosy visions and to spare for next week, or the
week after, or any other time, so long as it is not too near us. There
is something in this beats me. We are alive--we are quite all right--the
Brigade of the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit> sent on to Kuchuk <location town="Anafarta_Ova">Anafarta Ova</location> made good its point.
True, one battalion got separated from its comrades in the forest and
was badly cut up by Turkish snipers just as was Braddock's force by the
Redskins, but this, though tragic, is but a tiny incident of a great
modern battle and the rest of the 163rd Brigade have not suffered and
hold the spot whence, it was settled, the attack on <location hill="Kavak_Tepe">Kavak Tepe</location> should
jump off. Nothing practical or tactical seems to have occurred to force
us to drop our plan.</p>

<p>But no; <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and Reed count the <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit> Division as finished: the
<unit type="division">LIVth</unit> incapable of attack; the rest of the IXth Corps immovable.</p>

<p>If I accept; we have lost this battle. We are not beaten now--the men
are not--but if I accept, we are held up.</p>

<p>There is no way out. Whether there is any good looking back even for one
moment, God knows; I doubt it! But I feel so acutely, I seem to see so
clearly, where our push for Constantinople first began to quit the
rails, that I must put it down right here. The moment was when I asked
for Rawlinson or Byng, and when, in reply, the keen, the young, the fit,
the up-to-date Commanders were all barred, simply and solely that Mahon
should not be disturbed in his Divisional Command. I resisted it very
strongly: I went so far as to remind <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> in my cable of his own sad
disappointment at Bloemfontein when he (<person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>) had offered him a Cavalry
Brigade and he returned instead to his appointment in the Sudan. The
question that keeps troubling me is, ought I to have fought it further;
ought I to have resigned sooner than allow generals old and yet
inexperienced to be foisted on to me?</p>

<p>These stories about the troops? I do not accept them. The troops have
lost heavily but they are right if there were leaders.</p>

<p>I know quite well both Territorial Divisions. I knew them in England
that is to say. Since then, they have had their eyes picked out. They
have been through the strainer and the best officers and men and the
best battalions have been serving for months past in France. The three
show battalions in the <unit type="division">54th</unit> (Essex) Division are in France and their
places have been taken by the 10th and 11th London and by the 8th Hants.
Essex is good; London is good and Hants is good; but the trinity is not
Territorial. The same with the <unit type="division">Welsh</unit>men.</p>

<p>Yet even so; taking these Territorials as they are; a scratch lot; half
strength; no artillery; not a patch upon the original Divisions as I
inspected them in England six months ago; even so, they'd fight right
enough and keen enough if they were set fair and square at their fence.</p>

<p>In the fight of the 10th the <unit type="division">Welsh</unit>men were not given a chance. Sent in
on a narrow front--jammed into a pocket;--as they began to climb the
spur they caught it from the guns, rifles and machine guns on both
flanks.</p>

<p>We might still do something with a change of commanders. But I have been
long enough Military Secretary both in India and at home to realize that
ruthlessness here is apt to be a two-edged sword. You can't clap a new
head on to old shoulders without upsetting circulation and equilibrium.
Still, I would harden my heart to it now--to-night--were not my hands
tied by Mahon's seniority. Mahon is the next senior--in the whole force
he stands next to myself. Had not Bruce Hamilton been barred by the P.M.
when I wanted to put him in vice <person name="Aylmer_Hunter-Weston">Hunter-Weston</person> at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>, the problem
would be simple enough. Even if I had not, at the outset, given that
well-tried, thrusting old fighter the conduct of the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> enterprise,
at least I would have brought him in on the morning of the 9th instant
quite easily and without causing any upset to anyone or anything. He
ranks both <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and Mahon and nothing would have been simpler than
to let him bring up a contingent of troops from <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>, when,
automatically, he would have taken command in the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> area. What it
would have meant to have had a man imbued with the attack spirit at the
head of this IXth Corps would have been just--victory!</p>

<p>Anchored at 9 p.m. and, before going to bed, sent following cable:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"From General <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian Hamilton</person> to Secretary of State for War.</p>

<p>"The result of my visit to the IXth Corps, from which I am just back,
has bitterly disappointed me. There is nothing for it but to allow them
time to rest and reorganize, unless I force <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> and his Divisional
Generals to undertake a general action for which, in their present frame
of mind, they have no heart. In fact, these generals are unfit for it.
With exceeding reluctance I am obliged to give them time to rest and
reorganize their troops.</p>

<p>"Though we were to repeat our landing operations a hundred times, we
would never dare hope to reproduce conditions so favourable as to put
one division ashore under cover of dark and, as the day broke, have the
next division sailing in to its support. No advantage was taken of these
favourable conditions and, for reasons which I can only explain by
letter, the swift advance was not delivered,--therefore, the mischief is
done. Until we are ready to advance again, reorganized and complete, we
must go slow."</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_14th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Before breakfast, <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> brought me a
statement of our interview of last night with <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>. He dictated it,
directly he got back last night; i.e., about three hours after the
event. I agree with every word:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"Notes of an interview which took place on board H.M.S. _Triad_ between
6 and 7 p.m. on the 13th August, 1915, between the General Commanding
and Sir Frederick <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>, commanding <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit>.</p>

<p>_Present_:--</p>

<p>  General <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian Hamilton</person>, G.C.B., D.S.O., A.D.C.,
  Lieut.-General Hon. Sir Frederick <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>,
  <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>C.M.G., etc.,
  Major-General <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, C.B.</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"Sir Frederick represented that the <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit> were not fit to undertake
an advance at the present moment. Questioned why, he replied that the
losses had been considerable, that the disorganization of units was very
great, and that the length of the line he had to hold was all too thinly
held as it was. He stated that his Divisional Generals were entirely of
the same opinion as himself; in fact, he gave us completely the
impression that they were 'not for it,' but he only specifically
mentioned Hammersley and <person name="John_Lindley">Lindley</person>. He said water was no difficulty. He
implied that the troops were getting better every day, and given time to
rest and reorganize, he thought they would be able in time to make an
advance. But he was very emphatic on the point that at present such a
thing as an attack had practically no chance of success. He told us that
the opposition in the centre about <location town="Anafarta_Ova">Anafarta Ova</location> could no longer be
classed as sniping, but that it was regular opposition. But as he also
told us that his landing was an opposed landing, I think perhaps that
during the short time he has been on active service in this country he
has not quite realized what opposition really means. But the salient
fact remains that none of his Divisional Generals who would be employed
in the attack thought that that attack would have any chance of success
whatever. Indeed, he saw every difficulty, and though he kept saying
that he was an optimist, he foresaw every bad thing that could possibly
happen and none of the bright spots. It was a most depressing interview,
but it left no doubt in the minds of the hearers that it would be quite
useless to order an attack to be undertaken by a Commander and
Divisional Generals whose hearts were confessedly not in it, who saw a
Turk behind every bush, a battalion behind every hill, and a Brigade
behind every mountain."</p>

<p>At lunch time <person name="Lord_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> answered my last night's cable:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"If you should deem it necessary to replace <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>, Mahon and
Hammersley, have you any competent Generals to take their place? From
your report I think <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> should come home.</p>

<p>"This is a young man's war, and we must have commanding officers that
will take full advantage of opportunities which occur but seldom. If,
therefore, any Generals fail, do not hesitate to act promptly.</p>

<p>"Any Generals I have available I will send you."</p>

<p>Close on the top of this tardy appreciation of youth, comes another
cable from him saying he has asked French to let me have Byng, Horne and
Kavanagh. "I hope," he says, "<person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> has been relieved by you
already."</p>

<p>Have cabled back thanking him with all my heart; saying I shall be glad
of the Generals he mentions as "Byng, Kavanagh and Horne are all
flyers."</p>

<p>Between them, these two messages have cleared the air. Mahon's seniority
has been at the root of this evil. <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s conscience tells him so and,
therefore, he pricks his name now upon the fatal list. But he did not
know, when he cabled, that Mahon had done well. I shall replace <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>
forthwith by <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> and chance Mahon's seniority.</p>

<p>De Robeck came over for an hour in the evening.</p>

<p>Lord and Lady Brassey arrived in the _Sunbeam_, together with two young
friends. They have both of them shown great enterprise in getting here.
The dear old man gave me a warm greeting, but also something of a shock
by talking about our terrible defeat: by condoling and by saying I had
been asked to do the impossible. I have _not_ been asked to do anything
impossible in taking Constantinople. The feat is perfectly feasible. For
the third time since we began it trembled in the balance a week ago. Nor
is the capture of <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay and the linking up thereof with Anzac a
defeat: a cruel disappointment, no doubt, but not a defeat; for, two
more such defeats, measured in mere acreage, will give us the Narrows. A
doctor at Kephalos, it seems, infected them with this poison of
despondency. In their _Sunbeam_ they will make first class carriers.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_15th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">De Lisle</person> has come over to relieve <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>.
He has got his first instructions[10] and is in close communication with
myself and General Staff on the preparations for the next move which
will be supported by the Yeomanry from Egypt and by some more artillery.
I had meant to make time to run across to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> to-day but <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> may
wish to see me on his way to <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location> so I shall sit tight in case he
does.</p>

<p>Cables to and from <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> about our new Generals. Byng, <person name="Stanley_Maude">Maude</person> and <person name="Edward_Fanshawe">Fanshawe</person>
are coming. A brilliant trio. All of the three <person name="Edward_Fanshawe">Fanshawe</person> brothers are
good; this one worked under me on Salisbury Plain. <person name="Stanley_Maude">Maude</person> is splendid!
Byng will make every one happy; he never spares himself. <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> has agreed
to let <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> hold the command of the <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit> until Byng turns up.
He wants Birdie to take over the control of the whole of the Northern
theatre, i.e., Anzac and <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>. I must think over this. Meanwhile, have
cabled back, "I am enchanted to hear Byng, <person name="Stanley_Maude">Maude</person> and <person name="Edward_Fanshawe">Fanshawe</person> are
coming--I could wish for no better men."</p>

<p>Sent also following which explains itself:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"When I appointed <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> to command temporarily the IXth Corps I sent
the following telegram to Mahon:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"'Although <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> is junior to you, Sir Ian hopes that you will waive
your seniority and continue in command of the Xth Division, at any rate
during the present phase of operations.'</p>

<p>"To this Mahon sent the following reply:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"'I respectfully decline to waive my seniority and to serve under the
officer you name. Please let me know to whom I am to hand over the
command of the Division.'</p>

<p>"Consequently, I have appointed Brigadier-General F. F. Hill to command
temporarily the Division and have ordered Mahon to go to <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location> to await
orders. Will you please send orders as to his disposal. As Peyton is not
due from Egypt till 18th August, he was not in any case available."</p>

<p>Also:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"Personal. You will like to know that the <unit type="division">XIIIth</unit> Division is said to
have fought very well and with great tenacity of spirit. In many
instances poor company leading is said to have been responsible for
undue losses."</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_16th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> A great press of business. Amongst other
work, have written a long cable home giving them the whole story up to
date. Lots of petty troubles. <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> goes to <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location> direct. <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">De Lisle</person>
makes a thorough overhaul at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>.</p>

<p>Glyn and Hankey both looked in upon me. It is a relief to have an
outsider of Hankey's calibre on the spot. He said, "Thank God!" when he
heard of <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s cable, and urged Birdie should be told off to take <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>
in hand, in his stead. I suppose the G.S. have let him get wind of <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s
identical suggestion. As I told Hankey, I have not yet made up my mind.
But it would be an awkward job for Birdie with all the Anzacs to run,
and no nearer <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> really--in point of time--than we are. Nor is he
staffed for so big a business. Hankey has been too long away from
executive work to realize that difficulty. But the decisive factor is
this; that having been closely associated with him and with his work for
a good many years, I know as Hankey cannot know, how much of his
strength lies in his personal touch and presence:--spread his powers too
wide he loses that touch. Felt the better for my talk with Hankey. He
can grasp the bigness of what we are up against and can yet keep his
head and see that the game is worth the candle and that it is in our
hands the moment we make up our minds to pay the price of the
illuminant.</p>

<p>Have written to the Chief of the Imperial General Staff saying:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"I have just been through a horrible mental crisis quite different from
the ordinary anxiety of the battlefield, where I usually see what I
think to be my way and chance it. I refer to <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Freddy Stopford</person>. Here is a
man who has committed no fault; whose life-long conscientious study of
his profession has borne the best fruits in letting him see the right
thing to do and how it should be done. And yet he fails when many a man
possessing not one quarter of his military qualifications carries on
with flying colours. For there is no use beating about the bush now and,
simply, he was not big enough in character to face up to the situation.
It overwhelmed him.</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"A month ago we had the Turks down, undoubtedly and, whenever we could
get a little ammunition together, we were confident we could take a line
of trenches. As for their attacks, it was obvious their men were not for
it. Now their four new Divisions of fine fighting material seem to have
animated the whole of the rest of the force with their spirit, and the
Turks have never fought so boldly as they are doing to-day. They are
tough to crack, but D.V., we will be the tougher of the two."</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_17th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> From his cable of the 14th, <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> seems
prepared to see me relieve Mahon of his command. But Mahon is a fighter
and if I give him time to think over things a bit at <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location>, he'll be
sure to think better. I am sure the wisest course to take, is to take
time. A Lieutenant-General in the British Army chucking up his command
whilst his Division is actually under fire--is a very unhappy affair.
Lord <person name="Lord_Bobs">Bobs</person> used to say that a soldier asked, for the good of the cause,
to serve as a drummer boy under his worst enemy should do so not only
with alacrity but with joy. <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> agrees with me that we must
just take the responsibility of doing nothing at all and of leaving him
quietly to cool down at <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location>. Hill, who carries on, was the General in
command at Mitylene when I inspected there; he is a good fellow; he was
anxious to push on upon that fatal 7th August at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> and everyone says
he is a stout fellow.</p>

<p>Have got the name of the doctor who upset the Brasseys with his yarns.
He declares he only retailed the tales of the wounded youngsters whom he
tended. No more to be said. He has studied microbes extensively but one
genus has clearly escaped his notice: he has never studied or grasped
the fell methods of the microbes of rumour or panic. Am I sure that I
myself have not crabbed my own show a bit in telling the full story of
our fight to <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> this afternoon? No, I am by no means sure.</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 562.) From General <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian Hamilton</person> to Earl Kitchener. Have
thought it best to lay the truth fully before you, and am now able to
give a complete _rsum_ of the past week's operations, and an
appreciation of the situation confronting me.</p>

<p>"In broad outline, my plan was to hold the Turks in the Southern zone by
constant activity of French and VIIIth Corps, and to throw all the
reinforcements into the Northern zone with the object of defeating the
enemy opposite Anzac, seizing a new base at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>, and gaining a
position astride the narrow part of the peninsula. With this object, I
reinforced General <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> with the <unit type="division">XIIIth</unit> Division, <unit type="brigade">29th Brigade</unit>, Xth
Division, and <unit type="division">29th</unit> Indian Brigade, all of which were secretly dribbled
ashore at Anzac Cove on the three nights preceding commencement of
operations. This was done without arousing the suspicions of the enemy.
Arrangements were made for the XIth Division to land at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay on the
same night as General <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> commenced his attack. Meanwhile, the
Turks were deceived by ill-concealed preparations for landings on
Asiatic coast near Mitylene, at Enos, South of Gaba Tepe.</p>

<p>"Following is detailed plan of operations:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"On the afternoon of 6th August the VIIIth Corps were to attack Krithia
trenches, and simultaneously General <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> was to attack Lone Pine
trenches on his right front, as though attempting to break out in this
direction. In this way it was hoped to draw the Turkish reinforcements
towards Krithia and Gaba Tepe and away from Anzac's left and <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay.
At 10 p.m. General <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person>'s main attack was to develop on his left
flank, the Turkish outposts were to be rushed and an advance made in
several columns up the precipitous ravines leading to <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location> and
the summit of Hill 305, which it was hoped might be captured before
daybreak.</p>

<p>"As soon as the high ridge was in our hands an advance was to be made
down the Hill 305 to take in the rear the trenches on Baby 700 (see
enlarged map of Anzac positions) and at the same time the troops in the
original Anzac position were to attack all along the line in an
endeavour to break out and hurl the enemy off the Sari Bair. Meanwhile
the XIth Division was to commence landing 10.30 p.m. on 6th August, one
brigade inside <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay, two brigades on shore to South were to seize
and hold all hills covering Bay and especially <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location> and Ismail
Oglu Tepe on which enemy were believed to have guns which could bring
fire to bear either on back of General <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person>'s advance on Hill 305,
or on <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay. The ridge from <location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location> to Aja Liman was also to
be lightly held. The Xth Division, less one brigade, was to follow XIth
Division at daybreak and <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit> Division was held in general reserve.
The <unit type="division">LIVth</unit> Division had not arrived and could not be employed in the
first instance.</p>

<p>"The moment <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person> had fulfilled the above tasks, which, owing to the
small number of the enemy in this neighbourhood and the absence of any
organized system of trenches, were considered comparatively easy, he was
to advance South-west through Biyuk Anafarta with the object of
assisting <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> in the event of his attack being held up.</p>

<p>"Reliable information indicated the strength of the enemy about <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>
Bay to be one regiment, one squadron and some Gendarmerie with at most
twelve guns, and events have shown that this estimate was correct. It
was also believed that the enemy had 36,000 in the Southern zone, 27,000
against Anzac, and 37,000 in reserve. Also 45,000 near Keshan who could
not arrive for three days and 10,000 on Asiatic shore.</p>

<p>"The attack by the VIIIth Corps opposite Krithia took place as arranged,
but was met by determined opposition. Some enemy trenches were
captured, but the Turks were found in great strength and full of fight.
They counter-attacked repeatedly on the night of 6th/7th, and eventually
regained the ground we had taken. Prisoners captured stated that the
Turks had planned to attack us that night in any case which accounts for
their strength.</p>

<p>"In the Northern zone General <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person>'s afternoon attack was successful
and Lone Pine trenches were captured by a most gallant Australian
assault. Throughout the day, and for three successive days the enemy
made repeated attempts to recapture the position, but each time were
repulsed with severe loss. At 10 p.m. the main advance on the left flank
by the New Zealanders, <unit type="division">XIIIth</unit> Division, <unit type="brigade">29th Brigade</unit> and <person name="Charles_Cox">Cox</person>'s Brigade
began, and in spite of stupendous difficulties, moving by night in most
difficult country, all enemy's posts in foot of hills were rushed and
captured up to and including Damakjelik Bair. The enemy was partly
surprised, but his reinforcements were all called up, and this, coupled
with the extreme difficulty of the country, made it impossible to reach
the crest of the hill that day or the following. The position
immediately below the crest, however, was reached, and on the morning of
the 8th, after severe fighting, two battalions of the <unit type="division">XIIIth</unit> Division
and Gurkhas reached the top of Kurt Ketchede, and two battalions of New
Zealanders established themselves on the crest of the ridge at Chunuk
Bair.</p>

<p>"Unfortunately, the troops on Kurt Ketchede were shelled off the ridge
by our own gun fire, and were unable to recapture it; and 48 hours
later two battalions of the <unit type="division">XIIIth</unit> Division, who had relieved tired New
Zealanders on <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location>, were driven back by determined daybreak
assault, carried by the Turks in many successive lines, shoulder to
shoulder. Our troops were too weary, and much too disorganized to make a
counter-attack at that time, and could only maintain positions below
crest. Water supply, which had always been an anxiety, began to fail,
and grave difficulties arose which prevented the possibility of
reinforcing <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person>, and almost necessitated our giving up our gains.
All this, however, has now been put right.</p>

<p>"Meanwhile, <person name="Frederick_Stopford">Stopford</person>'s Corps at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> had landed most successfully, but,
owing to lack of energy and determination on the part of leaders, and,
perhaps, partly to the inexperience of the troops, had failed to take
advantage of the opportunities as already reported.</p>

<p>"The result is that my coup has so far failed. It was soon realized that
it was necessary to give impetus to the IXth Corps, and the <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit>
Division was put in on 8th-9th. By this time the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit> Division was
available as general reserve. Unfortunately, the <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit> Division broke
in my hand, leaving me like a fencer with rapier broken, and by the time
the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit> Division arrived the remaining troops of the Corps were too
tired and disorganized for further immediate effort.</p>

<p>"The IXth Corps holds the position from Kiretch Tepe Sirt, bench mark 2;
Sulajik; <location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location>, with right flank thrown south to connect with
<person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> at Kazlar Chair. <person name="Alexander_Godley">Godley</person> has picket between Kazlar Chair and
Damakjelik Bair, whence his line runs South-east to the spur South of
Abdel Rahman Bair, thence South-west to square 80 D, South-east again to
within 300 yards of Point 161 on <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location>, and thence back to the
left of the Anzac position.</p>

<p>"<person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">De Lisle</person> has at his disposal the Xth Division, less one brigade, the
XIth, <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit> and <unit type="division">LIVth</unit> Divisions; total rifles, owing to casualties,
under 30,000. The <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> losses have been too severe considering extent
and nature of the fighting that has taken place, and can only be
attributed to the inexperience of the troops and their leaders, and the
daring way in which the enemy skirmishers presumed upon it in the broken
and wooded country. <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> has lost about 13,000 since the action
began, and has now available some 25,000 rifles. The VIIIth Corps has
23,000 rifles, and the French 17,000 rifles.</p>

<p>"The Turks have continued to be most active in the South, no doubt with
the object of preventing us moving troops, but apparently they have now
no more than 35,000 in this zone. The majority of the enemy Commander's
troops are against Anzac and in reserve in the valley between Hills 305
and 261, his strategic flank.</p>

<p>"In the Northern zone, in the fighting line at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> and Anzac and in
reserve he may now have in all 75,000, and can either reinforce Hill 305
or issue through the gap between the two Anafartas to oppose any attack
on <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> or on the ridge running thence to <location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location>. He
has guns on Hill 305, on <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location>, and on the ridge North of
<location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location> from which he can shell landing places at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay, but
is not holding the latter ridge in strength, nor do I think he has
enough troops to enable him to do so.</p>

<p>"The position regarding the Turkish reinforcements from Keshan is not
clear. Only small parties have been located by aeroplanes marching
South, and it appears that either this information was incorrect or that
the enemy's forces had already got as far as the peninsula before
fighting began.</p>

<p>"I consider it urgently necessary to seize <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> and Anafarta
Sagir at the earliest possible moment, and I have ordered <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> to
make the attempt at the earliest opportunity. I have also ordered
<person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> to make a fresh attack on Hill 305 as soon as troops are
reorganized and the difficulties of water supply solved, but for this he
will require drafts and fresh troops. I have great hopes that these
attacks may yet be successful, but it is impossible to disguise the fact
that owing to the failure of the IXth Corps to take advantage of
opportunities and the fact that surprise may now be absent, and that the
enemy is prepared and in much greater strength, my difficulties are
enormously increased. In any case my cadres will be so depleted as a
result of action that I shall need large reinforcements to enable me to
bring the operations to a happy conclusion.</p>

<p>"The Turkish losses have been heavier than ours, and the total number of
prisoners taken is 702, but I estimate that they have now in the
peninsula at least 110,000 rifles to my 95,000 and they have all the
advantage of position. They have, apparently, all the ammunition they
need and obtain reinforcements as they are wanted. In particular, we
have had no news of the arrival of the 45,000 troops reported to be at
Keshan, and only one of the Asiatic Divisions has as yet come over. I
had hoped that their reinforcements would be of poor quality and not a
match for ours but this is not the case, and unfortunately the Turks
have temporarily gained the moral ascendency over some of our new
troops. If, therefore, this campaign is to be brought to an early and
successful conclusion large reinforcements will have to be sent to
me--drafts for the formations already here, and new formations with
considerably reduced proportion of artillery. It has become a question
of who can slog longest and hardest.</p>

<p>"Owing to the difficulty of carrying on a winter campaign, and the
lateness of the season, these troops should be sent immediately. My
British Divisions are at present 45,000 under establishment, exclusive
of about 9,000 promised or on the way. If this deficit were made up, and
new formations totalling 50,000 rifles sent out as well, these, with the
60,000 rifles which I estimate I shall have at the time of their
arrival, should give me the necessary superiority, unless the absence of
other enemies allows the Turks to bring up large additional
reinforcements.</p>

<p>"I hope you will realize how nearly this operation was a success
complete beyond anticipation. The surprise was complete, and the army
was thrown ashore in record time, practically without loss, and a little
more push on the part of the IXth Corps would have relieved the pressure
on Anzac, facilitated the retention of <location town="Chunuk_Bair">Chunuk Bair</location>, secured <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay as
a port, and threatened the enemy's right in a way that should have
enabled Anzac to turn a success into a great victory.</p>

<p>"We are up against the Turkish Army which is well commanded and fighting
bravely."</p>

<p>After all's said and done the troops at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> and Anzac are still
perfectly game and we have got nearer our goal. We started forth to:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>(1) Seize <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay;</p>

<p>(2) Break out of Anzac and join on to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>;</p>

<p>(3) Seize Sari Bair crestline;</p>

<p>(4) Hold enough of the hinterland of <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay to make it a comfortable
harbour.</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>(1) and (2) we have carried through handsomely. We have trebled our
holding at Anzac and we have put <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay in our pocket. (3) we have
not done; we are short of it by a couple of hundred yards; (4) we have
not done; it is a practicable harbour but subject certainly to
annoyance. In honest, gambler's language, we have won a good stake but
we have not broke the Ottoman Bank.</p>

<p><person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">De Lisle</person> reports confusion throughout <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay area. He _must_ have
three or four days to pull the troops together before he organizes a
fresh offensive. The IXth Corps has been _un corps sans tte_.</p>

<p>FOOTNOTES:</p>

<p>[Footnote 9: Hankey belonged to the Royal Marine Artillery.--IAN H.,
1920.]</p>

<p>[Footnote 10: See Appendix IV containing actual letter of
instructions.--IAN H., 1920.]</p>

</entry>


<chapter n="17">CHAPTER XVII</chapter>

<title>THE LAST BATTLE</title>

<entry><p>_18th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Freddie and I left in the _Arno_ this
morning; <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> and his boy Val came with us. We sailed for <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>
_via_ Anzac and held a meeting which was nearer a Council of War than
anything up to date. <person name="Guy_Dawnay">Dawnay</person>, Deedes and Beadon stood by; so did Generals
Skeen, Hammersley and Peyton. Reed, C.G.S., IXth Corps, was also
present. The discussion of the steps to be taken within the next two or
three days lasted an hour and a half. Every one who spoke had studied
the data and the ground and there was no divergence of view, which was a
comfort. Our attack will have as its objective the seizure of a foothold
on the high ground. Anzacs will co-operate. As I explained to the
Generals, we hardly dare hope to make a clean break through till drafts
and fresh munitions arrive as the Turks now have had too long to dig in.
But if we can seize and keep a point upon the watershed (however small)
from which we can observe the drop of our shell, we can knock out the
landing places of the Turks. At the end, I told them I had asked for
95,000 fresh rifles, 50,000 in new formations, 45,000 to bring my
skeleton units up to strength, adding, that if I was refused that help
then I felt Government had better get someone cleverer than myself to
put their Fleet into the Marmora. The Generals seemed satisfied with my
demands and sympathetic towards my personal attitude.</p>

<p>As to the coming attack, the tone of the Conference was hopeful. They
agreed that the nut was hard for our enfeebled forces to crack, but they
seemed to think that if we were once to get the enemy on the run, with
the old <unit type="division">29th</unit> Division and the new, keen Yeomanry on their heels, we
might yet go further than we expected. One Brigade of the <unit type="division">29th</unit> Division
has been brought round from <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> to put shape and form into the <unit type="division">53rd</unit>
Division. Peyton's men are to be attached to the Irish Division. There
is a new spirit of energy and hope in the higher ranks but the men have
meanwhile been aimlessly marched and counter-marched, muddled, and
knocked about so that their spirit has suffered in consequence.</p>

<p>No end of Yeomen on the beaches; the cream of agricultural England. Many
of them recognized me from my various home inspections. Would like very
much to have had a war inspection, but the enemy gunners are too
inquisitive.</p>

<p><person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">De Lisle</person> tells me he has now been round every corner of <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> and that
the want of grip throughout the higher command has been worse than he
dared to put on paper. To reorganize will take several weeks; but we
have to try and act within two or three days.</p>

<p>Skeen told us that when the Turks stuck up a placard saying Warsaw had
fallen, the Australians gave three hearty cheers.</p>

<p>The chief trouble in making plans for the coming attack lies in the want
of cover on, and for a mile inland of, the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay beaches. The whole
stretch of the flat land immediately East and South of the Bay lies open
to the Turkish gunners. This is no longer a serious drawback if the men
are holding lines of trenches. But when the trench system is not yet in
working order, and they want to deploy, then it is so awkward a factor
that I would have been prepared to turn the whole battle into a night
attack. The others were not for it. They thought that the troops were
not highly enough trained and had lost too many officers to be able to
find their way over this country in the darkness. They are in immediate
touch with the men: I am not.</p>

<p><person name="John_Lindley">Lindley</person> asked if he might walk with me to the Beach, and on the way down
he told me frankly his Division had gone to pieces and that he did not
feel it in himself to pull it together again. Very fine of him to make a
clean breast of it, I thought, and said so: also advised him to put what
he had told me into writing to <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person>, when we will relieve him and I
promised for my part, to try and fit him with some honourable but less
onerous job.</p>

<p>On Hammersley's report, Sitwell, Brigadier of the <unit type="brigade">34th</unit> Brigade, 11th
Division, has just been relieved of his command.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_19th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Sat sweating here, literally and
metaphorically, from morn till dewy eve. King's Messenger left in the
evening. <person name="General_Altham">Altham</person> came over from <location town="Mudros">Mudros</location>. He stays to-night and we will
work together to-morrow when the mails are off my mind.</p>

<p>Hankey dined and left with the King's Messenger by the _Imogene_. He has
been a real help. The Staff has never quite cottoned to the chief among
us takin' notes, but that is, I think, from a notion that it is not
loyal to <person name="Lord_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> to press the P.M.'s P.S. too closely to their bosom.
From my personal standpoint, it will be worth anything to us if, amidst
the flood of false gossip pouring out by this very mail to our
<location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> Committee, to the Press, to Egypt and to London Drawing
Rooms, we have sticking up out of it, even one little rock in the shape
of an eye-witness.</p>

<p>A shocking aeroplane smash up within a few yards of us. A brilliant
young Officer (Captain Collet of the R.F.C.) killed outright and three
men badly hurt.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_20th August, 1915._ Stayed in my tent keeping an eye on to-morrow. Put
through a lot with <person name="General_Altham">Altham</person>. Am pressing him to hurry up with his canteens
at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>, Anzac and <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>. In May I cabled the Q.M.G. begging him
either to let me run a canteen on the lines of the South African Field
Force Canteen, myself; or, to run it from home, himself; or, to put the
business into the hands of some private firm like the Mess and Canteen
Company, or Lipton's, or Harrods or anything he liked. In South Africa
we could often buy something. In France our troops can buy anything.
Here, had they each the purse of Fortunatus, they could buy nothing. A
matter this, I won't say of life and death, but of sickness and health.
Now, after three months without change of diet, the first canteen ship
is about due. A mere flea bite of 10,000 worth. I am sending the whole
of it to the Anzacs to whom it will hardly be more use than a bun is to
a she bear. Only yesterday a letter came in from Birdie telling me that
the doctors all say that the sameness of the food is making the men
sick. The rations are A.1., but his men now loathe the very look of them
after having had nothing else for three months. Birdie says, "If we
could only get this wretched canteen ship along, and if, when she comes
she contains anything like condiments to let them buy freely from her, I
believe it would make all the difference in the world. But the fact
remains that at present we cannot count on anything like a big effort
from the men who have been here all these months."</p>

<p>De Robeck came over at 4 p.m., by formal appointment, to talk business,
and deadly serious business at that! He has heard, by cable I suppose,
that the people at home will see him through if he sees his way to
strike a blow with the Fleet. He takes this as a pretty strong hint to
push through, or, to make some sort of a battleship attack to support
us. De Robeck knows that when the Fleet goes in our fighting strength
goes up. But he can gauge, as I cannot, the dangers the Fleet will
thereby incur. Every personal motive urges me to urge him on. But I have
no right to shove my oar in--no right at all--until I can say that we
are done unless the Fleet do make an attack. Can I say so? No; if we
get the drafts and munitions we can still open the Straits on our own
and without calling on the sister Service for further sacrifice. So I
fell back on first principles and said he must attack if he thought it
right from the naval point of view but that we soldiers did not call for
succour or ask him to do anything desperate: "You know how we stand," I
said; "do what is right from the naval point of view and as to what _is_
right from that point of view, I am no judge."</p>

<p>The Admiral went away: I have been no help to him but I can't help it.</p>

<p>Hardly had he gone when <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person> (who had heard what was in the wind
by a side wind) came and besought me to try and induce the Admiral to
slip his battleships at the Straits. All the younger men of war are
dying to have a dash, he said. That's as it may be but my mind is clear.
If a sailor on land is a fish out of water, a soldier at sea is like a
game cock in a duckpond. When <person name="John_de_Robeck">de Robeck</person> said on March 22nd he wanted the
help of the whole Army that was quite in order. He would not have been
in order--at least, I don't think so--had he said in what manner he
wanted the Army to act after it had got ashore. We are being helped now
by the Navy; daily, hourly: we could not exist without the Fleet; but it
is not for me to say I think the battleships should or should not take
chances of mines and torpedoes.</p>

<p>Brodrick is quite seedy. We are all afraid he won't be able to stick it
out much longer although he is making the most heroic efforts. In the
morning I attended the funeral of young Collet, killed yesterday so
tragically. A long, slow march through heavy sand all along the beach to
Kephalos; then up through some small rocky gullies, frightfully hot,
until, at last, we reached a graveyard. The congregation numbered many
of the poor boy's comrades who seemed much cut up about his untimely
end.</p>

<p>The P.M. has answered my cable to <person name="Lord_Kitchener">Lord K.</person> asking for 45,000 rifles to
fill up and for 50,000 fresh rifles. <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> is in France, he says, and I
will have my answer when he gets back. The 5th Royal Scots are down to
289 rank and file. I have just cabled about them. Something must be
done. Certainly it must be "out" for that particular unit if they don't
very soon get some men. The War Office still refer to them as a
Battalion!</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_21st August, 1915._ Sailed for <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> about 1 o'clock with <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>,
<person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person>, <person name="Guy_Dawnay">Dawnay</person>, Deedes, <person name="General_Ellison">Ellison</person>, Pollen and <person name="Freddie_Maitland">Maitland</person>. The first time I
have set forth with such a Staff. Not wishing to worry <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person>, I
climbed up to the Karakol Dagh, whence I got something like a bird's eye
view of the arena which was wrapt from head to foot in a mantle of
pearly mist. Assuredly the Ancients would have ascribed this phenomenon
to the intervention of an Immortal. Nothing like it had ever been seen
by us until that day and the cloud--mist--call it what you will--must
have had an unfortunate bearing on the battle. On any other afternoon
the enemy's trenches would have been sharply and clearly lit up, whilst
the enemy's gunners would have been dazzled by the setting sun. But
under this strange shadow the tables were completely turned; the outline
of the Turkish trenches were blurred and indistinct, whereas troops
advancing from the gean against the Anafartas stood out in relief
against a pale, luminous background.</p>

<p>As a result of our instructions; of conferences and of the war council
we had got our plan perfectly clear and ship-shape. Everyone understood
it. The <unit type="division">10th Division</unit> was Corps reserve and was lying down in mass about
the old Hill 10 in the scrub. We had to trust to luck here as they were
under the enemy's fire if they were spotted. But very strict orders as
to keeping low and motionless had been issued and we had just to hope
for the best. The Yeomanry were also Corps reserve at <location hill="Lala_Baba">Lala Baba</location> where
they were safe. But when they advanced, supposing they had to, they
would have to cross a perfectly open plain under shell fire. This was
the special blot on the scheme but there was no getting away from it.
There was no room for them in the front line trenches and communication
trenches to the front had not yet been dug.</p>

<p>As to the attack:--on the extreme right the Anzacs and Indian Brigade
were to push out from Damakjelik Bair towards Hill 60. Next to them in
the right centre the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit> was to push for the trenches at
Hetman Chair. On the left centre the <unit type="division">29th</unit> Division were to storm the now
heavily entrenched Hill 70. Holding that and <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> we should
command the plateau between the two Anafartas; knock out the enemy's
guns and observation posts commanding <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay, and should easily be
able thence to work ourselves into a position whence we will enfilade
the rear of the Sari Bair Ridge and begin to get a strangle grip over
the Turkish communications to the Southwards. From the extreme left on
Kiretch Tepe Sirt by the sea, to Sulajik where they joined the <unit type="division">29th</unit>
Division the <unit type="division">53rd</unit> and <unit type="division">54th</unit> Divisions were simply holding the line.</p>

<p>Only the broad outline of the fighting was visible through the dim
twilight atmosphere and I have not yet got any details. Our bombardment
began at 2.30 and lasted till 3 p.m., very inadequate in duration but
the most our munitions would run to. Then, to the accompaniment of quick
battery salvoes of shrapnel from the enemy and a heavy rattle of
musketry, the whole line from about a mile due East of the Easternmost
point of the Salt Lake down to Damakjelik Bair, nearly two miles, began
to stir and move Eastwards. We had the joy of seeing the Turks begin to
clear out of the trenches on Hill 70, and by 3.30 p.m. it seemed as if
distinct progress was being made: about that time it was I saw the
Yeomen marching in extended order over the open ground to the South of
the Salt Lake in the direction of Hetman Chair. The enemy turned a
baddish shrapnel fire on to them, and although they bore it most
unflinchingly, old experience told me that their nervous fighting energy
was being used up all the time. If only these men could have been
brought within charging distance, fresh and unbroken by any ordeal! But
here was just one of the drawbacks of the battlefield and no getting
over it.</p>

<p>After a bit, I went down to <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> and found him sitting on a little
spur about fifty yards from his own Headquarters with one of his Staff
Officers. He was smoking a pipe--quite calm. There is usually nothing to
be said or to be done once our war dogs have been slipped. A soldier
might as well try to correct the aim of his bullet after he has pulled
the trigger! Whilst I was there we heard--probably about 4.30--that the
<unit type="division">11th Division</unit> had captured the Turkish first line trenches which run
North and South of Hetman Chair. Real good news this. We were
considerably bucked up. Climbed back to Karakol Dagh but, from that time
onwards, could make out nothing of the course of the battle save that
<location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> was not yet taken. As to Knoll 70, it was completely
shrouded in dust and smoke. Sometimes it seemed as if the Turkish guns
were firing against it; sometimes we thought they were our own. Far away
by <location hill="Kaiajik_Aghala">Kaiajik Aghala</location> things looked well as many enemy shrapnel were
bursting there or thereabouts showing our men must have got home. By
6.30 it had become too dark to see anything. The dust mingling with the
strange mist, and also with the smoke of shrapnel and of the hugest and
most awful blazing bush fire formed an impenetrable curtain.</p>

<p>As the light faded the rifles and guns grew silent. So I clambered down
off my perch and went again to <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person>'s post of command where I found
him still sitting. He had seen no more than I had seen. The bulk of our
reserves had been thrown in. No more news had come to hand. All was
quiet now. Our _rle_, in fact, was finished, and Marshall, the man on
the spot, by now held our destinies in his hands. Firm hands too. The
telephone was working all right and I told <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> to try and get a
message through to him quickly saying that I hoped he would be able to
dig in and hold fast to whatever he had gained. I have no fears about de
Lisle's nerve; nor of Marshall's.</p>

<p>Went on board and sailed for Headquarters, through darkness made visible
by the fires blazing on the battlefield. No shooting. Got on the wires
and found no news from Anzac nor more from <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person>. Crossed backwards
and forwards the best part of the night between my tent and the G.S.
tent, but <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> had heard nothing definite enough to report. Brodrick
still has fever. Ruthven has been wounded.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_22nd August, 1915._ <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> gone wrong again; Anzac right. Left G.H.Q. at
11 o'clock with <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, Commodore <person name="Roger_Keyes">Keyes</person>, Captain Phillimore,
<person name="Cecil_Aspinall-Oglander">Aspinall</person>, Beadon, <person name="Frederick Stopford">Freddy</person> and Val in the _Arno_ and went direct to Anzac.
There I picked up Birdie and heard the Anzac part of the battle. The
Indian Brigade have seized the well at Kabak Kuyu, and that fine
soldier, Russell, fixed himself into <location hill="Kaiajik_Aghala">Kaiajik Aghala</location> and is holding on
there tooth and nail. There was fighting going on there at the moment
but Russell is confident. How delightful it is to have to deal with men
who are confident!</p>

<p>This success of old <person name="Charles_Cox">Cox</person>'s is worth anything. The well alone, I suppose,
might be valued at twenty or thirty thousand a year seeing it gives us
beautiful spring water in free gift from Mother Earth instead of very
dubious fluid conveyed at God only knows what cost from the Nile to
Anzac Cove. If we can only hold on to <location hill="Kaiajik_Aghala">Kaiajik Aghala</location>, then the road
between Anzac and <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> will be freed from the sniper's bullet.</p>

<p>Went on to <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> and landed with all my posse, remaining in consultation
with Corps Headquarters till 3.30.</p>

<p>Our attack on Hill 70 and <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> has failed. The enemy has dug
himself well in by now and, therefore, we depended far more on our gun
fire than we did on the 7th, 8th, 9th and 10th. Unfortunately, the
bombardment seems to have been pretty near futile--not the fault of the
gunners, but simply because, on the one hand, the mist interfered with
the accuracy of their aim, on the other, shortage of shell prevented
them from making up for inaccuracy by quantity. Then the bush fires seem
to have come along in the most terrible fashion and interposed between
our brave <unit type="division">29th</unit> and the Turks. The ancient Gods fought against us
yesterday:--mist and fire, still hold their own against the inventions
of man. Last but not least, all are agreed the fine edge of the 11th
Division has been at last blunted--and small wonder: there is no use
attacking any more with the New Army until it has been well rested and
refreshed with new drafts.</p>

<p>So far <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> has no clear or connected story of the battle. The <unit type="division">29th</unit>
Division say they were shouldered off their true line of attack by the
<unit type="division">11th Division</unit>, then driven in by the fire; the <unit type="division">11th Division</unit>, on their
side, say that the Yeomen barged into them and threw them off their
line. Had we been able to dig in we would have made good a lot of
ground. But Marshall, not showy or brilliant but one of my most sound
and reliable soldiers, decided, although he knew my wishes and hopes,
that the troops had got themselves so mixed up and disorganized that it
would be imprudent. So orders were issued by him, on the battlefield, to
fall back to the original line. There was neither use nor time to refer
back to <person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">de Lisle</person> and he had to come to the decision himself. I am quite
confident he will be able to give good reasons for his act. Many of the
men did not get the order and were still out at daylight this morning
when they were heavily attacked by the Turks and fell back then of
themselves into their old trenches. Another case of "as you were." We
have lost a lot of men and can only hope that the Turks have lost as
many. I don't think for a moment they did, not at least in the <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay
sphere, but <person name="Charles_Cox">Cox</person> and Russell claim to have accounted for a very great
number of them in their first retreat and in their counter-attacks in
the Southern sector of the battle.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_23rd August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Not one moment, till to-day, to weigh
bearing of <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s message of the 20th instant,--the message sent me in
reply to my appeal for 50,000 fresh troops and 45,000 drafts. In it <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>
tells me that a big push is going to take place in the Western theatre,
and that I "must understand that no reinforcements of importance can be
diverted from the main theatre of operations in France." Certain named
transports are carrying, he says, more troops to Egypt, and he hopes
Maxwell will be able to spare me some. If we can't get through with
these we must hang on as best we may.</p>

<p>To-day it has been up to us to try and bring home to the Higher
Direction the possible effects of trying to do two things at once; i.e.,
break through in France and break through here. We are to stand aside
for a month or so just when we have made a big gain of ground but not
the decisive watershed gain; when the Turks, despite their losses in
life, shell, trenches and terrain, are shaken only; not yet shattered.</p>

<p><person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> sees all the Allied cards--we don't. But we do know our own hand. We
know that our Navy have now come clean down on the gean side of the
fence, and have determined once for all to make no attack on their own.
We have the _feel_ of the situation in our bones and it was up to us--I
_think_ it was--to rub it in that although the British War Direction may
decree that the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location> are to hang on without further help,
indefinitely, yet sickness is not yet under their high command, nor are
the Turks.</p>

<p>So <person name="Guy_Dawnay">Dawnay</person>, who is making a name for himself as a master of plain
business diction, was told off to draft me an answer to the War Office
which should remove as many beams as possible out of their optics. He
overdid it: the whole tone of it indeed was despondent, so much so that,
as I told <person name="Walter_Braithwaite">Braithwaite</person>, a S. of S. for War getting so dark a presentment
of our prospects would be bound to begin to think it might be better to
recall the whole expedition. So I rewrote the whole thing myself:--</p>

<p>       *       *       *       *       *</p>

<p>"(No. M.F. 578). From General <person name="Ian_Hamilton">Sir Ian Hamilton</person> to Secretary of State for
War. We will endeavour to do the best possible with forces at our
disposal; we quite understand reason for your inability to send us
reinforcements necessary to bring operations to a successful conclusion,
and thank you for putting it so plainly. After the failure of the IXth
Corps to take prompt action after landing I took immediate steps to
persevere with plan in spite of absence of surprise and reinforced
northern wing with 2nd Mounted Division from Egypt and XXIXth Division
from Cape <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location>. These movements and the necessary reorganization of
the IXth Corps formations which had become very mixed took time, so that
I was not able to renew the attack until 21st August.</p>

<p>"By then enemy positions in Ratilva Valley had been immeasurably
strengthened and I was confronted with the difficulty that if I could
not drive the Turks back between <location town="Anafarta_Sagir">Anafarta Sagir</location> and Biyuk Anafarta my
new line from right of old Anzac position to sea coast North-east of
<location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay would be more than I could hold with the troops at my
disposal. It would thus be a case of giving up either Anzac Cove or
<location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay. Therefore, as a preliminary step to my fresh offensive I
determined to mass every man available against <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> which
position it was necessary for me to capture whether as a first step
towards clearing the valley, or, if this proved impossible and I was
thrown on the defensive, to secure comparative immunity from shell fire
either for <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay or Anzac Cove.</p>

<p>"<person name="Beauvoir_De_Lisle">De Lisle</person> planned the attack well. The <unit type="division">LIIIrd</unit> and the <unit type="division">LIVth</unit> Divisions
were to hold enemy from Sulajik to Kiretch Tepe Sirt, and XXIXth
Division and XIth Division were to attack <location hill="Ismail_Oglu_Tepe">Ismail Oglu Tepe</location> with two
Brigades of Xth Division and the IInd Mounted Division (5,000 rifles) in
corps reserve. I arranged that General <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> should co-operate by
swinging his left flank to Susak Kuyu and <location hill="Kaiajik_Aghala">Kaiajik Aghala</location>.</p>

<p>"The troops attacked with great dash and stormed the lower slopes of the
hill in spite of strong entrenchments, but I regret to say they were not
able to attain their objective nor even to consolidate the position
gained and yesterday found the whole line back in their original
trenches except the left of the Australians where one battalion of
Gurkhas and new Australian Battalion continue to hold Susak Kuyu.
Casualties not yet to hand, but I fear they amounted to some 6,000 in
all. This renewed failure combined with the heavy total casualties since
6th August, and the fact that sickness has been greatly on the increase
during the last fortnight has profoundly modified my position, and as
you cannot now give me further reinforcements it is only possible for me
to remain on the defensive. Naturally, I shall keep on trying to harry
the Turks by local attacks and thus keep alive the offensive spirit but
it must be stated plainly that no decisive success is to be looked for
until such time as reinforcements can be sent.</p>

<p>"The total casualties including sick since 6th August amount to 40,000,
and my total force is now only 85,000, of which the fighting strength is
68,000. The French fighting strength is about 15,000. Sick casualties
are becoming abnormal chiefly owing to troops other than late arrivals
being worn out with hardship and incessant shell fire, from which even
when in reserve they are never free. Where Anzac evacuated 100 a day
they are now evacuating 500, where Royal Naval Division evacuated 10
they are now evacuating 60. The result is that I have only some 50,000
men in the North to hold a line from the right of Anzac to the sea
North-east of <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>, a distance of 23,000 yards.</p>

<p>"When there is no serious engagement, but only daily trench fighting,
the average net wastage from sickness and war is 24 per cent. of
fighting strength per month. The Anzac Corps, the XXIXth Division and
the XLIInd Division are very tired and need a rest badly. Keeping these
conditions in view, it appears inevitable that within the next fortnight
I shall be compelled to relinquish either <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay or Anzac Cove, and
must also envisage the possibility of a still further reduction of my
front in the near future. Taking the first question of abandoning Anzac
Cove and closing to the North, <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> Bay is now netted and comparatively
secure from torpedo attack. Further, it offers certain facilities for
disembarkation in winter gales. It has, therefore, some decided
advantages but though I should be able to hold it safely at present, it
would present no facilities for further contraction of my line to meet
the future wastage of my force. On the other hand, by retiring South of
<location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> I could first hold a line <location hill="Lala_Baba">Lala Baba</location>--<location hill="Yilghin_Burnu">Yilghin Burnu</location>--Kaiajik
Aghala, and then, when normal wastage diminished my strength below this
limit I could, if necessary, withdraw into the original Anzac position.
For these reasons it must probably be <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> and not Anzac which must be
given up, though on account of its advantages as indicated above, and on
account of the moral effect of retiring, you may rely on my not
relinquishing it a single day before I am compelled.</p>

<p>"I do not wish to paint a gloomy picture. It is a simple problem of
arithmetic and measurement. On the basis of normal wastage and the
present scale of drafts my total fighting strength by the middle of
December, including the French, will be only, say, 60,000. Of this
force, a certain percentage must of necessity be resting off the
peninsula, and the remainder will only suffice to hold Cape <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> and
the original Anzac line unless, of course, the enemy collapses. Until
now, however, the Turks replace casualties promptly, although frequently
by untrained men. Also our other foe, sickness, may abate, but seeing
how tired are the bulk of my force, I doubt if it would be wise to
reckon on this."</p>

<p>At 11.15, red hot from France, there arrived in camp Byng (to command
the <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit>), <person name="Stanley_Maude">Maude</person> and <person name="Edward_Fanshawe">Fanshawe</person> (to command Divisions); also Tyrrell
and Byng's A.D.C., Sir B. Brooke, nephew of my old friend, Harry Brooke.
All three Generals remained for lunch and then the two Divisionals made
off respectively to the 11th and <unit type="infantry">13th Division</unit>s. Byng and Brooke stayed
and dined. These fellows seem pretty cheery. <person name="Stanley_Maude">Maude</person> especially full of
ardour which will, I hope, catch on.</p>

</entry>

<entry><p>_24th August, 1915. <location island="Imbros">Imbros</location> Been resolving yesterday's long cable. How
often it happens that a draft letter, if only it is well put, fixes the
mind into its grooves. My words were brighter than <person name="Guy_Dawnay">Dawnay</person>'s but the
backbone was not really me. No one knows better than myself that a great
deal more than arithmetic or measurement will be needed to make me give
ground at <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location>. The truth is, it is infinitely difficult to spur these
high folk on without frightening them; and then, if you frighten them,
you may frighten them too much. That's why cables are no substitutes for
converse.</p>

<p>To a Commander standing in my shoes, the forces of the infidels are not
one half of the battle. The wobblers sit like nightmares on my chest.
"Tell them the plain truth" cries conscience. What is the plain truth?
Where is it? Is it in <person name="Guy_Dawnay">Dawnay</person>'s draft, or is it in my message, or does it
lie stillborn in some cable unwritten? God knows--I don't! But one thing
at least is true:--to steer a course between an optimism that deprives
us of support and a pessimism that may wreck the whole enterprise, there
indeed is a Scylla and Charybdis problem, a two-horned dilemma, or
whatever words may best convey the notion of the devil.</p>

<p>The blessed cable is now lying on the well-known desk where <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> will
frown at it through his enormous spectacles. Then he calls the
Adjutant-General and tells him Hamilton must be mad as all his
formations are full to overflowing and yet he says he is 45,000 short.
Next enters the Master-General of the Ordnance with a polite bow and <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>
tells him Hamilton must be delirious as he keeps on raving for shell,
bombs, grenades although as he, Von Donop, knows well, he has been sent
more guns and explosives than any man has ever enjoyed in war.
Impossible to be so disrespectful to the Field Marshal or so
inconsiderate to their department as to reject the soft impeachment. How
easily do the great ones of this world kid themselves back into a
comfortable frame of mind! Then <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> stalks off to the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>
Committee.</p>

<p>Turns out that <person name="Charles_Cox">Cox</person> and Russell did even better than <person name="William_Birdwood">Birdwood</person> had thought
in the fighting on the 21st and the morning of the 22nd. They have
killed more Turks and the line held runs well out to the North-east and
quite a good long way to the North of <location hill="Kaiajik_Aghala">Kaiajik Aghala</location>.</p>

<p>Byng left to take over his command. <person name="Francis_Davies">Davies</person> came over from <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> and
stayed for dinner.</p>

<p>The _Imogene_ sailed in with Mails. News by wireless of German Naval
defeat in the Baltic and Italian declaration of war against Turkey.
Well, that part at least of <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person>'s aspirations has come off; we have
dragged in Italy. Now--will she send us a contingent?</p>

<p><person name="Francis_Davies">Davies</person> dined. With his ideas still framed on Western standards he puts
it forcibly, not to say ferociously, that we must, must, _must_ be given
our fair share of trench mortars, bombs and gun ammunition. Fresh from
France he watched the artillery preparation at <location peninsula="Helles">Helles</location> and (although we
had thought it rather grand) says we simply don't know what the word
bombardment means. Instead of seeing, as in the Western theatre, an
unbroken wall of flame and smoke rising above the enemy trenches about
to be stormed, here he saw a sprinkling of shells bursting at intervals
of 20 yards or so--a totally different effect. And yet the Turks are as
tough as the Germans and take as much hammering!</p>

<p>When I read the British Press, starved and yet muzzled, I feel as if I
could render my country no better service than to kill my friend the
Censor and write them one or two articles.</p>

<p>By surprise either Army can bulge in a sector of the opposing lines but,
until one Army loses its _moral_, neither Army can break through. An
engine will be found to restore marches and manoeuvres but, at this
historic moment, our tactics are at that stage. To break through, Armies
must advance some six or seven miles; otherwise they can't bag the
enemy's big guns. But, the backbone of their attack, their own guns,
can't support them when they get beyond five or six miles. The enemy
reserves come in; they come at last to a stop. A three or four mile
advance _should_ be easy enough, but, in the West, that would mean just
three or four miles of land; nothing more. But _here_, those three or
four miles--nay, two or three miles--(so ineffective in France) are an
objective in themselves; they give us the strategical hub of the
universe--Constantinople!</p>

<p>Suppose even that by paying the cost in lives we did succeed in driving
the Germans over the Rhine, still we stand to gain less than by taking
this one little peninsula! A quarter of the energy they are about to
develop for the sake of getting back a few miles of _la belle France_
could give us Asia; Africa; the Balkans; the Black Sea; the mouths of
the Danube: it would enable us to swap rifles for wheat with the
Russians; more vital still, it would tune up the hearts of the Russian
soldiery to the Anglo-Saxon pitch.</p>

<p>Victory by killing Germans is a barbarous notion and a savage method. A
thrust with small forces at a weak spot to bring the enemy to their
knees by loss of provinces, resources and prestige is an artistic idea
and a scientific stroke: the one stands for a cudgel blow, the other for
rapier play.</p>

<p>We take it for granted that we have to "push" in France and <location region="Flanders">Flanders</location>;
that we _have_ to exhaust ourselves in forcing the invaders back over
their own frontiers. Whereas, content to "hold" there, we might push
wherever else we wished.</p>

<p>I can well understand that a Frenchman should say, "Let the world go
hang provided I get back my _Patrie_, whole; undivided and at once."
Indeed, only the other day, one of the best French Generals here, after
speaking of the decisive, world-embracing consequences of a victory at
the <location straits="Dardanelles">Dardanelles</location>, went on to say, "But we ought to be in France." Seeing
my surprise he added, "Yes, I am quite illogical, I admit, but until our
nine _departements_ are freed from the Boche, world strategy and tactics
may go to the devil for me."</p>

<p>
Have been writing my weekly budget. Part of my letter to <person name="Lord_Kitchener">K.</person> harks back
to the first <location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> landing, and tries to give him a better notion of the
failure to profit by the enemy's surprise. Not that I have yet got any
very clear conception of the detail myself. No coherent narrative does,
in fact, exist. New troops, new Staff, new Generals, heavy losses, have
resulted in the confusions, gaps and contradictions still obscuring the
story of those first few days.</p>

<p>Now that I am getting more precise news about what fighting there was,
it seems clear that this great mass of young, inexperienced troops
failed simply because their leaders failed to grasp the urgency of the
time problem when they got upon the ground, although, as far as orders
and pen and ink could go, it had been made perfectly clear. But, in face
of the Turk, things wore another and more formidable shape. Had Lord
<person name="Lord_Bobs">Bobs</person> been Commander of the <unit type="corps">9th Corps</unit>; yes, just think of it! How far my
memory carries me back. Every item needed for the rapid advance: water,
ammunition, supplies and mules closely and personally checked and
counter-checked. Once the troops landed a close grip kept on the
advance. At the first sign of a check nothing keeps him from the spot.
The troops see him. In an hour they are up upon the crest.</p>

<p>So far, so good. We had not another Lord <person name="Lord_Bobs">Bobs</person> and it would not have been
reasonable of us to expect him. But when I come to the failure of the
21st, where I have a seasoning of Regulars--as well as a commander of
energy--still we do not succeed. This time, no doubt, the enemy were on
the scene in force and had done ten days' digging; the non-success, in
fact, may be traced to the loss of the element of surprise; energy, in
fact, was met by preparation. The battle had to be fought like a
manoeuvre battle and yet the enemy were ready for us, more or less,
and already fairly well entrenched. Since the morning of the 7th the
chances had been rising steadily against us. Still, even so, the lack of
precise detail baffles me almost as much as in the case of the first
<location bay="Suvla_Bay">Suvla</location> landing.</p>

</entry>
</root>